<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.
-->

<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.1//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.1/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title></title>

    <author>
      <firstname></firstname>

      <surname></surname>

      <affiliation>
        <orgname></orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

    <pubdate></pubdate>
  </articleinfo>

  <section>
    <title>File name conventions used within [[NAME]]
    distributions</title>

    <section>
      <title>File names</title>

      <para>The names given to the download files indicate what the product
      is, which platform it runs on and its version. The version indicates the
      stage of development and how stable the system should be. The file name
      format is as follows:</para>

      <literallayout>isis-[version]-[type].[file-type]</literallayout>

      <para>For example:-</para>

      <literallayout>isis-4.0.1-for-maven.zip
isis-4.0-for-ant.tar.gz
isis-4.0-libs-only-with-dependencies.jar 
isis-4.1-source.zip</literallayout>

      <para>The parts of the name are:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>version</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>See next section</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>type</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>We provide the framework in a number of ways depending on
            how you want to work with it. The <emphasis>source</emphasis> is
            the most basic and requires the most work before the framwork can
            be used. This distribution allows you to regenerate the
            distributions, but does require Maven. The source distribution is
            simply an alternative to checking the code out from the Subversion
            repository. The <emphasis>for-maven</emphasis> and
            <emphasis>for-ant</emphasis> distributions provide all the
            required files to develop and run applications using the Maven and
            Ant build tools. The maven distribution is relatively small
            download as framework libraries are downloaded by Maven only when
            you actually build an application. An alternative to complete
            package is the <emphasis>libs-only-with-dependencies</emphasis>,
            which simply provides all the classes for the framework and
            dependent libraries in a single jar file that can be added
            straight to the class path, so there is no need to unpack
            it.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>file-type</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The file type is <filename moreinfo="none">jar</filename>,
            <filename moreinfo="none">zip</filename> or <filename
            moreinfo="none">tar.gz</filename> (GNU compressed tar).</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Versions</title>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>n.n.n</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Stable release, with version number split into major, minor
            and fix components. Major versions develop upon, but do not limit
            themselves to, the previous major version. Minor versions extend
            the previous version while maintaining compatibility with them.
            Fix versions fix problems in the existing version, but do not add
            any new functionality.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>n.n-alpha-n or n.n-beta-n</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Development release are releases are relatively stable
            versions of the framework that introduce new functionality that is
            part of the development plan for the versioned release. The
            milestones precede the versioned releases, that is 4.1-alpha-1
            will be released as part of the development of 4.1. Functionality
            within the alpha or beta release for a major version is not fixed
            and may change as further development takes place.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>n.n-wip-n</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Work in progress releases are made during the development of
            the current version to exhibit a particular state of develop -
            such as new features, major changes or important bug fixes. These
            should generally be stable as they are not normally released when
            the code has known major problems.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>n.n.n-SNAPSHOT</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Snapshot releases are available from every completed build,
            and hence may not even be runnable, depending the state of
            development. These are generally a way to keep up with latest
            development without using subversion.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>
