<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.
-->

<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.1//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.1/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>A quick tutorial</title>

    <author>
      <firstname></firstname>

      <surname></surname>

      <affiliation>
        <orgname></orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

    <pubdate></pubdate>
  </articleinfo>

  <section>
    <title>A quick tutorial</title>

    <para>The getting started section aims to get you using [[NAME]] in
    just a few minutes. This part helps you get it installed and run a demo.
    The next part looks at building and modifying some example applications,
    and final part take in-depth look at how a [[NAME]] is coded.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Installing [[NAME]]</title>

      <para>Before we launch into using [[NAME]] you need to have the
      [[NAME]] binary distribution installed. This is covered in this
      section if you have not already installed it. There are other ways of
      building and running [[NAME]], but these are covered in later in
      the documentation in the <ulink url="???">main installation</ulink>
      section.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Prerequisites</title>

        <para>To build and run [[NAME]] applications for this tutorial
        you need Java version 1.5 or above, and Ant 1.7 installed on your
        machine. These can be downloaded from <ulink type=""
        url="http://java.sun.com/">http://java.sun.com/</ulink> and <ulink
        url="http://ant.apache.org/">http://ant.apache.org/</ulink>
        respectively.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Downloading the framework</title>

        <para>The latest version of the [[NAME]] framework can be
        downloaded from the downloads page of the <ulink
        url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/isis/">[[NAME]]
        Sourceforge project</ulink> as shown below. For this tutorial you
        should download the binary release (suffixed with
        <emphasis>-for-ant</emphasis>) for immediate use. (There are three
        other versions available, suffixed <emphasis>-for-maven</emphasis>,
        <emphasis>-source</emphasis>, and
        <emphasis>-libs-only-with-dependencies</emphasis>. You can ignore
        these for now.</para>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentwidth="40%" fileref="images/downloads.png"
                       format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Installation</title>

        <para>Extract the downloaded file's content into a suitable directory
        (a root directory is created upon extraction so there is no need to
        create a directory in which to install everything). As an example here
        is the compressed <emphasis>tar</emphasis> file being extracted</para>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">$ tar xzf isis-4.0-for-ant.tar.gz</programlisting>

        <para>Once expanded you should have the following directories and
        files:-</para>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">/isis-4.0
    /demos
    /docs
    /examples
    /lib
    LICENSE.TXT
    /resources
</programlisting>

        <para>Change into the [[NAME]] directory before continuing the
        tutorial</para>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">$ cd isis-4.0</programlisting>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Running the Expenses demo application</title>

      <para>The [[NAME]] distribution comes with a demonstration
      application for expenses processing i.e. for creating, submitting and
      approving expense claims. The application has only limited functionality
      - a real expenses processing application would require many more
      features - but what it has is realistic in terms of
      implementation.</para>

      <para>There are two ways in which you can run the demonstration: as a
      standalone executable, or building it and running it from within a
      development environment. This chapter covers the former approach and
      looks at how a [[NAME]] application is used, while the next chapter
      looks at building and modifying the example allowing you to browse and
      modify the source code.</para>

      <para>The files for running the demo can be found in the <filename
      moreinfo="none">demo/expenses</filename> directory, while the source
      code and build files are in the <filename
      moreinfo="none">examples/expenses</filename> directory.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Running with the Drag and Drop user interface</title>

        <para>The executable version of the Expenses demo application exists
        within the <filename class="directory"
        moreinfo="none">demos</filename> directory of the [[NAME]]
        distribution.</para>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentwidth="40%" fileref="images/explorer-files.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>

        <para>Run the batch file <filename class="directory"
        moreinfo="none">ExpensesDND.bat</filename> file either by
        double-clicking on the icon (in Windows) or using the following
        commands on the command line. In Windows the commands are</para>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">&gt; cd demos\expenses 
&gt; ExpensesDND.bat</programlisting>

        <para>while on the Mac or when using Unix/Linux they are:</para>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">$ cd demos/expenses 
$ ./ExpensesDND.sh</programlisting>

        <para>After seeing the [[NAME]] splash screen, you'll be
        presented with a Login screen:</para>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentwidth="40%" fileref="images/log-on-dnd.png"
                       format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>

        <para>Log in as 'sven' and a password of 'pass'. The application will
        then open like this:</para>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentwidth="40%" fileref="images/home-dnd.png"
                       format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>

        <para>When an application is started an application window is opened
        and the user's services are displayed on the left hand side. These
        icons typically give the user access to the domain objects held and
        used by the system, and provide a way for you to create new instances.
        Any other object that subsequently appears on the screen represents
        one of those domain objects.</para>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentwidth="40%" fileref="images/dnd-example.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>

        <para>The service and objects can be manipulated as follows:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Object actions can be invoked by
            <emphasis>right-clicking</emphasis> on an icon and selecting one
            of the options from the menu.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Service actions can be invoked by
            <emphasis>right-clicking</emphasis> on a service icon.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>To inspect an object (when only an icon is shown)
            <emphasis>double-click</emphasis> it - this typically opens up the
            object in a new window.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Objects can be dragged by
            <emphasis>click-dragging</emphasis> on an icon and dropped by
            releasing the mouse button.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Dragged objects can be dropped on to an empty object field
            (identified by the grey hole; the label to the right of the hole
            specifies what type of object can be dropped). If the object can
            be dropped into that field then it will flash green. If the object
            cannot be dropped - either because it is the wrong type or that
            specific object is disallowed for some other reason - then the
            field will flash red. Dropping an object into a field sets up that
            field, effectively associating the two objects.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Dragged objects can be dropped onto other object icons. If
            the object that you attempting to drop onto accepts that type of
            object then it will flash green. If that object does not accept
            that kind of object, or disallows that specific object, then it
            will flash red. Dropping one object onto another invokes a
            specific object action, for example: add this product to that
            order.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>To quit the application, or access other application related
            options right-click on the desktop to bring up the system
            menu.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Right-clicking</emphasis> on the border of a view
            (window or icon) will bring up the view menu, allowing the objects
            to be show in other ways.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>TODO add examples interactions for the demo</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Running with the HTML user interface</title>

        <para>To run the expenses demo with the HTML user interface, run the
        batch file <filename class="directory"
        moreinfo="none">ExpensesHTML.bat</filename> either by double-clicking
        on the icon (in Windows) or using the following commands on the
        command line. In Windows the commands are:</para>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">&gt; cd demos\expenses 
&gt; ExpensesHTML.bat</programlisting>

        <para>while on the Mac, or when using Unix/Linux, they are:</para>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">$ cd demos/expenses 
$ ./ExpensesHTML.sh</programlisting>

        <para>Allowing a few seconds for the application to start up, you then
        need to launch a browser and point it to <filename class="directory"
        moreinfo="none">http://localhost:8080/logon.app</filename> and you'll
        be presented with a Login screen.</para>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentwidth="40%" fileref="images/html-login.png"
                       format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>

        <para>Log in as 'sven' and a password of 'pass'. This will direct you
        to the start page of the application, a welcome page is displayed and
        links to the application services are shown across the top. In the
        same ways as for DND these links give the user access to the objects
        held and used by the system and provide a way to create new objects.
        Any other object that subsequently appears on the screen represents
        one of those objects.</para>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentdepth="40%" fileref="images/html-start.png"
                       format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>

        <para>For example if the <emphasis>Expense Claims</emphasis> link has
        been clicked on in the screen above and now shows the available
        service actions on the left hand side of the screen. Clicking on the
        first action brings up <emphasis>My Claims</emphasis> as shown
        below.</para>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentwidth="40%"
                       fileref="images/html-exampl-claims.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Object actions can be invoked by clicking on one of the
            options from the left hand menu.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Resource actions can be invoked by clicking on a service
            icon link in the resource bar and then clicking on a menu item
            from the left hand menu.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>As objects are created or opened they are shown as links in
            an object history beneath the resource bar (the darker grey bar
            below the banner).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Similarly the current context, i.e. the current nesting of
            actions, is shown beneath the object history (the lighter grey
            bar).</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>TODO add examples interactions for the demo</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>
