<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"file:./src/docbkx/dtd-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.
-->
<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <title><?eval ${docbkxGuideTitle}?></title>

    <subtitle><?eval ${docbkxGuideSubTitle}?></subtitle>

    <releaseinfo><?eval ${project.version}?></releaseinfo>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Dan</firstname>

        <surname>Haywood</surname>
      </author>

      <author>
        <firstname>Robert</firstname>

        <surname>Matthews</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Permission is granted to make and distribute verbatim copies of
      this manual provided that the copyright notice and this permission
      notice are preserved on all copies.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </bookinfo>

  <!-- front matter -->

  <toc></toc>

  <!-- main content -->

  <part>
    <title>Understanding Apache Isis</title>

    <partintro>
      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>
    </partintro>

    <chapter id="chp.WhatMakesUpAnIsisApp">
      <title>What makes up an Isis Application</title>

      <abstract>
        <para>The code you need to write in order to develop an Isis
        application.</para>
      </abstract>

      <para><emphasis>Apache Isis</emphasis> implements the naked objects
      pattern, and that means that it will automatically provide an
      object-oriented user interface directly from the domain objects. In this
      section we will look at that relationship in more detail, with reference
      to one of the example applications, a simple Expenses Processing
      application, available in trunk/examples/ supplied as part of the
      download. As we showed in the previous section, any domain model written
      for <emphasis>Isis</emphasis> may be run with any of the viewers - there
      is no specific coding required, and the domain model has no knowledge of
      which viewer is being used. However, each viewer will have different
      gestures or mechanisms for providing the same functionality. To
      illustrate this, we will show the same objects being accessed through
      both the DnD and the HTML viewers, side by side.</para>

      <para>The application code for the Expenses Processing example, like any
      <emphasis>Isis</emphasis> application, consists of two things: domain
      objects and services. The domain objects form the lion's share of that
      code, so we'll look at how those work first.</para>

      <para>The code for examples we will be looking at can be found in the
      directory <filename>examples/expenses/expenses-dom/src</filename> in the
      downloaded files.</para>

      <sect1>
        <title>Domain objects</title>

        <para>The domain objects are the entities - the nouns - that represent
        the application domain: employee, claim, expense item, project code,
        currency, and so forth. In the course of using the application, a user
        will view and manipulate many instances of these domain objects. To
        understand how Isis handles domain objects, we'll start by looking at
        an Employee object:</para>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata contentwidth="40%"
                         fileref="images/employee-views.png" format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>Every object presented in the user interface will have a
        corresponding Java class in the domain model - in this case it is
        <classname>org.apache.isis.example.expenses.employee.Employee</classname>.
        Below we can see the code for the <classname>Employee</classname>
        object, as presented in Eclipse, with the object's list of methods
        presented on the left hand side.</para>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata contentwidth="40%" fileref="images/employee-code.png"
                         format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>The first thing to note is that the type of the object as shown
        in the user views is derived directly from the class name in Java. The
        framework inserts spaces before capital letters, so that the class
        <classname>TemporaryEmployee</classname> would be presented to the
        user as 'Temporary Employee'. However we will see later that the name
        may be over-ridden where necessary, for example if we want the name to
        include punctuation or other characters not allowed in Java class
        names. (Note that there is a separate mechanism for dealing with
        internationalisation).</para>

        <para>Secondly, we can see that <classname>Employee</classname>
        extends <classname>AbstractDomainObject</classname> - a class provided
        within the Isis application library. This is not a requirement: your
        domain objects may be Plain Old Java Objects (POJOs) - they do not
        need to extend any class in the framework. However, extending from
        <literal moreinfo="none">AbstractDomainObject</literal> will save us
        having to write a few lines of code in each case, as we'll see
        later.</para>

        <para>Note also that in the body of the object we use 'code folding'
        (the plug-in used here is <ulink
        url="http://www.realjenius.com/platform_support">Coffee Bytes</ulink>)
        to break the object's code into regions, each typically containing one
        or more related methods that together fulfill a high-level
        responsibility of the object. This is just a coding convention, not a
        requirement.</para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Properties</title>

        <para>In both of the user views of an Employee we can see a field
        called 'Name'. Within the <classname>Employee</classname> class there
        is a <literal moreinfo="none">Name</literal> region of code, expanded
        here:</para>

        <programlisting condition="" format="linespecific">// {{ Name
    private String name;

    @MemberOrder(sequence="1")
    @Disabled
    public String getName() {
        return this.name;
    }
    public void setName(String name) {
        this.name = name;
    }
// }}</programlisting>

        <para>The <literal moreinfo="none">Name</literal> region contains a
        simple property, of type <literal moreinfo="none">String</literal>,
        defined by a <literal moreinfo="none">getName</literal> and a <literal
        moreinfo="none">setName</literal> method. This is sufficient
        information to allow the viewers to display a field containing a
        textual value. Note that if the property is to be persisted, then it
        will need both a <literal moreinfo="none">get</literal> and a <literal
        moreinfo="none">set</literal> method - per the standard JavaBeans
        convention. If you wish to display a field that is derived
        automatically from other information in the object, and do not require
        this to be persisted, then a <literal moreinfo="none">get</literal>
        alone will suffice.</para>

        <para>As with the name of the object, the field name is derived
        automatically from the name of the property - though we'll see later
        that this may be over-ridden if needed.</para>

        <para>The <literal moreinfo="none">getName</literal> has been marked
        up with two Java annotations, both defined in the Isis application
        library. Annotations allow the programmer to enrich the information
        available to the framework. On properties, any Isis annotations are
        always associated with the <literal moreinfo="none">get</literal>
        method. However, annotations are not mandatory - you can write a
        simple Isis application without using any annotations at all.</para>

        <para>By default, any property with both a <literal
        moreinfo="none">get</literal> and <literal
        moreinfo="none">set</literal> method will be editable by the user.
        <literal moreinfo="none">@Disabled</literal> tells the framework that
        this particular property may never be altered by the user (though it
        may be altered programmatically). Later we'll see how to make a
        property modifiable on certain conditions.</para>

        <para><literal moreinfo="none">@MemberOrder(sequence="1")
        </literal>tells the framework that this property should be the first
        field displayed in any view of the Employee - irrespective of where it
        is defined within the code. This ordering information has been
        observed by both the viewers.</para>

        <para>The next region of the code contains another <literal
        moreinfo="none">String</literal> property, called <literal
        moreinfo="none">UserName</literal>:</para>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">// {{ UserName field
private String userName;

@Hidden
public String getUserName() {
    return userName;
}

public void setUserName(final String variable) {
    this.userName = variable;
}
// }}</programlisting>

        <para>Note that <literal moreinfo="none">getUserName</literal> has
        been marked up with <literal moreinfo="none">@Hidden</literal>. This
        tells the framework that this property should never be shown in user
        views of the object (check this against the two user views above).
        Later on we'll see how it is possible to hide a property in certain
        circumstances.</para>

        <para>Next we'll look at the <literal
        moreinfo="none">EmailAddress</literal> region:</para>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">// {{ EmailAddress
private String emailAddress;
    
@MemberOrder(sequence = "2")
@Optional
@RegEx(validation = "(\\w+\\.)*\\w+@(\\w+\\.)+[A-Za-z]+")
public String getEmailAddress() {
    return this.emailAddress;
}
public void setEmailAddress(final String emailAddress) {
    this.emailAddress = emailAddress;
}
public void modifyEmailAddress(final String emailAddress) {
    getRecordActionService().recordFieldChange(this, "Email Address", getEmailAddress(), emailAddress);
    setEmailAddress(emailAddress);
}
public void clearEmailAddress() {
    getRecordActionService().recordFieldChange(this, "Email Address", getEmailAddress(), "EMPTY");
    setEmailAddress(null);
}
public boolean hideEmailAddress() {
    return !employeeIsCurrentUser();
}
private boolean employeeIsCurrentUser() {
    return getUserFinder().currentUserAsObject() == this;
}
// }}</programlisting>

        <para>As well as <literal moreinfo="none">@MemberOrder</literal>, this
        property is marked up with <literal
        moreinfo="none">@Optional</literal> and <literal
        moreinfo="none">@RegEx</literal> annotations. By default, all
        properties are taken to be mandatory - if the user creates or edits an
        object then they will be required to specify the contents of each
        field. <literal moreinfo="none">@Optional</literal> overrides this
        default behaviour - indicating here that the object may be saved
        without an email address.</para>

        <para><literal moreinfo="none">@RegEx</literal> is applicable only to
        <literal moreinfo="none">String</literal> properties. In this case the
        annotation specifies a Regular Expression that will be used to
        validate any value that the user types into the field. In a
        conventional architecture, this functionality would typically be found
        in the user interface code. The Isis argument is that this
        functionality should apply to any user interface that might want to
        change the property, so its proper place is in the object. <literal
        moreinfo="none">@RegEx</literal> may also be used to reformat a String
        that has been entered by the user.</para>

        <para>The two screens below show how two different viewers make use of
        the functionality in different ways. In both cases the user has typed
        in a value that does not match the RegEx specification (they have
        typed in an email address that contains a space), so the new value has
        not been accepted or saved.</para>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata contentwidth="40%"
                         fileref="images/employee-email-invalid.png"
                         format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>In addition to <literal
        moreinfo="none">getEmailAddress</literal> and <literal
        moreinfo="none">setEmailAddress</literal>, there are <literal
        moreinfo="none">modifyEmailAddress</literal>, <literal
        moreinfo="none">clearEmailAddress</literal> and <literal
        moreinfo="none">hideEmailAddress</literal> methods. Isis recognises
        the <literal moreinfo="none">modify</literal>, <literal
        moreinfo="none">clear</literal> and <literal
        moreinfo="none">hide</literal> prefixes (and a few others that we
        shall see later) as specifying additional functionality relating to
        the <literal moreinfo="none">EmailAddress</literal> property.</para>

        <para>If a property has a corresponding <literal
        moreinfo="none">modify&lt;propertyName&gt;</literal> method, then
        whenever the user modifies the field, this will be called rather than
        the <literal moreinfo="none">set</literal>. In this case the <literal
        moreinfo="none">modify</literal> method uses the <literal
        moreinfo="none">RecordActionService</literal> to record the details of
        the change, and then calls <literal
        moreinfo="none">setEmailAddress</literal> to change the value. The
        reason for adopting this pattern, rather than including the
        functionality in the <literal moreinfo="none">set</literal> itself, is
        that the <literal moreinfo="none">set</literal> will be called by the
        object store each time the object is retrieved. So we use a <literal
        moreinfo="none">modify</literal> method where we want to do something
        (such as add to a total) only when the user changes a field.</para>

        <para><literal moreinfo="none">clearEmailAddress</literal> is called,
        in a similar manner, if the user clears the contents of the field.
        Again, it is optional - added where we want to perform some logic only
        when the user clears the property. On the <literal
        moreinfo="none">UserName</literal> field we saw that <literal
        moreinfo="none">@Hidden</literal> hides a property from the user
        permanently. We may, however, want to hide fields under certain
        circumstances. The visibility of all classes, properties and methods
        may be controlled via conventional authorization techniques, based on
        the user's role(s). In rarer cases, we want to control visibility at
        an instance level. In this case, for privacy reasons we do not want
        the email address to be visible, except to that person. This is what
        the <literal moreinfo="none">hideEmailAddress()</literal>method is
        doing. If the method returns true, the field will be hidden from the
        user.</para>

        <para>Next we will look at the <literal
        moreinfo="none">NormalApprover</literal> region:</para>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">// {{ NormalApprover
    private Employee normalApprover;
    
    @MemberOrder(sequence="4")
    public Employee getNormalApprover() {
        return this.normalApprover;
    }
    public void setNormalApprover(final Employee normalAuthoriser) {
        this.normalApprover = normalAuthoriser;
    }
    public void modifyNormalApprover(final Employee normalAuthoriser) {
        getRecordActionService().recordFieldChange(this, "Normal Approver", getNormalApprover(), normalApprover);
        setNormalApprover(normalAuthoriser);
    }
    public void clearNormalApprover() {
        getRecordActionService().recordFieldChange(this, "Normal Approver", getNormalApprover(), "EMPTY");
        setNormalApprover(null);
    }
    public String validateNormalApprover(Employee newApprover) {
        return newApprover == this ? CANT_BE_APPROVER_FOR_OWN_CLAIMS: null;
    }
    public String disableNormalApprover() {
        return employeeIsCurrentUser() ? null: NOT_MODIFIABLE;
    }
    
    public static final String NOT_MODIFIABLE = "Not modifiable by current user";
    public static final String CANT_BE_APPROVER_FOR_OWN_CLAIMS = "Can't be the approver for your own claims";
// }}</programlisting>

        <para>The <literal moreinfo="none">NormalApprover</literal> property
        takes an object of type <literal moreinfo="none">Employee</literal>.
        Assuming that this field is not disabled, the user may specify an
        Employee object for this field. Isis will prevent the user from trying
        to associate the wrong type of object with this field. This is
        illustrated in the two screens below:</para>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata contentwidth="40%"
                         fileref="images/employee-approver-views.png"
                         format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>In the left-hand screen (DND) we can see the user dropping an
        Employee object into the empty field, and the field is flashing green
        to indicate that this will succeed. If the user attempted to drop
        another type of object into the empty field, then the field would
        flash red, and the drop would not update the field. A successful drop
        will call the <literal moreinfo="none">set</literal> method, or, if a
        <literal moreinfo="none">modify&lt;propertyName&gt;</literal> method
        is provided (as it is here), it will call that instead. Note that on
        the DND viewer, if a field already contains an object, then this may
        be cleared by right-clicking on that object and selecting 'Clear
        Association'. This will set the property to <literal
        moreinfo="none">null</literal>. If there is a <literal
        moreinfo="none">clear&lt;propertyName&gt;</literal> field (as there is
        in this example) then that will be called rather than the <literal
        moreinfo="none">set</literal> method. Alternatively a new reference
        can be dropped on to the field's label, which combines both the
        clearing and the subsequent setting of the field.</para>

        <para>In the HTML viewer (right-hand screen) drag and drop is not
        possible. In a reference field such as this one, the user will be
        given a drop-down list of objects of the appropriate type (i.e.
        Employees here) that the user has recently viewed. If the required
        Employee object is not in that list then the user may go and find that
        object (e.g. from the Employees tab) and then return to the context -
        this time the newly viewed Employee will have been added to the list
        automatically. (Note: This is a generic capability provided by the
        HTML viewer. In other contexts, the programmer may want to specify an
        explicit list of objects to appear in a drop-down list. This would be
        achieved by means of a <literal
        moreinfo="none">choices&lt;propertyName&gt;</literal> method).</para>

        <para>The <literal moreinfo="none">validateNormalApprover</literal>
        method enforces any rules concerning the specific instances of
        <literal moreinfo="none">Employee</literal> that may be associated
        with this field. In this particular example, it prevents the user from
        specifying an Employee as their own approver. Note that this method
        returns a <literal moreinfo="none">String</literal>. If the specific
        Employee instance being passed into the method is acceptable, the
        method should return <literal moreinfo="none">null</literal>; if
        unacceptable then the method should return a <literal
        moreinfo="none">String</literal> message that will be made available
        to the user to advise them why the action will not succeed. (On the
        DND this appears at the bottom of the screen.)</para>

        <para>The <literal moreinfo="none">disableNormalApprover</literal>
        method prevents the user from modifying the field in certain
        circumstances. In this example the method enforces the rule that only
        the Employee themselves may change this field. Like the <literal
        moreinfo="none">validate</literal> method, it returns a <literal
        moreinfo="none">null</literal> if the user may modify the field
        (subject to the validate rules), or returns a <literal
        moreinfo="none">String</literal> message if they may not. (Note that
        this method, along with hide (seen earlier) allow for 'instance-based
        authorization'. Most applications can manage with 'class-based
        authorization' - in which the classes, properties and actions made
        available to a user are based on their roles. Class-based
        authorization in Isis is administered externally to the application
        and does not require any coding within the domain objects.)</para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Title</title>

        <para>In the next screen we will look at the <literal
        moreinfo="none">title</literal> region of the Employee object.</para>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">// {{ Title
    public String title() {
        return getName();
    }
// }}</programlisting>

        <para>The <literal moreinfo="none">title</literal> method specifies
        the title for the object - which, on both the DND and HTML viewers
        appears next to the icon. The title is there to help the user identify
        objects. Isis also provides an easy mechanism to retrieve objects from
        the object store by their title. Other methods of finding/searching
        may require repository methods to be written. If no <literal
        moreinfo="none">title</literal> method is specified, Apache Isis will
        use the object's <literal moreinfo="none">toString</literal> method as
        a title. Titles are usually based on one or more of the persisted
        properties - in this case on the Name. When constructing a title from
        multiple elements, the Isis application library provides a helper
        object: <classname>TitleBuffer</classname>.</para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Actions</title>

        <para>The screen below shows the action menu for the Taxi object, as
        rendered by the two different user interfaces:</para>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata contentwidth="40%" fileref="images/taxi-menu.png"
                         format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>By default, any <literal moreinfo="none">public</literal>
        instance methods on an object, included inherited public methods, will
        be rendered as a user-action. The exceptions to this rule are:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Any methods that are recognised by Isis as having a specific
            intent. We've seen a number of these already, including <literal
            moreinfo="none">get</literal> and <literal
            moreinfo="none">set</literal> methods, <literal
            moreinfo="none">title</literal>, and the methods prefixed by
            <literal moreinfo="none">modify</literal>, <literal
            moreinfo="none">clear</literal>, <literal
            moreinfo="none">validate</literal>, <literal
            moreinfo="none">disable</literal> and so on. There is a full list
            of recognised methods included in the applib documentation.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Any methods that the programmer has specified should be
            hidden from the user, either statically with <literal
            moreinfo="none">@Hidden</literal>, or dynamically with a <literal
            moreinfo="none">hide&lt;methodName&gt;</literal> method.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para><literal moreinfo="none">private</literal>, <literal
        moreinfo="none">protected</literal>, and <literal
        moreinfo="none">static</literal> methods are ignored by Apache
        Isis.</para>

        <para>For example, the action 'Copy From' on the Taxi object, is
        derived from this method on the
        <classname>AbstractExpenseItem</classname> class (from which
        <classname>Taxi</classname> inherits):</para>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">    @MemberOrder(sequence="5")
    public void copyFrom(final ExpenseItem otherItem) {
        if (belongsToSameClaim(otherItem)) {
            if (dateIncurred == null) {
                modifyDateIncurred(otherItem.getDateIncurred());
            }
        } else if (getClass().isInstance(otherItem)) {
            copyAllSameClassFields(otherItem);
        }
    }</programlisting>

        <para>Again, we can see that the method has been marked up with
        <literal moreinfo="none">@MemberOrder</literal>, which will govern the
        relative location of this action on the action menu.</para>

        <para>Because the <literal moreinfo="none">copyFrom</literal> method
        takes a parameter, when the user invokes the corresponding menu action
        they will be presented with a dialog, wherein each of the parameters
        may be specified. This is shown below on the two user
        interfaces:</para>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata contentwidth="40%"
                         fileref="images/taxi-copy-dialog.png" format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>Editing a dialog is similar to editing an object: though there
        are differences in the way they are rendered (for example a dialog has
        an 'OK' button in both the DND and HTML user interfaces). Parameters
        that take value types (such as <classname>String</classname> or
        <classname>Date</classname>) are rendered as fields that the user can
        type into. Where a parameter is a domain object class or interface, as
        in this case with <classname>ExpenseItem</classname>, then the user
        must specify an object of that type. In the DND user interface, the
        user may drag and drop an object into the parameter field. In the HTML
        user interface, the user is automatically presented with a drop-down
        list of objects of that type that they have recently viewed. If the
        desired object doesn't appear, they may go and find the object (by
        navigating from another object, or using a find method on one of the
        start points) and then return to the dialog, where the
        recently-located object should now appear on the list.</para>

        <para>Adjacent to the <literal moreinfo="none">copyFrom</literal>
        method on <classname>AbstractExpenseItem</classname> we can also find
        the following two methods:</para>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">    public String disableCopyFrom() {
        return disabledIfLocked();
    }

    public String validateCopyFrom(final ExpenseItem otherItem) {
        if (belongsToSameClaim(otherItem) || (getClass().equals(otherItem.getClass()))) {
            return null;
        }
        return COPY_WARN;
    }
    private final static String COPY_WARN = "Cannot copy";</programlisting>

        <para><literal moreinfo="none">disableCopyFrom</literal> and <literal
        moreinfo="none">validateCopyFrom</literal> are other examples of
        recognised methods (fully documented in the applib documentation).
        They work in a similar manner to the <literal
        moreinfo="none">disable&lt;propertyName&gt;</literal> and <literal
        moreinfo="none">validate&lt;propertyName&gt;</literal> methods that we
        have previously seen - in this case disabling the action under certain
        conditions, and validating the parameters of the action. For both the
        user-interfaces shown, disabling the action will result in it being
        greyed-out on the menu. If the entered set of parameters does not pass
        the validity test, this will be brought to the user's attention when
        they attempt to execute the action (e.g. by hitting the OK button),
        along with an explanatory message.</para>

        <para>By default, the user will be required to specify each of the
        parameters within the dialog. The programmer may, however, use the
        <literal moreinfo="none">@Optional </literal>annotation in-line (i.e.
        immediately before any parameter in the method signature) to specify
        that that parameter may be left empty.</para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Defining Services</title>

        <para>As stated previously all the application code consists either of
        domain objects or services, with the former typically representing the
        lions share of the code. Now we'll look at the services.</para>

        <para>Services perform two roles in an Isis application. First, they
        provide a place to put functionality that cannot be placed on an
        instance of a domain object, of which the two most obvious examples
        are:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Finding one or more domain objects where you don't have an
            associated object to navigate from e.g. finding a Customer object
            by their name or customer number.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Creating a new instance of a domain object class, where you
            don't have an existing object to create it from. Thus, although
            you might decide that it makes sense to create a new Order object
            by means of an action on Customer, you will probably want to be
            able to create a new Customer object without necessarily having
            any Order.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>To fulfill these requirements we could create two separate
        services, called, say, CustomerFinder and CustomerFactory. Or we could
        create a single service called, say, Customers, which has methods to
        cover both requirements. There's no hard-and-fast rule about how
        services should be partitioned.</para>

        <para>The second role that services perform within an Isis application
        is to bridge domains. The following are examples of what we mean by
        bridging domains:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Linking to functionality that already exists, or has to
            exist, outside of the Isis application, such as pre-existing
            services, or functionality within legacy systems.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Bridging between technical domains, such as between the
            object domain and the relational database domain, or the email
            domain.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>(Less commonly) Bridging between isolated modelling domains.
            The Isis philosophy is to aim, where possible, for a single
            coherent enterprise object model running within the same
            application space. Where this is not possible (e.g. for technical
            or for political reasons), then services may be used to
            communicate between the domains without requiring common object
            definitions and/or identities.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>In this section we'll look at how services are defined, and in
        the next section at how they are used.</para>

        <para>Services are implemented as Java classes, as are domain objects,
        but they are handled differently by the framework.</para>

        <para>It is good practice to define services as Java interfaces. That
        way it is possible for the implementation of the service to change
        over time, without affecting any of the objects that use the service.
        During development it is often useful to develop a simple 'mock'
        implementation of a service that can be used either for prototyping or
        testing purposes; this can then be replaced with a proper
        implementation as development progresses towards deployment. For
        example, within the Expenses Processing application, the following
        Java interface defines a service for sending an email:</para>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">    package org.apache.isis.example.expenses.services;

    public interface EmailSender {

        void sendTextEmail(final String toEmailAddress, final String text);
    }</programlisting>

        <para>This service definition has just one method, but it could easily
        have more, such as methods that take a <literal
        moreinfo="none">List</literal> of recipient addresses, or that can
        accommodate file attachments. <literal
        moreinfo="none">JavaMailSender</literal> is an implementation of that
        service:</para>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">public class JavaMailSender extends AbstractService implements EmailSender {

    private static final String SMTP_HOST_NAME = "localhost";
    private static final String SMTP_AUTH_USER = "expenses@donotreply.org";
    private static final String SMTP_AUTH_PWD = "";
    private static final boolean authenticate = false;

    private class SMTPAuthenticator extends javax.mail.Authenticator {
        public PasswordAuthentication getPasswordAuthentication() {
            final String username = SMTP_AUTH_USER;
            final String password = SMTP_AUTH_PWD;
            return new PasswordAuthentication(username, password);
        }
    }

    public void sendTextEmail(final String toEmailAddress, final String text) {
        try {
            final Properties properties = new Properties();
            properties.put("mail.smtp.host", SMTP_HOST_NAME);
            properties.put("mail.smtp.auth", authenticate ? "true" : "false");
            final Authenticator authenticator = authenticate ? new SMTPAuthenticator() : null;
            final Session session = Session.getDefaultInstance(properties, authenticator);
            final Message message = new MimeMessage(session);
            final InternetAddress fromAddress = new InternetAddress(SMTP_AUTH_USER);
            final InternetAddress toAddress = new InternetAddress(toEmailAddress);
            message.setFrom(fromAddress);
            message.setRecipient(Message.RecipientType.TO, toAddress);
            message.setSubject("Expenses notification");
            message.setContent(text, "text/plain");
            Transport.send(message);
        } catch (AddressException e) {
            throw new ApplicationException("Invalid email address", e);
        } catch (MessagingException e) {
            throw new ApplicationException("Problem sending email", e);
        }
    }
}</programlisting>

        <para>We can see that this service performs a technical bridging role:
        it bridges between the object domain and an external SMTP
        server.</para>

        <para>Since there could be multiple implementations of any one service
        within our code base, Isis needs to be informed of which services it
        is to reference when running an application. This is done within the
        properties files. For example, the <filename class="directory"
        moreinfo="none">isis.properties</filename> file, which may be found
        within the <literal
        moreinfo="none">expenses.app.client\config</literal> directory,
        contains the property specification:</para>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">isis.services.prefix=org.apache.isis.example.expenses
isis.services=services.JavaMailSender</programlisting>

        <para>This specifies that the class JavaMailSender is to be referenced
        as a service within the application. You will find a list of other
        services being referenced there also. Many of those services are
        'repositories', and though there is no technical difference between a
        repository and any other kind of service, repositories play such an
        important role in Isis applications, that they are worth exploring in
        more detail.</para>

        <sect2>
          <title>Repositories</title>

          <para>Isis handles the basic object lifecycle (create, read, update,
          delete) automatically - there is no need to define your own methods
          for saving or updating objects, or for retrieving an object that you
          have a reference to. These mechanisms work the same way irrespective
          of what technology you are using to persist the objects - such as
          via Hibernate, natively to a relational database, or via the 'XML
          Object Store'.</para>

          <para>Isis even provides some simple mechanisms for searching for
          persisted objects - that also operate the same way, irrespective of
          the object store. However, a business application will also need
          more complex search queries that, for reasons of efficiency, will
          need to be written specifically for the type of object store you are
          working with.</para>

          <para>Best practice in application design suggests that such queries
          should be implemented on 'Repository' classes, rather than within
          the domain classes directly. That way if you change the persistent
          object store, you can just create a new implementation of the
          affected Repositories, without having to change any domain classes.
          Isis supports this concept. Within the Expenses application you will
          find the following three repository definitions:</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">org.apache.isis.example.expenses.claims.ClaimRepository
org.apache.isis.example.expenses.employee.EmployeeRepository;
org.apache.isis.example.expenses.recordedAction.impl.RecordedActionRepository;</programlisting>

          <para>In each case the repository is defined as a Java interface,
          anticipating the possibility of different implementations. We'll
          look at the <classname>ClaimRepository</classname>
          definition:</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">public interface ClaimRepository {
    final static int MAX_CLAIMS = 20;
    final static int MAX_ITEMS = 10;

    List&lt;Claim&gt; findClaims(final Employee employee, final ClaimStatus status, final String description);

    List&lt;Claim&gt; findRecentClaims(final Employee employee);

    boolean descriptionIsUniqueForClaimant(final Employee employee, final String initialDescription);

    List&lt;ExpenseItem&gt; findExpenseItemsLike(final ExpenseItem item);

    List&lt;Claim&gt; findClaimsAwaitingApprovalBy(Employee approver);
    
    ClaimStatus findClaimStatus(String title);

    ExpenseItemStatus findExpenseItemStatus(String title);
}</programlisting>

          <para>This interface defines some seven method signatures for
          retrieving <classname>Claim</classname>s and
          <classname>ExpenseItem</classname>s. Note that there is no hard rule
          about the scope of a single Repository - we could have decided to
          separate this into a <classname>ClaimRepository</classname> and an
          <literal moreinfo="none">ExpenseItemRepository</literal> if that
          offered us some advantage.</para>

          <para>The example application contains two concrete implementations
          of <classname>ClaimRepository</classname>:</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">org.apache.isis.example.expenses.services.inmemory.ClaimRepositoryInMemory
org.apache.isis.example.expenses.services.hibernate.ClaimRepositoryHibernate</programlisting>

          <para>The first of these is intended for use with a standalone
          prototype - with a relatively small number of object instances, all
          held in memory. So the finder methods can be written 'naively' - to
          enumerate through all the objects in a class and find the match(es).
          The following is its implementation of the
          <methodname>findClaimsAwaitingApprovalBy</methodname> method:</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">    public List&lt;Claim&gt; findClaimsAwaitingApprovalBy( final Employee approver ) {
        return allMatches(
            Claim.class, 
            new Filter() {
                public boolean accept(final Object obj) {
                    Claim claim = (Claim) obj;
                    return claim.getStatus().isSubmitted() &amp;&amp; claim.getApprover() == approver;
                }
            });
    }</programlisting>

          <para>This delegates to an <methodname>allMatches</methodname>
          method, inherited from
          <classname>AbstractFactoryAndRepository</classname>, and use a
          <classname>Filter</classname> object (created in-line) to compare to
          each instance of <classname>Claim</classname> held in memory. Such
          methods are very simple to write and debug (because they can invoke
          methods on the objects being searched, such as
          <methodname>isSubmitted</methodname> here), but they would not
          operate efficiently for large numbers of objects.</para>

          <para><classname>ClaimRepositoryHibernate</classname> is written to
          work with the Hibernate Object Store and can work efficiently at
          large scale. Here is its the
          <methodname>findClaimsAwaitingApprovalBy</methodname> method:</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">public List&lt;Claim&gt; findClaimsAwaitingApprovalBy( final Employee approver ) {
    final Criteria criteria = hibernateHelper.createCriteria(Claim.class);
    criteria.
        add(Restrictions.eq("approver", approver)).
        createCriteria("status").
        add(Restrictions.eq("titleString", ClaimStatus.SUBMITTED));
    return hibernateHelper.findByCriteria(criteria, Claim.class);
}</programlisting>

          <para>This implementation uses a <classname>Criteria</classname>
          object, a class provided by the <ulink
          url="www.hibernate.org">Hibernate</ulink> framework.</para>

          <para>Both <classname>ClaimRepositoryInMemory</classname> and
          <classname>ClaimRepositoryHibernate</classname> inherit from
          <classname>ClaimRepositoryAbstract</classname>, which inherits from
          <classname>AbstractFactoryAndRepository</classname> and also
          implements the <classname>ClaimRepository</classname> interface.
          This pattern is not a requirement - the implementations do not need
          to inherit from any framework class, they can just implement the
          required Repository interface natively. However the advantage of
          this pattern is that some simple query methods can be written
          generically, as shown in these two examples:</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">public List&lt;ExpenseItem&gt; findExpenseItemsOfType(final Employee employee, final ExpenseType type) {
    final List&lt;Claim&gt; claims = findClaims(employee, null, null);
    final List&lt;ExpenseItem&gt; items = new ArrayList&lt;ExpenseItem&gt;();
    for (final Claim claim : claims) {
        ExpenseItem pattern = (ExpenseItem) newTransientInstance((Class) type.correspondingClass());
        pattern.setClaim(claim);
        List list = (List) uniqueMatch((Class) type.correspondingClass(), pattern, EXCLUDING_SUBCLASSES);
        items.addAll(list);
    }
    return items;
}

public ClaimStatus findClaimStatus(String title) {
    return uniqueMatch(ClaimStatus.class, title, EXCLUDING_SUBCLASSES);
}</programlisting>

          <para>These two query methods both delegate to
          <methodname>uniqueMatch</methodname>, inherited from
          <classname>AbstractFactoryAndRepository</classname>, but different,
          overloaded, versions of that method.
          <methodname>findExpenseItemsOfType</methodname> invokes
          <methodname>uniqueMatch</methodname> with a pattern - an instance of
          <classname>ExpenseItem</classname> that has been set up with the
          fields where a match is required.
          <methodname>findClaimStatus</methodname> invokes
          <methodname>uniqueMatch</methodname> with a
          <classname>String</classname> representing the title of the object
          required. The implementation of both of these forms of query is
          delegated to the object store, in a manner that is transparent to
          the application programmer. So, if the nature of the query can be
          represented in the form of a find by title, or a find by pattern,
          then it is advantageous to use these methods on
          <classname>AbstractFactoryAndRepository</classname>. Otherwise you
          can write specialised methods on the respective repository
          implementations.</para>

          <para>As with all services, we need to inform the framework of the
          existence and intent of these implementations, via the properties
          files. Within <filename class="directory"
          moreinfo="none">isis.properties</filename> you will find:</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">isis.services=services.inmemory.ClaimRepositoryInMemory</programlisting>

          <para>and within <filename class="directory"
          moreinfo="none">persistor_hibernate.properties</filename> you will
          find:</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">isis.services = services.hibernate.ClaimRepositoryHibernate</programlisting>

          <para><filename class="directory"
          moreinfo="none">persistor_hibernate.properties</filename> is only
          referenced if the application is run with the Hibernate Object
          Store, in which case the framework will recognise that
          <classname>ClaimRepositoryHibernate</classname> is intended to
          replace <classname>ClaimRepositoryInMemory</classname> as the
          implementation to use.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>Factories</title>

          <para>A Factory is just the name we give to a kind of service that
          specialises in the creation of new objects, of one or more kinds. It
          is not necessary to use a Factory in order to create objects within
          Isis: we may invoke the methods
          <methodname>newTransientInstance</methodname> from within a method
          on a domain object or within any service.</para>

          <para>However, if there is a need to create a type of object from
          several different places in the application, and there are common
          steps involved, then it is good practice to delegate this to a
          Factory. Within Isis a Factory is just another service, it doesn't
          have any special status. For example, within the Expenses
          application, new <classname>Claim</classname>s and new
          <classname>ExpenseItem</classname>s are created via the
          <classname>ClaimFactory</classname>. However, new
          <classname>RecordedAction</classname>s are created in the
          <classname>RecordedActionService</classname>. Note that
          <classname>ClaimFactory</classname> is specified as a class rather
          than an interface, because we have no particular reason to
          anticipate different implementations of the factory.</para>
        </sect2>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Using services</title>

        <para>Services are used within Isis in three ways:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Injected into domain objects</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Directly accessible to the user</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>To contribute actions to domain objects</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>We'll look at these three in turn.</para>

        <sect2>
          <title>Injecting Services into domain objects</title>

          <para>Objects may need access to services, such as repositories for
          finding related objects, or for calling functionality from outside
          the domain model. Isis uses the 'dependency injection' model. Each
          object merely needs to provide a <literal
          moreinfo="none">set</literal> method for each type of service that
          it requires. For example, within the Employee object there is a code
          region labelled <literal moreinfo="none">Injected
          Services</literal>:</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">// {{ Injected Services
    // {{ Injected: RecordActionService
    private RecordActionService recordActionService;

    protected RecordActionService getRecordActionService() {
        return this.recordActionService;
    }

    public void setRecordActionService(final RecordActionService recordActionService) {
        this.recordActionService = recordActionService;
    }
    // }}

    // {{ Injected: UserFinder
    private UserFinder userFinder;

    protected UserFinder getUserFinder() {
        return this.userFinder;
    }

    public void setUserFinder(final UserFinder userFinder) {
        this.userFinder = userFinder;
    }
    // }}
// }}</programlisting>

          <para>In this case, the Employee object has specified that it
          requires two services to be injected: a <literal
          moreinfo="none">RecordActionService</literal> and a <literal
          moreinfo="none">UserFinder</literal>. Whenever an instance of
          Employee is created, or retrieved from the object store, Apache Isis
          will inject the implementation that it knows about (as specified in
          properties) for each type of service required. Note that, unlike the
          other properties we have looked at, <literal
          moreinfo="none">get</literal> methods may be <literal
          moreinfo="none">protected</literal>, because the property is not
          displayed. (Strictly speaking a <literal
          moreinfo="none">get</literal> is often not needed here - as the
          injected service may be accessed via the variable - but it is
          considered to be good practice.)</para>

          <para>From within the object we can then call any of the methods
          defined for those types of service. For example, we can see that the
          <methodname>hideEmailAddress</methodname> method makes a call (via
          <methodname>employeeIsCurrentUser</methodname>) to the
          <classname>UserFinder</classname> service:</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">public boolean hideEmailAddress() {
    return !employeeIsCurrentUser();
}

private boolean employeeIsCurrentUser() {
    return getUserFinder().currentUserAsObject() == this;
}</programlisting>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>Making services directly accessible to the user</title>

          <para>Services may be made available directly to the user. On the
          DND user interface these appear as the large icons on the desktop;
          on the HTML user interface (that is, as styled by the default CSS)
          these appear as the tabs across the top of the screen. Which
          services are made available to a particular user are defined in
          'perspectives' within a user profile. Within the Fixture project the
          class <classname>ExplorationUserProfileFixture</classname> defines
          the perspectives for various defined prototype users:</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">public class ExplorationUserProfileFixture extends UserProfileFixture {

    @Override
    protected void installProfiles() {
        ...
        Profile svenProfile = newUserProfile();
        Perspective claimsPerspective = svenProfile.newPerspective("Claims");
        claimsPerspective.addToServices(Claims.class);
        claimsPerspective.addToServices(Employees.class);
        saveForUser("sven", svenProfile);
        ...

    }
}</programlisting>

          <para>The above example specifies that the user 'sven' is to be
          given a perspective called 'Claims', which gives him direct access
          to two services: <classname>ClaimStartPoints</classname> and
          <classname>EmployeeStartPoints</classname>. If we look at the second
          of those, we can see that it defines two actions:
          <methodname>findEmployeeByName</methodname> and
          <methodname>me</methodname>:</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">  @Named("Employees")
  public class EmployeeStartPoints extends AbstractService {
      // {{ Title &amp; ID

      // {{ Injected Services

      @MemberOrder(sequence = "2")
      public List&lt;Employee&gt; findEmployeeByName(@Named("Name (or start of Name)")
      final String name) {
          List&lt;Employee&gt; results = employeeRepository.findEmployeeByName(name);
          if (results.isEmpty()) {
              warnUser("No employees found matching name: " + name);
              return null;
          }
          return results;
      }

      @Executed(Executed.Where.LOCALLY)
      public Employee me() {
          Employee me = employeeRepository.me();
          if (me == null) {
              warnUser("No Employee representing current user");
          }
          return me;
      }
  }</programlisting>

          <para>Both of these methods delegate to methods on the
          <classname>EmployeeRepository</classname>, which has been injected
          (services may be injected into other services, just as into domain
          objects). Note that it is not necessary to define specific services
          to be provided directly to the user - we could provide the user with
          direct access to the Repositories, Factories or other services
          specified within the application. Creating dedicated user-oriented
          service definitions just helps us to separate the concerns. Calling
          them 'Start Points' is also just a convention.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>Using services to contribute actions to domain
          objects</title>

          <para>The screens below show the action menu on the Claim object, as
          rendered by the two different user interfaces:</para>

          <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="center" contentwidth="40%"
                           fileref="images/claim-contributed-actions.png"
                           format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>

          <para>This menu has a sub-menu, entitled 'Recorded Actions',
          containing, in this case, a single method 'All Recorded Actions'.
          Sub-menus in Isis are 'contributed' by services; the actions in the
          sub-menus are described as 'contributed actions'. In this case the
          actions are contributed the service
          <classname>RecordedActionContributedActions</classname>:</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">  @Named("Recorded Actions")
  public class RecordedActionContributedActions extends AbstractService {

      // {{ Injected Services
 
      public List&lt;RecordedAction&gt; allRecordedActions(RecordedActionContext context) {
          return recordedActionRepository.allRecordedActions(context);
      }
  }</programlisting>

          <para>The method <methodname>allRecordedActions</methodname> takes a
          <classname>RecordedActionContext</classname> as a parameter, and
          will return all the <classname>RecordedAction</classname>s
          associated with that object. Note that
          <classname>RecordedActionContext</classname> is an interface that
          defines no methods - it is purely a type definition:</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">public interface RecordedActionContext {
}</programlisting>

          <para>However, this interface is implemented by two classes:
          <classname>Employee</classname> and <classname>Claim</classname>.
          The net result of this is that the action 'All Recorded Actions'
          will be contributed to each instance of
          <classname>Employee</classname> and of <classname>Claim</classname>.
          By default, this would appear in a sub-menu named after the service
          on which the method was defined (i.e. 'Recorded Action Contributed
          Actions'), but in this case we have used the <literal
          moreinfo="none">@Named</literal> annotation to override this and
          render the service name, and hence the sub-menu name, simply as
          'Recorded Actions'.</para>

          <para>We can also see that this method delegates its execution to
          the <classname>RecordedActionRepository</classname>, which has been
          injected as a service. You are not required to follow this pattern,
          or this naming convention. In fact, if the
          <methodname>allRecordedActions</methodname> method on
          <classname>RecordedActionRepository</classname> was not
          <classname>@Hidden</classname>, then it would have been contributed
          automatically - without the need for defining
          <classname>RecordedActionContributedActions</classname>. We have
          defined the latter purely to help convey intent and manage our code
          base.</para>

          <para>The rule is that any method defined on any service that the
          user is authorised to access (see <xref
          linkend="chp.SecurityApi" />) and is not hidden, will be contributed
          to any object of a type that features as any of the parameters to
          that method.</para>

          <para>This is a very powerful feature of Isis, but it is one that
          takes a bit of getting used to. In some respects it is a little bit
          like Aspect Oriented Programming (AOP), in that it allows an object
          effectively to inherit capabilities from several different sources.
          However, this all takes place at run-time, not at compile
          time.</para>

          <para>In a more complex application, it might well be that a domain
          object might have several contributed sub-menus, each containing
          several methods. Designing an application this way allows us to keep
          the model well partitioned. In this very simple example, it has
          allowed us to keep the part of the model concerned with recording
          actions very separate from the other parts of the model.</para>
        </sect2>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Fixtures</title>

        <para>Fixtures are used to set up objects within the code based,
        principally for use within prototyping and or testing. Isis provides
        specific support for using fixtures. The following code shows a
        fixture class that sets up one claim:</para>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">public class SvenClaim1NewStatus extends AbstractClaimFixture {
    
    public static Employee SVEN;
    public static Employee DICK;
    public static Claim SVEN_CLAIM_1;

    @Override
    public void install() {
        SVEN = EmployeeFixture.SVEN;
        DICK = EmployeeFixture.DICK;

        SVEN_CLAIM_1 =createNewClaim(SVEN, DICK, "28th Mar - Sales call, London", ProjectCodeFixture.CODE1, new Date(2007,4,3));
        Date mar28th = new Date(2007,3,28);
        addTaxi(SVEN_CLAIM_1, mar28th, null, 8.50, "Euston", "Mayfair", false);
        addMeal(SVEN_CLAIM_1, mar28th, "Lunch with client", 31.90);
        addTaxi(SVEN_CLAIM_1, mar28th, null, 11.00, "Mayfair", "City", false);
    } 
}</programlisting>

        <para>This inherits from <classname>AbstractClaimFixture</classname>,
        which provides the helper methods such as
        <methodname>createNewClaim</methodname>, and which inherits in turn
        from <classname>AbstractFixture</classname>, a class in the Isis
        application library. However, there is no need to follow this pattern:
        a fixture may be any class that has an
        <methodname>install</methodname> method.</para>

        <para>Fixtures may be composite, as we can see in this example:</para>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">public class SvenClaims_All extends AbstractClaimFixture {
    
    public SvenClaims_All() {
        addFixture(new SvenClaim1NewStatus());
        addFixture(new SvenClaim2Submitted());
        addFixture(new SvenClaim5New());
        addFixture(new SvenClaim3Returned());
        addFixture(new SvenClaim4Approved());
    }  
    
    public void install() {}
}</programlisting>

        <para>This fixture has had five other fixtures added to it. The
        <methodname>install</methodname> method is empty: Isis will
        automatically call <methodname>install</methodname> on each of the
        fixtures that has been added to this composite fixture. This pattern
        makes it easy to manage large fixtures, and multiple sets of
        (potentially overlapping) fixtures, both for prototyping and for
        testing.</para>

        <para>As with services, Isis needs to be instructed which fixtures it
        should use when running an application. This may be done in the
        properties files, for example:</para>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">isis.fixtures.prefix=org.apache.isis.example.expenses.fixtures
isis.fixtures=ExplorationPerspectiveFixture, RefdataFixture, EmployeeFixture,  SvenClaims_All</programlisting>

        <para>Note that this also specifies the
        <classname>ExplorationPerspectiveFixture</classname>, which we looked
        at earlier.</para>

        <para>Fixtures may also be specified as a command line parameter (see
        <xref linkend="sec.RuntimeLauncher" />) when launching the application
        from the command line; composite fixtures are especially handy in this
        circumstance.</para>
      </sect1>
    </chapter>
  </part>
</book>
