<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
  
         http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
         
  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.
-->
<document>
		<properties>
				<title>[[NAME]]</title>
				<author email="jruiz@exist.com">Johnny R. Ruiz III</author>
		</properties>

		<body>
				<release version="3.0.1" date="unreleased" description="Bug fixes">

						<action dev="rcmatthews" type="add">
								All types of Java collections can now be used, specifically Sets. (408)
						</action>

						<action dev="scascarini" type="add">
								Made database authenticator more configurable by moving (optional) SQL into properties
								and allowing algorithm to be switched off or changed
						</action>

						<action dev="scascarini" type="fix">
								Bug 418: Fixtures always run against PostgreSQL database - fix by checking both upper
								and lower case names for table existence.
						</action>

						<action dev="rcmatthews" type="fix">
								Currency, in expense example, was not resolving itself - added resolve calls for each
								get method.
						</action>

						<action dev="scascarini" type="fix">
								Made bounded objects in expenses DOM immutable so users cannot edit them
						</action>

						<action dev="rcmatthews" action="add">
								Replaced the TransientObjectStore with InMemoryObjectStore. This stores the POJOs rather
								than the adapters and hence work more like an persisting object store as the objects are
								retrieved from memory and adapters are created for them. This is particularly important
								when fixtures are run and the system is reset before running. (422)
						</action>

						<action dev="rcmatthews" action="fix">
								Transient border now recursively works through views checking for valid fields. (423)
						</action>

						<action dev="rcmatthews" action="fix">
								All adapters now handle the empty state consistently and with out throwing NPE. (413)
								Have reviewed and consolidated the parsing, encoding and decoding of adapter values.
						</action>

						<action dev="scascarini" action="fix">
								Bug 420 Hib OS: ConcurrentListModification in Hibernate when deployed via Tomcat (works
								okay in Jetty). Fixed by removing pre and post flush interceptors that update resolving
								state (to and from serializing).
						</action>

						<action dev="rcmatthews" action="fix">
								Blank lines are now ignored in password files, and invalid entries are flagged. (425)
						</action>

						<action dev="rcmatthews" action="fix">
								HTML page builder now has a default title so every page is guaranteed to display with a
								title. (425)
						</action>

						<action dev="rcmatthews" action="fix">
								Choices method for properties can now be lists or arrays. (426)
						</action>

						<action dev="rcmatthews" action="fix">
								Choices drop down on value fields now show the selection that was made. (426)
						</action>

						<action dev="rcmatthews" action="fix">
								Collection views, when updated, no longer remove duplicated elements. (415)
						</action>

						<action dev="rcmatthews" action="fix">
								Named parameters (using @Named) are no longer being ignored when internationalization
								decorator is used. (416)
						</action>

						<action dev="rcmatthews" action="fix">
								All removed views are now released from the view update notifier list. (407)
						</action>

						<action dev="rcmatthews" action="fix">
								Fixed hanging of DND Viewer when dropping object onto field within the top-level form
								view. (412)
						</action>

						<action dev="rcmatthews" action="fix">
								Using the back button on the browser doesn't not cause exception anymore when a link is
								selected or a task is completed. (414)
						</action>

						<action dev="rcmatthews" action="fix">
								If an reflectively called method throws a runtime exception this is now thrown on
								(rather than a ReflectionException)
						</action>

						<action dev="rcmatthews" action="fix">
								The RegEx processor now places a much better message into the regex failure exception
						</action>

						<action dev="rcmatthews" action="fix">
								Descriptions for options are changed to an empty string instead of being left as null
								(for better message concatenation).
						</action>

						<action dev="rcmatthews" action="fix">
								If a regex fails to validate a field or parameter the user is now prevented from saving
								(in HTML and DND). (111)
						</action>

						<action dev="scascarini" action="fix">
								Refactored web code to be independent of servlet implmentation classes for ASP.NET port
						</action>

						<action dev="rcmatthews" action="fix">
								Objects that are destroyed are flaged as such (with a ResolveState of DESTROYED) and any
								root views are removed from DND UI. (417)

								When actions are execute remotely, or locally and changes are passed to the server, the
								set of objects that has been disposed is passed back to the client so it can remove the
								views of the disposed objects.
						</action>

						<action dev="rcmatthews" action="fix">
								Mouse pointer was not changing to resize cursor when over a resizable view.
						</action>
				</release>

		</body>
</document>
