<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"file:./src/docbkx/dtd-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.
-->
<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <title><?eval ${docbkxGuideTitle}?></title>

    <subtitle><?eval ${docbkxGuideSubTitle}?></subtitle>

    <releaseinfo><?eval ${project.version}?></releaseinfo>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Dan</firstname>

        <surname>Haywood</surname>
      </author>

      <author>
        <firstname>Robert</firstname>

        <surname>Matthews</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Permission is granted to make and distribute verbatim copies of
      this manual provided that the copyright notice and this permission
      notice are preserved on all copies.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </bookinfo>

  <!-- front matter -->

  <toc></toc>

  <preface id="preface">
    <title>Preface</title>

    <para><emphasis>Apache Isis</emphasis> is designed to allow programmers
    rapidly develop domain-driven applications following the <ulink
    url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Naked_Objects">Naked Objects</ulink>
    pattern. It is made up of a core framework plus a number of alternate
    implementations, and supports various viewers and object stores.
    <emphasis>Apache Isis</emphasis> is hosted at the <ulink
    url="http://incubator.apache.org/isis">Apache Foundation</ulink>, and is
    licensed under <ulink
    url="http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0.html">Apache Software
    License v2</ulink>.</para>

    <para>This guide is written for programmers looking to understand how
    <emphasis>Apache Isis</emphasis> fits together, what
    <acronym>API</acronym>s it defines, what the default implementations are.
    It also explains the principles of deploying an Isis application and
    describes how to do so as a standalone application or as a webapp.</para>

    <para>It is divided into four parts:<itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Introduction</para>

          <para>This part of the guide discusses the principles and patterns
          of the framework, understanding how an Isis application works,
          getting started with the quickapp archetype, the process of
          developing Isis applications, and tips for developing with an
          <acronym>IDE</acronym></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Architecture</para>

          <para>This part of the guide discusses some of the main architecture
          elements of the framework's design, distinguishing and explaining
          the reason for the applib, the core modules, the viewers, the
          default implementations of the main APIs exposed by the core, and
          the alternative implementations of those APIs.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Core Modules</para>

          <para>This part of the guide goes through each of the modules that
          make up the core framework.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Default Implementations</para>

          <para>This part of the guide outlines the default implementations of
          the core <acronym>API</acronym>s. Note: because of its size, the
          default runtime implementation has its own additional
          documentation.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>You'll note that we <emphasis>don't</emphasis> describe how to
    actually deploy an Isis application. That's because the details depend on
    the which runtime is being used. See the relevant runtime documentation
    for details.</para>
  </preface>

  <!-- main content -->

  <part id="prt.Introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <partintro>
      <abstract>
        <para>Principles and patterns, how Isis works, the quickapp archetype,
        and a development process.</para>
      </abstract>

      <para>This part of the guide discusses the principles and patterns of
      the framework, understanding how an <emphasis>Isis</emphasis>
      application works, getting started with the quickapp archetype, the
      process of developing Isis applications, and tips for developing with an
      <acronym>IDE.</acronym></para>
    </partintro>

    <chapter id="chp.Intro">
      <title>Overview</title>

      <abstract>
        <para>What's in this guide, it's relationship to the applib
        documentation.</para>
      </abstract>

      <para><emphasis>Apache Isis</emphasis> is a full-stack open source
      application development framework, designed to let you rapidly develop
      enterprise business applications following a domain-driven philosophy.
      Developing an application in <emphasis>Isis</emphasis> is - at least
      initially - about focusing on the bit that matters to the business, the
      core domain logic.</para>

      <sect1>
        <title>What's in this Guide</title>

        <para>This guide is intended to provide a comprehensive introduction
        to the <emphasis>Apache Isis</emphasis> framework. As such, it
        describes:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>the main principles that lie behind the framework (such as
            enabling domain-driven design)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>the patterns that we have adopted to fulfil those principles
            (such as the naked objects pattern)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>the high-level architecture of the framework, including why
            there are different modules and how they fit together</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>the responsibilities of the various modules that make up the
            core framework</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>the main <acronym>API</acronym>s defined by the modules of
            the core framework</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>an overview of the default implementations of the core
            <acronym>API</acronym>s</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Reading through this guide should give you a good understanding
        as to how <emphasis>Isis</emphasis> fits together and how it can be
        extended. You'll also understand the wider "world view" for
        <emphasis>Isis</emphasis>, in terms of its principles, and its
        flexibility.</para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>What's NOT in this Guide</title>

        <para>It's also worth stating what this guide does not cover.</para>

        <sect2>
          <title>Applib Documentation</title>

          <para>While this guide should help you understand how
          <emphasis>Isis</emphasis> fits together, it won't precisely tell you
          what you should write in your application. For this, you should look
          to the applib (application library) documentation, because it is the
          applib that defines the conventions of the Isis programming model;
          in other words what code you should actually write.<footnote>
              <para>This is a slight simplification; the applib defines the
              programming conventions of the <emphasis>default</emphasis>
              programming model. As you will learn, Isis can be extended to
              support different programming models. Therefore the conventions
              your application code follows will actually depend on whether
              you have customized the programming mode or not.</para>
            </footnote></para>

          <para>You'll find that <emphasis>this</emphasis> guide (the core
          documentation) does not cover the programming model in the same sort
          of depth. Rather, it explains why we have an applib in the first
          place, and more generally covers the main principles and patterns of
          writing any <emphasis>Apache Isis</emphasis> application. It also
          goes in depth into the architecture and design of the
          framework.</para>

          <para>Put another way: the applib covers the "what", whereas this
          guide covers more of the "why" along with the underlying
          "how".</para>

          <para>Therefore, if you are starting out using
          <emphasis>Isis</emphasis> then we recommend reading both this guide
          but also the documentation for the applib.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>Alternative Implementations</title>

          <para><emphasis>Isis</emphasis> is component based, with the core
          modules defining a number of <acronym>API</acronym>s (eg for
          security and runtime). This guide also covers the default
          implementations for most of these <acronym>API</acronym>s (though
          because of its size the default runtime is covered in its own
          documentation).</para>

          <para>However, there are multiple other implementations of these
          <acronym>API</acronym>s. Each of these alternative implementations
          comes with its own documentation.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>Deployment</title>

          <para>Any application must be deployed, though the details of the
          deployment will depend upon which runtime implementations is in use.
          The documentation for each runtime implemenation (including the
          default runtime) provides details on how to deploy your application
          using that runtime.</para>
        </sect2>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Where Next?</title>

        <para>We recommend that you read through all the chapters in part 1 of
        this guide; they'll provide you with a good understanding as to the
        why's and wherefore's of <emphasis>Isis</emphasis>.</para>

        <para>If you want to just start developing with
        <emphasis>Isis</emphasis>, you should also read the applib
        documentation. You should then know enough to start developing
        <emphasis>Isis</emphasis> prototypes, and using the default
        implementations of the core module <acronym>API</acronym>s.</para>

        <para>As your application starts to mature, you will probably want to
        understand more about how <emphasis>Isis</emphasis> works in order to
        determine which alternative implementations to use. Part 3 describes
        each of the core modules, and part 4 describes the configuration and
        capabilities of the default implementations. You'll find both of these
        parts are good reference material<footnote>
            <para>They are perhaps more targetted at
            <emphasis>Isis</emphasis>' own contributors rather than
            <emphasis>Isis</emphasis> users, so feel free to skim read if you
            wish.</para>
          </footnote>, and from there you'll be in a position to evaluate
        alternative implementations.</para>

        <para>Finally, part 5 describes the basic deployment options. This is
        useful reading for principles and objectives; and will be relevant if
        you have only used default implementations or one of the basic
        viewers. More likely though you will have used an alternative
        implementations or viewer; you should therefore also read the
        deployment information in the guide relating to that
        implementation/viewer.</para>
      </sect1>
    </chapter>
  </part>

  <part id="prt.Architecture">
    <title>Architecture</title>

    <partintro>
      <abstract>
        <para>The framework's design, the applib, the core modules and
        <acronym>API</acronym>s, viewers, default and alternative
        implementations of <acronym>API</acronym>s.</para>
      </abstract>

      <para>This part of the guide discusses some of the main architecture
      elements of the framework's design, distinguishing and explaining the
      reason for the applib, the core modules, the viewers, the default
      implementations of the main <acronym>API</acronym>s exposed by the core,
      and the alternative implementations of those
      <acronym>API</acronym>s.</para>
    </partintro>

    <chapter>
      <title>Overview</title>

      <abstract>
        <para>*** yada yada</para>
      </abstract>

      <para>***</para>

      <para></para>

      <sect1>
        <title>Hexagonal Architecture</title>

        <para></para>

        <para>x-ref</para>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/HexagonalArchitectureOverview.png"
                       scale="50" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>
    </chapter>

    <chapter>
      <title>Core, Defaults, Alternatives and Viewers</title>

      <abstract>
        <para>*** Explain what each of the modules are for</para>
      </abstract>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <sect1>
        <title>Core</title>

        <para>x-ref part 2...</para>

        <para>consists of:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>common</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>test support</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>metamodel</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>progmodel</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>runtime</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>webapp</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>webserver</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Defaults</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Alternative Implementations</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Other Alternatives</title>

        <para></para>

        <sect2>
          <title>Embedded</title>

          <para></para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>Remoting</title>

          <para></para>
        </sect2>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Viewers</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>
    </chapter>

    <chapter>
      <title>Configuration</title>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <para>If you have a look at Installer#getConfigurationResources(),
      you'll see that the javadoc explains how which property files we look
      for to build up the configuration; each component's Installer adds its
      own set of property files. The implementaiton of this,
      InstallerAbstract, will indicate that the configurations xxx.properties
      and xxx_yyy.properties should be searched, where "xxx" is the installer
      type (eg "persistor") and "yyy" is the name of the implementation (eg
      "sql").</para>

      <para>Note that the type comes from the subclass of Installer for that
      module; in the case of a persistor, it'll implement
      PersistenceMechanismInstaller, where PersistenceMechanismInstaller.TYPE
      = "persistor". This "type" is also used to look for the key; and is
      done</para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>
    </chapter>

    <chapter>
      <title>Bootstrapping</title>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <para>There are two startup mechanisms provided with Isis: an Isis
      container; and a web container based on Jetty. Both are run from the
      command line and allow parameters to be specified that control its
      behaviour, determing how logging is performed, what components are
      loaded and so on.</para>

      <para>The Isis container is run using the <classname>Isis</classname>
      class from the core-runtime module.</para>

      <para>Another way to run Isis is in a independent web container like
      Tomcat or WebSphere. This process is dealt with later.</para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <sect1>
        <title>General process</title>

        <para>*** this material is probably better in the runtime module ...
        however we should have something here that describes the main concepts
        and classes.</para>

        <para></para>

        <para>The first thing that happens is the logging is set up so that
        everything can be logged. This attempts to load
        <filename>logging.properties</filename> from the
        <filename>config</filename> directory on the filesystem and if that
        cannot be found it will look for the same file in the same directory
        on the classpath. If neither of these are found then a default logging
        configuration will be programmatically installed that writes to the
        console.</para>

        <para>Now that logging is initialised the container can prepare for
        bootstrapping the system. The first task is load up all the component
        installers, which is done by the InstallerLookupDefault class. This
        reads the <filename>installer-registry.properties</filename> file from
        classpath and attempts to load each class listed. Any class not found
        is logged so it is easy to determine if a component should be
        available. Each installer simply knows how to install a component; the
        component is not loaded at this stage.</para>

        <para>Now the container knows what components are available a series
        of option handlers (<classname>OptionHandler</classname>) are
        intialise, with addtional one provided by the Isis container and web
        server subclasses. These interact with the Apache CLI library to
        provide details about the command line parameters and will lookup the
        available components so they can be listed on the command line help.
        With the handlers set up the command line is parsed using the Apache
        library. If this parse fails then the library generates a error
        message with an option summary and displays via the console and the
        startup process terminates.</para>

        <para>The last step before bootstrapping starts is to prepare the
        ground for using congfiguration properties. Configuration details are
        loaded by a <classname>ConfigurationBuilder</classname> object and
        will be subsequently placed in an immutable
        <classname>IsisConfiguration</classname> object. Immediately after
        this has been created each handler is visited so that it can, via its
        <methodname>primeConfigurationBuilder</methodname> method, add it
        properties to the builder. This way each command line option is
        converted to one or more properties of the same form as can be
        specified in the properties files, hence we only need one way to
        determine how the system is to be run.</para>

        <para>Now that the ground has been prepared it is time for the
        bootstrapping to begin. This is done via a call to the
        <methodname>bootstrapIsis</methodname> method, which is where the
        process differs for the Isis container and the web server.</para>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Loading configurations</title>

        <para>Configurations are loaded by a
        <classname>ConfigurationBuilder</classname>. The builder should
        immediately create a <classname>Configuration</classname> object, and
        then can be used to add more confiration properties to the
        configuration object, ie properties cannot be added the
        <classname>Configuration</classname> object directly. Properties can
        loaded via the <classname>ConfigurationBuilder</classname> either from
        files, via Properties object, or as key-value pairs. When files are
        loaded they can be specified, via the addConfigurationFile(file name,
        ensure loaded) method, as mandatory or optional. If mandatory then the
        file must exist.</para>

        <para>Although properties can be accessed from the
        <classname>Configuration</classname> object at any point, it should be
        remembered that the properties that it contains only include
        properties that have been loaded so far.</para>

        <para>The default property loader (ConfigurationBuilderDefault) reads
        the file <filename>isis.properties</filename> from the directory
        <filename>config</filename>. The directory can be changed by
        specifying it as the parameter of the single parameter constructor.
        This loader uses Java style property files of the form</para>

        <programlisting>name=value
name2=value2 </programlisting>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <para>Using properties specified in the configuration files is done by
        get the <classname>IsisConfiguration</classname> singleton from the
        context and using one of the lookup methods to get a value, as the
        example below shows. The <literal
        moreinfo="none">Configuration.ROOT</literal> constant provides the
        base property name ("isis."). If no value is found with the specified
        property name exists then null (or 0 or false) will be
        returned.</para>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">String formatRequired = IsisContext.getConfiguration().getString(Configuration.ROOT + "value.format.date");</programlisting>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Property naming conventions</title>

        <para>Properties used within the framework start with 'isis', which is
        available from the <literal
        moreinfo="none">Configuration.ROOT</literal> constant. Next is the
        category and optionally a component. Finally is the property name
        (which can be as many levels as needed) for the component. Examples
        are:</para>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">isis.viewer.cli.log
isis.services.prefix
isis.viewer.dnd.specification.view
isis.exploration.users
isis.viewer.html.header</programlisting>
      </sect1>
    </chapter>

    <chapter>
      <title>Facet Decorators</title>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <sect1>
        <title>Introduction</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Existing Facet Decorators</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>
    </chapter>

    <chapter>
      <title>Diagnostics</title>

      <para></para>

      <para>The NOF provides a number of tools to help resolve problems and
      debug the system. These are mainly applicable to issues within system
      code, but some of them can be useful when developing applications. The
      framework provides the following:-</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Extensive use of logging through the <ulink
          url="http://logging.apache.org/log4j/docs/">Log4j</ulink> framework,
          an open source logging framework made available as part of the
          Apache Jakarta project ;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Additional logging decorators that can be explicitly added to
          specific component to capture details about the usage of those
          components;</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>In addition, the DnD viewer provides debug views that display
      details of components and anything else that implements the
      <classname>DebugInfo</classname> interface. There is further coverage of
      this last feature in the DnD viewer's documentation.</para>

      <para></para>

      <sect1>
        <title>Logging</title>

        <para>Logging using Log4j is used throughout the NOF and the
        components the Isis Group have created and it recommended that you use
        it too. Logging allows you to look what the framework and components
        have been when you investigate a problem and help to identify what
        parts of the system where doing what before an problem arose. Often
        logging alone is enough to pin point a problem, but if not it help you
        target what to investigate.</para>

        <para>Log4j allows you to log log debug messages, information about
        the system's state, warnings and errors. These events can be displayed
        on the console, written to files, or sent out over the network for
        remote logging. These are output in a user defined format and also can
        be filtered (so only events from certain components are seen). All
        this is configured through a set of properties passed to Log4J.</para>

        <sect2>
          <title>Configuring Logging</title>

          <para>The complete options for outputting and formatting can be
          found in the relavent Log4J documentation (including the API).
          However, it crucial to smooth development of an NOF system that will
          cover some of it here. The NOF configures Log4j using properties
          files and will generally load <filename class="directory"
          moreinfo="none">log4j.properties</filename> or retrieve the
          properties from the that were loaded from <filename
          class="directory" moreinfo="none">isis.properties</filename> after
          that is loaded for framework configuration (these files need to be
          located in the working directory). If you are not using classes
          within the NOF to start the framework then how these properties are
          loaded could vary. The downside of putting the logging properities
          in the framework properties files is that there is no logging until
          it has been loaded. If this is necessary then it is better to use
          the separate properties file.</para>

          <para>The following file, or portion of a file, is a basic
          configuration for logging. It consists of two appenders and a basic
          logging configuration.</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">log4j.rootLogger=INFO, Console, File

# The console appender
log4j.appender.Console=org.apache.log4j.ConsoleAppender
log4j.appender.Console.Target=System.out
log4j.appender.Console.layout=org.apache.log4j.PatternLayout
log4j.appender.Console.layout.ConversionPattern=%-5r [%-20c{1} %-10t %-5p]  \t\t%m%n

# The exploration.log file appender
log4j.appender.File=org.apache.log4j.FileAppender
log4j.appender.File.File=exploration.log
log4j.appender.File.layout=org.apache.log4j.PatternLayout
log4j.appender.File.layout.ConversionPattern=%-4r %-5p [%t] %37c %3x - %m%n
log4j.appender.File.Append=false</programlisting>

          <para>The first line sets up logging to show events of level
          <emphasis>INFO</emphasis> and above through the
          <emphasis>Console</emphasis> and <emphasis>File</emphasis>
          appenders, which writes those events to the console and the file
          <filename class="directory"
          moreinfo="none">exploration.log</filename> respectively. The two
          blocks sepcifiy how to write to the console and the file. Other
          appenders can be used to change where the logs are written to. The
          number of appenders specified is unlimited, although there should be
          at least one. The console below (from Eclipse) shows the log. The
          file will contain the same thing although the formatting will be
          slightly different as the conversion pattern for the two appenders
          is different.</para>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/console-log.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>

          <sect3>
            <title>Logging levels</title>

            <para>The types of events that are logged can be changed. This
            determines how large the files become or how much traffic is put
            over the network, and is reflected in the amount of processing
            that needs to be done to process the events into messages that can
            be written out. Levels in order of increasing verbosity and log
            size, and is decreasing order of severity are:-</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>OFF - no logging</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>FATAL - something very serious has happened that
                requires the system to be shut down.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>ERROR - something serious has happened that might affect
                any subsequent actions.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>WARN - something has not been set up properly, or needs
                attention. Although subsequent action might function
                correctly, they might not function as expected.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>INFO - information to the developer about something that
                has taken place.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>DEBUG - detailed information for the developer.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>So in the above example to increase the logging level to
            debug change the first part of the property to
            <emphasis>DEBUG</emphasis> from <emphasis>INFO</emphasis> as
            below:</para>

            <programlisting format="linespecific">log4j.rootLogger=DEBUG, Console, File</programlisting>

            <para>Logging should almost never be set to off, but should at
            least be set to log the errors (unsing level ERROR). Whilst
            developing we recommend that you set your basic level to INFO and
            switch to DEBUG if you need to investigate something.</para>

            <para>Setting the logging level via the properties file applies
            that level at startup and cannot be changed using the properties,
            ie, that level will be used to filter all logged event while the
            system is running. If you are using the Skylark viewer, however,
            you can use the debug options to change the logging level on the
            client at any time. By using Ctrl-Shift-right-click on the desktop
            you will be shown the debug menu and see the following
            options:-</para>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="left" fileref="images/logging-debug.png"
                           format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>

            <para>The greyed-out option indicates the current level.
            Selectiing one of the other levels will change the logging to that
            level.</para>
          </sect3>

          <sect3>
            <title>Limiting logging by class</title>

            <para>As well as limiting the level of events that are logged, we
            can also specify which classes we are interested in capturing log
            events for. In Log4j events are organised by loggers, which are
            set up programmatically, but as we create a logger for each class
            we talk about classes.</para>

            <para>To change the levels of events captured according to the
            class where the log event was created we can class based
            requirements after the root logger is specified. To set a logging
            level for a class add a property in the form</para>

            <programlisting format="linespecific">log4j.logger.&lt;package to log&gt;=&lt;level for package&gt;
log4j.logger.&lt;class to log&gt;=&lt;level for class&gt;</programlisting>

            <para>Events for the specified packages or class will be logged at
            the specified level, overriding the root level set up first. So
            for example the following configuration:</para>

            <programlisting format="linespecific">log4j.rootLogger=WARN, Console

log4j.logger.org.apache.isis.object=INFO
log4j.logger.org.apache.isis.object.reflect=DEBUG
log4j.logger.org.apache.isis.object.persistence=DEBUG

log4j.logger.org.apache.isis.object.loader.ObjectLoaderImpl=OFF</programlisting>

            <para>will capture warning and errors for all classes (as defined
            by the root logger), and information messages for those classes
            whose package begins with
            <classname>org.apache.isis.object</classname>. In addition those
            classes beginning with <classname>org.apache.isis.object.reflect
            </classname>or
            <classname>org.apache.isis.object.persistence</classname> will
            have their debug events captured as well. Finally, the class
            <classname>ObjectLoader</classname> will have all of its events
            ignored.</para>

            <para>It is important to make use of this feature when using the
            Skylark viewer as it logs events about it rendering. In Java
            rendering the screen (via the
            <methodname>paint(Graphics)</methodname> method) happens very
            often and can cause the logs to be swamped with superflous events.
            The logger for these events are prepended with the text 'ui.' so
            we can disable all of these events across all the viewing classes
            by adding the following to the properties:</para>

            <programlisting format="linespecific">log4j.logger.ui=OFF</programlisting>
          </sect3>

          <sect3>
            <title>Writing XML log files</title>

            <para>By writing out the logs to a file in XML rather than as text
            allows you to look at the log using Chainsaw, a Log4j viewer. This
            tool allows you to quickly look at events in specific classes and
            hide events that are of no interest by setting up simple
            conditions.</para>

            <para>To write out an XML file the same appender as before is
            used, but the layout is changed. The following configuration logs
            all events (DEBUG and greater) to a file with an XML
            layout.</para>

            <programlisting format="linespecific">log4j.rootLogger=DEBUG, XmlFile

log4j.appender.XmlFile=org.apache.log4j.FileAppender
log4j.appender.XmlFile.file=isis.log.xml
log4j.appender.XmlFile.layout=org.apache.log4j.xml.XMLLayout
log4j.appender.XmlFile.append=false</programlisting>
          </sect3>

          <sect3>
            <title>Writing HTML log files</title>

            <para>HTML files can be viewed in a web browser and will display
            nicely in most email clients. Change the appender to use the
            <classname>HTMLLayout</classname> class.</para>

            <programlisting format="linespecific">log4j.appender.Snapshot.layout=org.apache.log4j.HTMLLayout</programlisting>
          </sect3>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>Snapshot appenders</title>

          <para>The NOF provides a number of appenders that create a snapshot
          of the recently logged events instead of capturing all events since
          the system started. The benefits here are twofold. First, writing to
          the appenders is minimised as they are only written when errors
          occur or the user demands it. Second, the partial log can be
          automatically sent over the network to someone who needs to know
          when things have gone wrong.</para>

          <para>All the snapshot appends support the same basic
          properties:-</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis> <methodname>addInfo</methodname>
              </emphasis></para>

              <para>(boolean) indicates whether to prepend details about the
              machine, os and Java to log, eg</para>

              <programlisting format="linespecific">Snapshot:- Thu Dec 01 14:34:24 GMT 2005
  R Matthews
  Windows XP (x86) 5.1
  Java HotSpot(TM) Client VM 1.4.2_04-b05
  Version  000000</programlisting>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis> <methodname>bufferSize</methodname>
              </emphasis></para>

              <para>(integer) the number of events to write out to the
              snapshot. Defaults to 512 events.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis> <methodname>locationInfo</methodname>
              </emphasis></para>

              <para>(boolean) whether to capture the details of where in the
              code the event was generated. Note - capturing this information
              can be quite expensive.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis> <methodname>evaluatorClass</methodname>
              </emphasis></para>

              <para>(<classname>org.apache.log4j.spi.TriggeringEventEvaluator</classname>)
              a trigger that determines when a snapshot should be created. The
              trigger object is given each event that is logged and flags when
              to produce a snapsho.</para>

              <para>When not trigger is specified a default trigger is applied
              that triggers a snapshot when an event of level ERROR or FATAL
              occurs.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <sect3>
            <title>File snapshot appender</title>

            <para>The <classname>FileSnapshotAppender</classname> writes the
            snapshot to timestamped file. The following properties can be
            specified:-</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis><methodname>directory</methodname></emphasis></para>

                <para>The directory path where the files are to be created. If
                none is specified then the working directory will be
                used.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis><methodname>extension</methodname></emphasis></para>

                <para>The extension type to append to the file name.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis><methodname>fileName</methodname></emphasis></para>

                <para>The base name of the log file, which will have timestamp
                appended. Defaults to 'log-snapshot-'.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>The following example writes xml snapshots to the logs
            directory to files ending with '.xml'.</para>

            <programlisting format="linespecific">log4j.appender.Snapshot=org.apache.isis.utility.logging.FileSnapshotAppender
log4j.appender.Snapshot.bufferSize=1024
log4j.appender.Snapshot.addInfo=true
log4j.appender.Snapshot.locationInfo=true
log4j.appender.Snapshot.directory=logs
log4j.appender.Snapshot.extension=xml
log4j.appender.Snapshot.layout=org.apache.log4j.xml.XMLLayout</programlisting>
          </sect3>

          <sect3>
            <title>Popup snapshot appender</title>

            <para>The <classname>PopupSnapshotAppender</classname> displays a
            popup dialog showing the snapshot.</para>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="left" fileref="images/popup-snapshot.png"
                           format="PNG" width="12.5cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>

            <para>Do not use this on a server as there will be no one sitting
            in front of it to see it. It has no properties so its
            configuration is short.</para>

            <programlisting format="linespecific">log4j.appender.Popup=org.apache.isis.utility.logging.PopupSnapshotAppender
log4j.appender.Popup.layout=org.apache.log4j.PatternLayout
log4j.appender.Popup.layout.ConversionPattern=%-5r [%-20c{1} %-10t %-5p]  %m%n
</programlisting>
          </sect3>

          <sect3>
            <title>Email snapshot appender</title>

            <para>The <classname>SmtpSnapshotAppender</classname> generates an
            email with the snapshot in it and sends it to a specified
            recipient. The following properties can be specified:-</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis><methodname>server</methodname></emphasis></para>

                <para>Address of the email server</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis><methodname>port</methodname></emphasis></para>

                <para>The port the server listen on for SMTP requests.
                Defaults to port 25.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis><methodname>recipient</methodname></emphasis></para>

                <para>Email address to send the snapshot to.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis><methodname>domain</methodname></emphasis></para>

                <para>The address that client connects to the server with.
                Some email servers validate the sender's address in the MAIL
                FROM command so you may need to specify a real address
                here.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>The following example sends a short HTML snapshot logs to
            logs@support.acme.com, via the email server at my.emailserver.com
            using port 25.</para>

            <programlisting format="linespecific">log4j.appender.EmailSnapshot=org.apache.isis.utility.logging.SmtpSnapshotAppender
log4j.appender.EmailSnapshot.bufferSize=50
log4j.appender.EmailSnapshot.addInfo=true
log4j.appender.EmailSnapshot.server=my.emailserver.com
log4j.appender.EmailSnapshot.port=25
log4j.appender.EmailSnapshot.recipient=logs@support.acme.com
log4j.appender.EmailSnapshot.layout=org.apache.log4j.HTMLLayout</programlisting>
          </sect3>

          <sect3>
            <title>Socket snapshot appender</title>

            <para>The <classname>SocketSnapshotAppender</classname>
            establishes a socket connection to a server and passes across the
            the snapshot. This is designed to be used with
            <classname>SnapshotServer</classname>, which collects collects
            snapshots from multiple clients.</para>

            <para>The following example sends an XML snapshot to a server on a
            private network.</para>

            <programlisting format="linespecific">log4j.appender.SocketSnapshot=org.apache.isis.utility.logging.SocketSnapshotAppender
log4j.appender.SocketSnapshot.bufferSize=1024
log4j.appender.SocketSnapshot.addInfo=true
log4j.appender.SocketSnapshot.server=191.168.1.1
log4j.appender.SocketSnapshot.port=12345
log4j.appender.SocketSnapshot.layout=org.apache.log4j.xml.XMLLayout</programlisting>

            <para>The snaphot server should be directed to a maching running
            the server. The server is run using the following command:</para>

            <screen format="linespecific">java -cp isis.jar org.apache.isis.utility.logging.SnapshotServer</screen>

            <para></para>

            <para>The server needs a properties file with the following
            properties defined (with the prefix
            <methodname>isis.snapshotserver.</methodname>):-</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis><methodname>server</methodname></emphasis></para>

                <para>Address of the server.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis><methodname>port</methodname></emphasis></para>

                <para>The port the server listens on for logging requests.
                Defaults to port 9289.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis><methodname>directory</methodname></emphasis></para>

                <para>The directory path where the transferred files are to be
                saved. If none is specified then the working directory will be
                used.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis><methodname>fileName</methodname></emphasis></para>

                <para>The base name of the log file, which will have timestamp
                appended. Defaults to 'log-snapshot-'.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis><methodname>extension</methodname></emphasis></para>

                <para>The extension type to append to the file name.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>An example configuration would be:-</para>

            <programlisting format="linespecific">isis.snapshotserver.port=12345
isis.snapshotserver.directory=logs
isis.snapshotserver.filename=log
isis.snapshotserver.extension=xml</programlisting>
          </sect3>

          <sect3>
            <title>Web snapshot appender</title>

            <para>The <classname>WebSnapshotAppender</classname> sends the
            snapshot to a web server. The following properties can be
            specified:-</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis><methodname>url</methodname></emphasis></para>

                <para>URL of server to post data to (including the protocol
                'http').</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis><methodname>proxyAddress</methodname></emphasis></para>

                <para>Address of web proxy if one is being used.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis><methodname>proxyPort</methodname></emphasis></para>

                <para>Port of proxy server.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>The following example sends a default length snapshot to the
            webserver.</para>

            <programlisting format="linespecific">log4j.appender.Remote=org.apache.isis.utility.logging.WebSnapshotAppender
log4j.appender.Remote.addInfo=true
log4j.appender.Remote.locationInfo=true
log4j.appender.Remote.url=http://192.168.1.3/support/test.php
log4j.appender.Remote.layout=org.apache.log4j.HTMLLayout</programlisting>

            <para>This appender use the HTTP POST method to upload the data.
            It passes up a message and the snapshot as two parameters to the
            request: <varname>error</varname> and
            <varname>trace</varname>.</para>
          </sect3>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>Using logging to get help</title>

          <para>When you are working with someone else it is often useful to
          send details of what is happening including screenshots, code, and
          logs. To make the other person's life easier provide as much
          information as possible:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Detail the version of the framework and the platform (Java
              or .Net) you are using</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Describe the problem in detail</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Provide screenshots (as a <filename class="directory"
              moreinfo="none">.gif</filename> or <filename class="directory"
              moreinfo="none">.png</filename>, avoid jpegs and Word documents)
              that shows the problem</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Provide log files from both the client and the server in
              an XML format so they can be viewed using Chainsaw</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Include your contact details, preferrably you email
              address</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>Collate all this information ensuring each file is clearly
          named. Then zip up (or tar) the whole set (as the logs, in
          particular, can be huge) and email the compressed file.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>Adding logging to your code</title>

          <para>It is recommended that you also add logging to your code,
          particularly if you are developing a component or extending the
          framework in some way. This way you will be able to see the
          interaction of your classes with those of the NOF. The following
          lays out how the framework uses Log4j, and hence how you should use
          it to be consistent.</para>

          <para>Simple ensure that any class that does any logging makes a
          <classname>Logger</classname> available. By convention the name is
          always <varname>LOG</varname>. The name of the logger should be the
          name of the class in its fully qualified form. To make this easy use
          the constructor that takes a <classname>Class</classname> object and
          pass in your class using as shown here. Don't forget to add an
          import to <classname>org.apache.log4j.Logger</classname>, not the
          class of the same name in the NOF or in Java itself.</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">private final static Logger LOG = Logger.getLogger(IsisClass.class);</programlisting>

          <para>Where you wish to add log message add a statement like the
          following, deciding first what level the event should be classified
          as (see above); the available methods are
          <methodname>debug</methodname>, <methodname>info</methodname>,
          <methodname>warn</methodname>, <methodname>error</methodname> and
          <methodname>fatal</methodname>.</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">LOG.debug("mark as dirty " + object);

LOG.error("failed to create instance of " + this, e);</programlisting>

          <para>The first statement in this example contains just a message,
          while the second version logs a message and, separately, the
          complete stack trace.</para>

          <sect3>
            <title>Making you classes useful in logs</title>

            <para>To make the most of logging, even if you don't log anything
            in you code, make sure that you declare a
            <methodname>toString</methodname> method in each of you classes.
            This way when a log message is created that references your object
            the message will show your object in detail rather than like
            this:</para>

            <screen format="linespecific">MyObject@33D4</screen>

            <para>A suitable toString can cause it to be rendered more
            usefully such as:</para>

            <screen format="linespecific">MyObject [name=windows,size=34x20]</screen>
          </sect3>
        </sect2>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Component loggers</title>

        <para>The NOF provides a set of component loggers that specifically
        log the use of a component, adding additional log messages to the
        Log4j log or write out to a separate file. Additional logger can also
        be defined for other components. These logger are designed to log the
        parameters passed to and the the results return from the requests to a
        component and tend to be more verbose than the general logging just
        discussed. At present the following components have loggers
        available:-</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The object persistor -
            <classname>ObjectPersistorLogger</classname></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The object store -
            <classname>ObjectStoreLogger</classname></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The distibution interface -
            <classname>DistributionLogger</classname></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>To set up a logger create an instance of it passing in the
        object you are logging. Then use the logger instance in place of the
        original component. The constructors for each of the loggers are
        overloaded so they take a component to decorate and possibly a file
        name. If the filename is specified then the logging is done to that
        file. If there is no file name then the events are logged via Log4j.
        For example the object store persistor would logged by
        replacing:</para>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">ObjectAdapterPersistor persistor = new ObjectStorePersistor();
isis.setObjectPersistor(persistor);</programlisting>

        <para>with this, which will log request to the persistor the <filename
        class="directory" moreinfo="none">sever-persistor.log</filename>
        file:</para>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">ObjectAdapterPersistor persistor = new ObjectStorePersistor();
persistor = new ObjectManagerLogger(persistor, "server-persistor.log");
isis.setObjectPersistor(persistor);</programlisting>

        <para>Please note that the log files, when used, are created when the
        logger is instantiated and will overwrite any exsiting file. This is
        not normally a problem as we are interested in the activities during
        an entire session. However on a stateless server where the component
        is being recreated each time the continual recreation of the file
        could be a problem.</para>

        <sect2>
          <title>Defining a logger</title>

          <para>To define a logger extend the Logger class, providing a
          suitable constructor, and implement the
          <methodname>getDecoratedClass</methodname> so it passes back the
          <classname>Class</classname> object of the class being decorated
          (this allows the Log4j logger to log messages as that class rather
          than as a separate class). Within the subclass you can use the
          following methods:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis> <methodname>void log(String
              message)</methodname> </emphasis></para>

              <para>output a log entry with the specified message.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis> <methodname>void log(String message, Object
              result)</methodname> </emphasis></para>

              <para>output a log entry with the specified message and the
              specified result. This is useful when needing to show both the
              entry and exit states, or the paramters and the return
              value.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis> <methodname>void close()</methodname>
              </emphasis></para>

              <para>closes the file that is being written to.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect2>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Writing code to help investigate problems</title>

        <sect2>
          <title>The Dump Utility</title>

          <para>The <classname>org.apache.isis.object.Dump</classname> class
          provides a simple way out outputting the details of adapters and
          specifications. The two <methodname>specification
          </methodname>methods detail the specified
          <classname>ObjectSpecification</classname> as follows:-</para>

          <screen format="linespecific">Full Name: bom.Location
Short Name: Location
Plural Name: Locations
Singular Name: Location

Abstract: false
Lookup: false
Object: true
Value: false
Persistable: User Persistable
Superclass: java.lang.Object
Subclasses: empty
Interfaces: bom.Common
Fields
    OneToOneAssociationImpl@1408a92 [type=VALUE,id=type,label='Type',derived=false,type=Option]
    :
    :</screen>

          <para>The two <methodname>object</methodname> methods detail the
          specified <classname>Isis</classname> object as follows:-</para>

          <screen format="linespecific">Specification: bom.Location
Class: bom.Location
Adapter: org.apache.isis.object.defaults.PojoAdapter
Hash: #dada24
Title: test, Fort Worth
Object: bom.Location@18e4327
OID: OID#2F
State: ResolveState@1e1be92 [name=Resolved,code=PR]
Version: LongNumberVersion#1 20051118-025400170
Icon: null
Persistable: User Persistable</screen>

          <para>The two <methodname>graph</methodname> methods detail the
          specified <classname>Isis</classname> object as follows, showing
          each adapter, it associated objects and values:-</para>

          <screen format="linespecific">PojoAdapter@dada24 [PR:OID#2F,specification=Location,version=LongNumberVersion#1 20051118-025400...
    +--type: POJO BusinessValueAdapter: One
    +--knownas: POJO TextStringAdapter: test
    +--streetaddress: POJO TextStringAdapter: address
    +--city: PojoAdapter@b51404 [PR:OID#C,specification=City,version=LongNumberVersion#1 ...
    |    +--name: POJO TextStringAdapter: Fort Worth
    +--customer: PojoAdapter@92dcdb [PR:OID#1C,specification=Customer,version=LongNumberVers...
    |    +--firstname: POJO TextStringAdapter: Richard
    |    +--lastname: POJO TextStringAdapter: Pawson
    |    +--phonenumbers: VectorCollectionAdapter@1d381d2 [PR:-,specification=Vector,version=...
    : 
    :</screen>
        </sect2>
      </sect1>
    </chapter>
  </part>

  <part id="prt.CoreModules">
    <title>Core Modules</title>

    <partintro>
      <abstract>
        <para>The modules that make up the core framework.</para>
      </abstract>

      <para>This part of the guide goes through each of the modules that make
      up the core framework.</para>
    </partintro>

    <chapter>
      <title>Test Support</title>

      <para>The testsupport module holds helper classes to support writing
      unit tests in either JUnit or JMock.</para>

      <para>It should only ever be added as a dependency with a scope of
      test.</para>

      <para></para>
    </chapter>

    <chapter>
      <title>Common</title>

      <abstract>
        <para>***</para>
      </abstract>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <sect1>
        <title></title>

        <para></para>

        <para>The core commons module provides a set of common utilities and
        language extensions for use across the rest of the framework.</para>

        <para>It also defines a number of small APIs that are used
        throughout:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>a set of interfaces for defining Components and their
            scope</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>a debug framework</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>an Ensure API</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>a set of Hamcrest Matchers</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>a ResourceStream API</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>a Future API</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>an Encoding API</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>a Configuration Builder API</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>definition of an AuthenticationSession</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <para>Package dependencies:</para>

        <para></para>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/common/composition-perspective.png"
                       scale="60" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <para>Architecture layering:</para>

        <para></para>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/common/architecture-perspective.png"
                       scale="60" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Scopes</title>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/architecture.gif" scale="30" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Encoding</title>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/common/encoding-classdiagram.png"
                       scale="30" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>
    </chapter>

    <chapter>
      <title>MetaModel</title>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <sect1>
        <title></title>

        <para></para>

        <para>The core metamodel module defines the interfaces and classes
        that make up the Apache Isis metamodel. The metamodel is used in
        numerous ways, including:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>by viewers to obtain information about the domain objects,
            so that they can be rendered in a generic object-oriented user
            interface;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>by object stores (the default and some of the alternatives)
            to determine which data is to be persisted;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>by remoting, to marshall domain objects automatically
            between different tiers;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>by the core runtime, to provide the ability to provide XML
            Snapshots (through the <classname>XmlSnapshot</classname> utility
            class). The metamodel module does not itself define the
            programming model conventions; that is the responsibility of the
            core progmodel.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Architecture Diagram</title>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Top-level Architecture Diagram with SpecLoader
          expanded</screeninfo>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/metamodel/architecture-diagram-top-level-with-specloader-expanded.png"
                         scale="60" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para></para>

        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Composition Diagram</screeninfo>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/metamodel/composition-diagram-top-level.png"
                         scale="60" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>ObjectAdapter and ObjectSpecification</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>ObjectMember hierarchy</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>FacetedMethod</title>

        <para>aka ObjectMemberPeer</para>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Similarity between Properties and Parameters</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Oid</title>

        <para></para>

        <para>An Oid is an object identifier, assigned by the runtime. For
        persisted objects it is value is assigned by the object store, but for
        transient objects the framework still assigns an Oid also (and will
        update the Oid if the object is persisted).</para>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>FacetFactory</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>MethodFilteringFacetFactory</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>MethodPrefixBasedFacetFactory</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>PropertyOrCollectionIdentifyingFacetFactory</title>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>InteractionAdvisor</title>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <sect2>
          <title>HidingInteractionAdvisor</title>

          <para></para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>DisablingInteractionAdvisor</title>

          <para></para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>ValidatingInteractionAdvisor</title>

          <para></para>
        </sect2>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>RuntimeContext</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>PropertyOrCollectionIdentifyingFacetFactory</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Reflector Properties</title>

        <sect2>
          <title>FacetDecorator</title>

          <para></para>

          <para>*** gonna try to get rid of.</para>

          <para></para>

          <para>The reflector facet-decorators property specifies a list of
          <classname>FacetDecoratorInstaller</classname> objects that should
          be installed and registered with the reflector. These decorators
          decorate specific facets of the metamodel, allowing it change or
          modify their behaviour. This allows us to add internationalization,
          help look up and other features. Although transaction management is
          also achieved by decorating the reflector this is done automatically
          and does not need to be specified using this property. The following
          example adds a single decorator that provide internationalization
          via resource files.</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">isis.reflector.facet-decorators=resource-i18n</programlisting>

          <para></para>

          <para></para>

          <para></para>
        </sect2>
      </sect1>

      <sect1 id="i18n-files" label="">
        <title>Internationalization resource files</title>

        <sect2>
          <title>Files</title>

          <para>Translated names, descriptions and help text for a specific
          language should be held in a file named in the following
          format:</para>

          <screen format="linespecific">i18n_&lt;language code&gt;_&lt;country code&gt;.properties</screen>

          <para>The language and country codes must reflect the translated
          language are ISO standards and are detailed in the <link
          linkend="locale">Locale section</link>.</para>

          <para>Theses files must be on the root of the class path, otherwise
          they cannot be loaded.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>Properties</title>

          <para>Each property can have a line for each of the name,
          description and help text. The format for each is shown
          below.</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">&lt;fully qualified class name&gt;.property.&lt;property name&gt;.name=&lt;translated name&gt;
&lt;fully qualified class name&gt;.property.&lt;property name&gt;.description=&lt;translated description&gt;
&lt;fully qualified class name&gt;.property.&lt;property name&gt;.help=&lt;translated help&gt;</programlisting>

          <para>The class name must be fully qualified and the property name
          is the short name provided by the reflector. All the values are case
          sensitive. The following shows the translated name and description
          being specified for the property <emphasis>fullName</emphasis>,
          which is defined by the <methodname>getFullName</methodname>
          method.</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">example.dom.Contact.property.fullName.name=Nom
example.dom.Contact.property.fullName.description=Le nom complet du client</programlisting>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>Collections</title>

          <para><remark>TODO: presumably i18n is supported for collections,
          too?</remark></para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>Actions</title>

          <para>Actions are specified in a similar fashion to properties but
          with the keyword <emphasis>action</emphasis> instead of
          <emphasis>property</emphasis>. Parameters within an action can also
          be translated by inserting <emphasis>parameter</emphasis> and a
          number before the keyword. Each parameter must be numbered to show
          its position, starting from one (1), eg
          <emphasis>parameter1</emphasis>, <emphasis>parameter2</emphasis>
          etc.</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">&lt;fully qualified class name&gt;.action.&lt;action name&gt;.name=&lt;translated name&gt;
&lt;fully qualified class name&gt;.action.&lt;action name&gt;.description=&lt;translated description&gt;
&lt;fully qualified class name&gt;.action.&lt;action name&gt;.help=&lt;translated help&gt;

&lt;fully qualified class name&gt;.action.&lt;action name&gt;.parameter&lt;index&gt;.name=&lt;translated name&gt;
&lt;fully qualified class name&gt;.action.&lt;action name&gt;.parameter&lt;index&gt;.description=&lt;translated description&gt;
&lt;fully qualified class name&gt;.action.&lt;action name&gt;.parameter&lt;index&gt;.help=&lt;translated help&gt;</programlisting>

          <para>The class name must be fully qualified and the action name is
          the short name provided by the reflector. All the values are case
          sensitive. The following shows the translated action name and
          description, and two parameter names being specified for the action
          <emphasis>createPhone</emphasis>, which is defined by the
          <methodname>createPhone</methodname> method.</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">example.dom.Contact.action.createPhone.name=Nouveau tlphone
example.dom.Contact.action.createPhone.parameter1.name=Indicatif de zone
example.dom.Contact.action.createPhone.parameter2.name=Nombre
example.dom.Contact.action.createPhone.description=Crez un nouveau tlphone et ajoutez-le au contact actuel</programlisting>

          <para></para>
        </sect2>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Using the reflector</title>

        <para></para>

        <para>When the framework starts up it is told about the service
        objects that are provided by DOM and any referenced class is then
        introspected to build up the model of the known domain objects. Any
        other domain classes that are subsequently used will also be reflected
        upon as they are used (this will happen when there are classes that
        have no direct references from the service objects, typically because
        the references are for abstract types and not concrete ones). With the
        model in place clients can then determine how to interact with the
        domain model. Each domain class that is in use by the framework has a
        corresponding <classname>ObjectSpecification</classname> detailing the
        properties and structure of the domain class. Properties include the
        classes variouse names (full, short, singular and plural names), a
        description and flags indicating various features. The structure of
        the object includes related classes (superclass, subclasses and
        implemented interfaces), properties and actions. In additions to these
        common elements there are also a set of <classname>Facet</classname>s
        associated with each specification that provide additional information
        about and behaviour for the class.</para>

        <para></para>

        <remark>Classes: MemberIdentifier</remark>

        <sect2>
          <title>Specifications</title>

          <para>The specification is typically got from an adapted domain
          object via the
          <methodname>ObjectAdapter.getSpecification()</methodname> method,
          but can also be looked up via the
          <emphasis>ObjectReflector.loadSpecification()</emphasis> method (for
          a class object or class name) as follows</para>

          <programlisting>ObjectSpecification spec;
spec = IsisContext.getReflector().loadSpecification(Book.class);
String screenName = spec.getSingularName();</programlisting>

          <para></para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>Properties</title>

          <para></para>

          <formalpara>
            <title></title>

            <para></para>
          </formalpara>

          <para>From the specification an array of every available property
          can be access via the <methodname>getProperties()</methodname>
          method and an individual property can be accessed via the
          <methodname>getProperty(String)</methodname> method, where the sole
          parameter is the the identifier of the property. For the included
          introspector the property identifier will be the name of the
          property method with the <emphasis>get</emphasis> prefix removed,
          and the first character of the remaining string converted to
          lowercase, so <methodname>getCustomerId()</methodname> become
          <emphasis>customerId</emphasis>. Typically the complete list of
          properties is used for things like persistence and remoting, user
          interfaces need to consider what properties they show to avoid
          making hidden or unauthorised properties visible.</para>

          <para>To gather a selective set of properties for a specification
          you can use the .... method.</para>

          <para>All properties detailed are as
          <classname>ObjectAssociation</classname> objects, specifically
          <classname>OneToOneAssociation</classname> and
          <classname>OneToManyAssociation</classname> for value and reference
          objects and collections respectively. Each association object knows
          what type it for (<methodname>getSpecification()</methodname>), can
          provide its name, description and help text, determine whether it
          should be visible and useable, provides various flags indicating its
          usage and provides access to the facets that exist a the property
          level.</para>

          <programlisting>ObjectAssociation[] properties = spec.getProperties();
for (int i = 0; i &lt; properties.length; i++) {
    String name = properties[i].getName();
    boolean mustEnter = properties[i].isMandatory();
    :
    :
}</programlisting>

          <para>To selectively get hold of properties the
          <methodname>getProperties(ObjectAssociationFilter)</methodname>
          method should be used. The
          <classname>ObjectAssociationFilter</classname> class allows us to
          set up a search filter to get properties based on name, type, facet
          etc. Predefined instances and factory methods are available from the
          <classname>Filters</classname> and
          <classname>DynamicFilters</classname> classes or you can extend the
          <classname>ObjectAssociationFilter</classname> class to create your
          own. Two useful predefined versions are the
          <varname>Filters.STATICALLY_VISIBLE</varname> instance and the
          <methodname>DynamicFilters.dynamicallyVisible(ObjectAdapter)</methodname>
          factory method. Using these filters you can find the properties that
          are visible on a particular type and for a particular object, in
          other words excluding those that where hidden during definition
          (using anotations etc) and those that are programatically hidden
          depending on role or state. Typically views are created using only
          dynamically visible properties so hidden fields are not visible and
          do not have any screen space reserved form them. In particular views
          all the possible properties might need space although the final
          propert might not be shown, a good example of this is table views
          where each statically visible property has a column created for it,
          while for each object shown in table only the dynamically visible
          properties for that object are show (ie there may be blank
          cells).</para>

          <para></para>

          <programlisting>ObjectAssociationFilter filter = DynamicFilters.DynamicFilters.dynamicallyVisible(object);
ObjectAssociation[] properties = object.getSpecification().getProperties(filter);
for (int i = 0; i &lt; properties.length; i++) {
    addField(properties[i].getName(), createFieldView(properties[i]));
}</programlisting>

          <para></para>

          <para></para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>Actions</title>

          <para></para>
        </sect2>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Extending the reflector</title>

        <remark>Describe how introspection takes place</remark>

        <para></para>

        <remark>Facets (describe (including how they are defined, how they are
        used), then list all types with descriptions; Javadocs should detail
        how to use each one, but do check as working through list)</remark>

        <para></para>

        <remark>Detail how introspector determines what facets to give to each
        holder</remark>

        <para></para>

        <remark>Adding behaviour via decorator facets, eg for I18n, logging
        etc</remark>

        <para></para>

        <remark>Adding new behaviour by adding new facets, including how to
        access then</remark>

        <para></para>

        <formalpara>
          <title>Interaction utilties</title>

          <para>Other than the properties and actions that the are made
          available by the reflector the other way the reflector is used is
          via by the reflector utilities classes <remark>I don't think this
          name really reflects the intent, a better one is required</remark>
          such as InteractionUtils and CollectionUtils. These helper classes
          generally make use of the <classname>Facet</classname>s on a
          <classname>FacetHolder</classname> to interact with the domain
          model. For example the <methodname>size(ObjectAdapter)</methodname>
          method on the <classname>CollectionFacetUtils</classname> class will
          determine the size of the collection without having to resort to
          finding the right facet and using that yourself.</para>
        </formalpara>

        <para>These utility classes then make use of the related facets (got
        singularly or a set via the
        <methodname>getFacets(FacetFilter)</methodname> method that typically
        search for facets using the mix-in interfaces that are used to mark
        the facets for this kind of use) which are then all process on behalf
        of the client. For example, the <methodname>isVisible</methodname>
        method get all the facets to do with hidding things by filtering for
        facets that <classname>are of the type
        HidingInteractionAdvisor</classname>. This interface is implemented by
        hide-related facets</para>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <para><classname>DisablingInteractionAdvisor</classname>,
        <classname>HidingInteractionAdvisor</classname> and
        <classname>ValidatingInteractionAdvisor</classname> interfaces are
        used to bring together all facets for disabling, hiding and validating
        properties, actions and parameters. These each provide a single method
        for for checking a proposed interaction. These are then used by the
        <classname>InteractionUtils</classname> class to provide all the
        domain related interaction checking behaviour to the clients of the
        reflector</para>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>How to write your own Facet Decorator</title>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>
    </chapter>

    <chapter>
      <title>ProgModel</title>

      <abstract>
        <para>***</para>
      </abstract>

      <para></para>

      <sect1>
        <title></title>

        <para></para>

        <para>The core progmodel provides a set of reusable elements
        (implementations of the <classname>FacetFactory</classname> API) that
        can be reused to make up a programming model.</para>

        <para>Most of those within this module are in fact used in the default
        programming model, defined by the default progmodel module. They are
        defined within core, however, to allow custom programming models
        (perhaps extending or trimming back the default programming model) to
        be defined.</para>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Architecture Diagram</screeninfo>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/progmodel/architecture-diagram.png"
                         scale="60" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para></para>

        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Composition Diagram (facets package)</screeninfo>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/progmodel/composition-diagram-facets-package.png"
                         scale="60" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Reflection</title>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <para>To make the domain objects useful within the framework the
        objects' public interfaces must be exposed. Reflection capabilities
        are used to determine what fields or properties an object has, what
        behaviour it can offer, and to find other information such as the
        object's title, a suggested order of it fields, when the actions can
        or can't be used. The details about this interface are recorded in an
        instance of <classname>ObjectSpecification</classname>. As each class
        of domain object is loaded into the system introspection is performed
        and an instance of <classname>ObjectSpecification</classname> is
        generated. That specification object is subsequently available from
        any object adapter (using the
        <methodname>ObjectAdapter.getSpecification</methodname> method) for
        that type of domain object; or it can be retrieved directly, by name
        or class, from the <classname>ObjectSpecificationLoader</classname>
        instance (obtained from the <classname>Isis</classname>
        repository).</para>

        <para>Through an object's <classname>ObjectSpecification</classname>
        instance the rest of the NOF can find out the fields that an object
        has, the methods it offers, the title to use to identify the object,
        and other details about the object. These are used normally used by
        the implementations of ObjectAdapter etc when another component ask
        the adapter for details about another object. For example For example
        the statement <code>adapter.getField(no.getFields()[0])</code> would
        retrieve the first field in the domain object held by the Isis
        referenced by <code>adapter</code>.</para>

        <sect2>
          <title>How it Works</title>

          <para>When a domain object is used within the NOF the
          <classname>ObjectSpecificationLoader</classname> instance is asked
          for the <classname>ObjectSpecification</classname> for the domain
          object's class (by name or <classname>java.lang.Class</classname>
          object). For performance reasons these objects are normally cached
          and if the class has previously been introspected then the cached
          version would be returned. The first time that class is requested
          however the loader is responsible for performing the introspection
          and creating a complete
          <classname>ObjectSpecification</classname>.</para>

          <para>For each field that the reflector recognises the loader
          creates either a <classname>OneToOneAssociation</classname> object
          for a value field or a reference field, or a
          <classname>OneToManyAssociation</classname> object for a collection
          or array. Using the field objects the NOF can access or change the
          values and references in the domain object. The fields can also be
          used by the NOF to find out the field name, if the fields are
          visible and whether it can be modified.</para>

          <para>For each action method that the reflector recognises the
          loader must create an <classname>Action</classname> object. Using
          the action object the NOF can invoke the method on the domain
          object. The action object also can be used by the NOF to find out
          the action's name, whether it is visible and whether it can be
          executed.</para>

          <para>In addition to the fields and actions the specification must
          can also: return the various forms of class name (singular; plural;
          short; and full); retrieve a title from, or generate a title for,
          the domain object; flag the type of object (abstract, lookup,
          object, value, and whether persistable); refer to its superclass,
          any inteferfaces it implements and any subclasses; and allow objects
          to marked/cleared as being dirty.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>Installation</title>

          <para>To set up the NOF to use a reflection mechanism the
          <classname>Isis</classname> repository must be given a
          <classname>ObjectSpecificationLoader</classname> instance before the
          repository is initialised. This can be done using the repository's
          static <methodname>setSpecificationLoader</methodname> method. For
          example, the following sets the NOF up to use the basic
          reflector.</para>

          <programlisting>ObjectSpecificationLoader loader = new
        JavaSpecificationLoader();
        Isis.setSpecificationLoader(loader);</programlisting>

          <para></para>
        </sect2>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Reflector</title>

        <para></para>

        <para>The reflector provides the NOF with two distinct facilities.
        First it provides the framework with a model of the domain objects
        that it will be using, and second, it provides a mechanism for the
        framework and the clients of the framework to access and maniplate the
        domain objects (the framework and its clients should never interact
        with the domain objects directly).</para>

        <para>This section is divided into two. The first part looks at how
        the reflector is used by the framework and its clients, while the
        second part looks at how the reflector itself works and how it can be
        extended.</para>
      </sect1>
    </chapter>

    <chapter>
      <title>Runtime</title>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <para>The runtime module is the "engine-room" of the framework, taking
      responsibility to manage domain object (pojo) instances at
      runtime.</para>

      <para>Each pojo is wrapped in an <classname>ObjectAdapter</classname>
      (cf <classname>java.lang.Object</classname>) from which the
      <classname>ObjectSpecification</classname> (cf
      <classname>java.lang.Class</classname>) can be obtained.</para>

      <para>Associated with each <classname>ObjectAdapter</classname> is an
      <classname>Oid</classname>: an opaque serializable identifier to the
      object. The runtime module maintains a 3-way identity map between these,
      allowing forward and reverse lookups.</para>

      <para>The runtime module defines a number of APIs the most important of
      which is the <classname>ObjectStore</classname> API. The runtime module
      manages persistence and transaction demarcation, with the actual storage
      of objects being delegated to an object store implementation.</para>

      <para>The other major API defined by the runtime module security API,
      dealing with authentication and authorization.</para>

      <para>In addition to all the above, the runtime module defines a
      command-line bootstrapper, making it easy to bootstrap Apache Isis from
      a main() or a JUnit test case.</para>

      <para></para>

      <sect1>
        <title></title>

        <para><emphasis>Context</emphasis></para>

        <para>The ObjectAdapterContext provide access to the main components
        of the NOF. If the system is started in a multi-user mode then the
        context will hold specific components for specific execution contexts,
        allowing the same process to access the same components and different
        processes to access unique instances.</para>

        <para>Each execution context will have its own Persistor, Message
        Broker and Update Notifier.</para>

        <para>The Reflector and Configuration are shared among all execution
        contexts.</para>

        <para><emphasis>Persistor</emphasis></para>

        <para>During startup the persistor is given a set of service objects.
        During intialisation the persistor must determine the OIDs for these
        service objects. If the persistor does not know about a service (by
        its ID) from a previous run then it must generate an OID for the
        service and persist that with the ID of the service. This allows
        references to be held persistently to service objects despite the fact
        that they are singletons.</para>

        <para><emphasis>Isis</emphasis></para>

        <para></para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Oid</term>

            <listitem>
              <para></para>

              <para></para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Resolved State</term>

            <listitem>
              <para></para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Version</term>

            <listitem>
              <para></para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term></term>

            <listitem>
              <para></para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <para><emphasis>Identity map</emphasis></para>

        <para>Any object that has identity (whether it is persisted or not)
        must be registered with the identity map. This maps two relationships:
        domain objects to proxies and OIDs to proxies.</para>

        <para>Whenever a domain object is handled by the system, and before a
        proxy is created, it must be checked against the identity map and if
        it exists the proxy already in the identity map must be used instead
        of creating a new proxy.</para>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Adapters and OIDs</title>

        <para>Isis wrap each domain object in the system. The rest of the
        framework does not normally work with the domain objects directly, but
        via these proxies. The proxies provide access to the tools of the
        reflector by providing a <classname>ObjectSpecification</classname>
        for the object's class and to access additional information about the
        domain object. The specification is accessed via the
        <methodname>getSpecification()</methodname> method and is then used
        with the proxy as a mechanism to access and manipulate the domain
        object. Other key methods on the proxy allow access to the: object
        identifier, via the getOid() method to get its unique OID; version
        information, via <methodname>getVersion()</methodname> to get it
        current Version object; and its lazy loaded state, via the
        <methodname>getResolved()</methodname> state returning the
        <classname>ResolvedSate</classname> object reflecting how complete the
        object is.</para>

        <sect2>
          <title>OIDs</title>

          <para>Any domain object that is not a composite part of another
          domain object must have an identity so that the references between
          objects can be persisted for future access and transferred between
          VMs. The OID must be unique so that a one to one mapping can be
          maintained between an <classname>Oid</classname> and a
          <classname>ObjectAdapter</classname>, and hence a domain object.
          Using the OID the client and server can have copies of the same
          objects and identify those objects remotely and persistently. The
          identity is held by the proxy is an <classname>Oid</classname>
          object. The OID for a specific domain object is unique and will not
          change other than when the object is persisted. Until that point it
          has a transient OID that is morphed into the persistent OID when the
          object is persisted. This is so that the transient objects can be
          passed back and forth between client and server, and once persisted
          both ends can match the identity of the previously transient object
          with the identity of the now persistent object.</para>

          <para>When an object is made persistent (typically via the persistor
          and specifically via <classname>OidGenerator</classname>) its OID is
          changed to reflect this and also to allow the persistor to provide
          its own identifier (as is necessary when using natural keys in a
          relational database backend). So the
          <methodname>isTransient()</methodname> state changes from
          <code>true</code> to <code>false</code> while the internal id state
          might be changed. More visibly, the previous state of the OID is
          copied so that <methodname>getPrevious()</methodname> now returns a
          copy of the original OID instead of null and
          <methodname>hasPrevious()</methodname> will return true.</para>

          <para>When a OID with a previous OID is used to retrieve an object
          from the persistor the persistor first checks the OID and if
          <methodname>hasPrevious()</methodname> returns <code>true</code> the
          original tranisent object is retrieved, that object is removed from
          the cache, its OID is updated (via the
          <methodname>copyFrom(Oid)</methodname> method) and then it is
          returned to the cache. This results in the newly persisted object
          having the new persistent OID and it being accessible as such from
          the cache. At this point the original version's transient state will
          no longer be recognised.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>ResolveState</title>

          <para></para>

          <para></para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>Version</title>

          <para></para>

          <para></para>
        </sect2>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Persistor</title>

        <para></para>

        <para>The persistor is tasked with managing all of the domain objects
        and ensuring that they can be retrieved in the futures. In addition to
        it more obvious role in the storing of objects the persistor must also
        manage the object that are memory. This second task is known a
        identity mapping and is required to ensure that any domain object only
        ever has one adapter for it. If more than one adapter exists for an
        object then there will be risk that the system has .......</para>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <sect2>
          <title>Identity Map</title>

          <para>A persistor should utilise an object-identity map (see Martin
          Fowler's Patterns of Enterprise Application Architecture) to manage
          the mapping of domain objects and adapters, and OIDs and adapters.
          For each domain object the map should store a single adapter, and an
          OID to that same adapter. The persitor can then guarantee that the
          same adapter is always provided for a specific domain object or
          OID</para>

          <para></para>

          <para></para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>Creating Adapters</title>

          <para>Numerous methods exist in the persistor (see
          <classname>ObjectAdapterManager</classname>) for creating adapters.
          These methods do three things. First, they insure that there is no
          existing adapter for a domain object or OID, and if there is one
          then that adapter is returned to the caller immediately. Assuming
          there is no existing adapter then a new one is created for the
          domain object and the adapter's OID and resolved state are
          initialised. The OID is typically set to the one provided during the
          reuqest except when a new domain object is being created, in which
          case a new transient OID is created for it. The resolved state
          reflects the type of object and its persistent state. Newly created
          objects end up with <constant>TRANSIENT</constant>, persistent ones
          with <constant>GHOST</constant> and for objects that are aggregated
          the state is intialised to <constant>AGGREGATED (see
          ResolvedState)</constant></para>

          <para></para>

          <para></para>
        </sect2>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Update Notifier (Change Listener)</title>

        <para></para>

        <para>Changes to objects are collected by the
        <classname>UpdateNotifier</classname> object once they have been
        persisted. These changes can then be asynchronously accessed by a
        client to keep it in sync with the underlying model. Once changes are
        retrieved by client the notifier resets its collection so that changes
        are only available once.</para>

        <para>Within the framework, specifically the persistor, when objects
        changes and deletions are persisted the notifier should be informed
        via its <methodname>addChangedObject(ObjectAdapter)</methodname> and
        <methodname>addDisposedObject(ObjectAdapter)</methodname>
        methods.</para>

        <para>Clients should use the
        <methodname>allChangedObjects()</methodname> and
        <methodname>allDisposedObjects()</methodname> to get an
        <classname>Enumeration</classname> of the changes.</para>

        <para>The notifier itself can be got from system context using
        <methodname>IsisContext.getUpdateNotifer()</methodname>.</para>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>What makes up a PersistenceSession</title>

        <para></para>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/PersistenceSession.png" scale="30" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1 id="sec.RuntimeLauncher">
        <title>Launcher</title>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <para>The command line container runs Isis within its own container
        and is best suited to running from the command line where parameters
        are used to determine what components are used and how it all
        runs.</para>

        <para>In essense we are running Java with the Isis class like
        this</para>

        <para>$ java -cp &lt;classpath&gt; org.apache.isis.runtime.IsisObject
        &lt;parameters...&gt;</para>

        <para>however we typically use a script like the one created by the
        archetype so we can run more easily, eg</para>

        <para>$ ./isis.sh &lt;parameters...&gt;</para>

        <para>The Isis class immediately starts up the logging so that log
        messages are never lost. Next the
        <classname>InstallerLookup</classname> object is instantiated. This
        loads up all the installers that can be found on the classpath, which
        are listed in <filename>installer-registry.properties</filename> . (In
        the source tree, this file physically resides in
        <filename>core/runtime/src/main/resources/</filename>). This allows
        Isis to be aware of all the components that are available, allowing
        names such as xml, file, dnd and html to be used to refer to
        components instead of their fully qualified class names. We maintain
        this list with the framework and public available components will be
        added to the registry list when we know about them.</para>

        <para>With these details loaded Isis then parses the command line
        parameters. If there is problem with these then a help text is
        displayed list all the options and the program exits. With the command
        line arguments processed Isis initializes the installers and
        bootstraps the system.</para>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <para>If you are asked from diagnostic information then run Apache
        Isis as follows to capture details about your machine, configuration
        and Isis.</para>

        <programlisting>$ isis.sh --diagnostics &gt; diagnostics.txt</programlisting>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <para>A bootstrapper takes care of loading up the Isis framework and
        application, initialising it, and running it. When it starts up it
        reads in a list of components and attempts to load in each one. Any
        component that can be loaded is then available to be used and can then
        be specified on the command line if required. Requesting a component
        that cannot be loaded will result in an error. To resolve such an
        error simply ensure that the component's Jar file is available on the
        class path. All the components supplied with the framework are listed
        in the file <filename class="directory"
        moreinfo="none">installer-registry.properties</filename> which is part
        of the <filename class="directory"
        moreinfo="none">runtime-4.0.jar</filename> file.</para>

        <para>During start-up Isis loads in a number of configuration files.
        The main file, <filename class="directory"
        moreinfo="none">isis.properties</filename>, is always loaded and must
        be present for the framework to start up. For each of the various
        types of persistor and viewer, there is a separate configuration file.
        For example, for the following command line parameters</para>

        <screen format="linespecific">-v dnd -r xml</screen>

        <para>specifies that the viewer is to be the drag and drop (<literal
        moreinfo="none">dnd</literal>) interface, and the persistor is to be
        the 'xml object store'. As well as loading those components, the
        framework will look for configuration files named
        <filename>viewer.properties</filename>, <filename class="directory"
        moreinfo="none">viewer_dnd.properties</filename>,
        <filename>persistor.xml</filename> and <filename class="directory"
        moreinfo="none">persistor_xml.properties</filename> and will load them
        if found.</para>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <sect2>
          <title>Class</title>

          <para>The bootstrapper is the class
          <classname>org.apache.isis.runtime.Isis</classname> and takes the
          following options on the command line. (Note that in each case there
          is an abbreviated, and a full, version of the option).</para>

          <para>There is also an alternative bootstrapper,
          org.apache.isis.webserver.WebServer.</para>

          <para></para>

          <para>*** can also use org.apache.Isis - just delegates to
          org.apache.isis.runtime.Isis.</para>

          <para></para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>Configuration</title>

          <screen format="linespecific">-c &lt;config file&gt;
--config &lt;config file&gt;</screen>

          <para>Loads in the specified configuration file, in addition to
          <filename class="directory"
          moreinfo="none">isis.properties</filename> and the properties files
          relating to the installed component.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>Disable splash</title>

          <screen format="linespecific">-s
--nosplash</screen>

          <para>Prevents the splash screen from being displayed during start
          up.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>Help</title>

          <screen format="linespecific">-h
--help</screen>

          <para>Prints out the options that are available. This is dynamic so
          that only the components that can be used are listed.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>Logging</title>

          <para>The amount of logging detail can be controlled from the
          command line. If no flag is specified only warnings and errors are
          output. All logging level relate to the Log4J levels, which is the
          logging mechanism used by Isis.</para>

          <screen format="linespecific">-quiet</screen>

          <para>Quiet reduces logging to show errors only.</para>

          <screen format="linespecific">-verbose</screen>

          <para>Increases logging to show information about the system as it
          runs.</para>

          <screen format="linespecific">-debug</screen>

          <para>Increases logging to show all logged entries. At this level so
          much is logged that it will likely slow down the system if used when
          outputting log details to the console or other slow devices.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>Deployment Type (or Mode)</title>

          <screen format="linespecific">-t &lt;mode&gt;
--type &lt;mode&gt;</screen>

          <para>The framework is started up in one of several different
          deployment modes, as listed below:</para>

          <para><emphasis>exploration</emphasis> - Exploration mode is for
          developers to explore and test their code. The framework always uses
          an in-memory persistor and runs the fixtures at startup to ensure a
          known state every time the system is started. The user is not
          prompted to log in, but is automatically logged in as user
          'exploration'. The logged in user can be changed on the fly using an
          option with the user interface; this simply changes the user and
          does not require an explicit login action. Also, exploration methods
          defined in the DOM are also available to the user to do things that
          a user would not normally be allowed to do. These are used expressly
          for testing the system. Please note it is an error to specify a
          persistor type in exploration mode.</para>

          <para><emphasis>prototype</emphasis> - Prototype mode is for
          demonstrating the system in realistic fashion. The user is always
          prompted to log in at start up, and can log out and log in again
          without losing the state of the objects. This allows a user to
          demonstrate exactly how a system would work.</para>

          <para><emphasis>single-user</emphasis> - Single user mode runs the
          system for a single user with object persistence.</para>

          <para><emphasis>client</emphasis> - Client mode provides multiple
          users access to a server. With this mode selected the
          <emphasis>connection</emphasis> option must also be
          specified.</para>

          <para><emphasis>server-exploration</emphasis> - Server mode, but all
          clients will automatically be logged in as the 'exploration' user
          (or as <classname>LoginFixture</classname> is present).</para>

          <para><emphasis>server-prototype</emphasis> - Server mode, but if a
          <classname>LoginFixture</classname> is present then all clients will
          automatically be logged in as this user.</para>

          <para><emphasis>server</emphasis> - Server mode runs Isis as a
          server for multiple clients. With this mode selected the
          <emphasis>connection</emphasis> option must also be
          specified.</para>

          <para>If no mode is specified, the framework will start up in
          <emphasis>prototype</emphasis> mode.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>Overridden properties</title>

          <screen format="linespecific">-D property=value</screen>

          <para>Using this flag we can pass in properties from the command
          line that would otherwise need to specified in a configuration file.
          This is normally used to override a property, or to temporarily
          specify one.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>Password</title>

          <screen format="linespecific">-p &lt;password&gt;
--password &lt;password&gt;</screen>

          <para>Ignored if type is prototype or not used with the user option
          below.</para>

          <para>Uses the specified password when logging the user in with the
          username specified with <methodname>--user</methodname>.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>Persistor</title>

          <screen format="linespecific">-r &lt;persistor&gt;
--persistor &lt;persistor&gt;</screen>

          <para>Ignored if type is client.</para>

          <para>The persistor option allows you to choose how the objects
          created by the system will be persisted so they are still available
          the next time you run the system. The following options are
          available with the current distribution, and if none is specified
          then the in-memory persistor will be used for exploration mode and
          xml persistor will be used for other non-client modes by
          default.</para>

          <para><emphasis>in-memory</emphasis> - A simple non-persisting
          mechanism that will only hold the persisted object while the virtual
          machine is running. This is used for testing and
          demonstrating.</para>

          <para><emphasis>xml</emphasis> - A simple file based mechanism that
          encodes each object's data in an XML file. Alongside the data files
          for the objects are instance lists listing all the files for each
          type of object.<emphasis></emphasis></para>

          <para><emphasis>&lt;class name&gt;</emphasis> - By specifying a
          class name the boot loader will load up that class as the
          persistor.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>Remote connector</title>

          <screen format="linespecific">-x &lt;connector&gt;
--connector &lt;connector&gt;</screen>

          <para>Ignored if mode is not a client. If the type is a client then
          a connection mechanism can be specified. Connector mechanisms
          available are:-</para>

          <para><emphasis>encoding-sockets</emphasis> - Uses the encoding
          mechanism (of value types) to serialize/deserialize objects, over
          TCP/IP sockets.</para>

          <para><emphasis>encoding-http</emphasis> - Uses the encoding
          mechanism (of value types) to serialize/deserialize objects, over
          HTTP.</para>

          <para><emphasis>serializing-sockets</emphasis> - Uses Java
          serialization (of value types) to serialize/deserialize objects,
          over TCP/IP sockets.</para>

          <para><emphasis>xstream-sockets</emphasis> - Uses the Xstream
          library to serialize/deserialize objects to/from XML for simple
          stream communications, over TCP/IP sockets.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>User</title>

          <screen format="linespecific">-u &lt;user name&gt;
--user &lt;user name&gt;</screen>

          <para>Ignored if type is prototype.</para>

          <para>Uses the specified name when logging the user in. If the
          password is also specified (see above) then an attempt to log in
          using the supplied user name and password is made; authentication
          failure at this point will exit the program.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>Viewer</title>

          <screen format="linespecific">-v &lt;viewer&gt;
--viewer &lt;viewer&gt;</screen>

          <para>The viewer option allows you to choose the user interface that
          is used to access your Isis application. The following options are
          available with the current distribution, and if none is specified
          then the drag and drop view will be used by default.</para>

          <para><emphasis>dnd</emphasis> - Drag and Drop viewer</para>

          <para><emphasis>html</emphasis> - Web browser viewer - accessed via
          standard web browser such as FireFox, Internet Explorer or
          Opera</para>

          <para><emphasis>encoding-sockets</emphasis> - Uses the encoding
          mechanism (of value types) to serialize/deserialize objects, over
          TCP/IP sockets.</para>

          <para><emphasis>encoding-http</emphasis> - Uses the encoding
          mechanism (of value types) to serialize/deserialize objects, over
          HTTP.</para>

          <para><emphasis>serializing-sockets</emphasis> - Uses Java
          serialization (of value types) to serialize/deserialize objects,
          over TCP/IP sockets.</para>

          <para><emphasis>xstream-sockets</emphasis> - Uses the Xstream
          library to serialize/deserialize objects to/from XML for simple
          stream communications, over TCP/IP sockets.</para>

          <para><emphasis>&lt;class name&gt;</emphasis> - By specifying a
          class name the boot loader will load up that class as the
          viewer</para>
        </sect2>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Configuration Loading</title>

        <para>*** explain the principle, how we construct from the "id" of the
        installer.</para>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <para>The configuration file (<filename class="directory"
        moreinfo="none">isis.properties</filename>) needs to specify what
        resources are used by the application and what fixtures to load. These
        details are common to all the modes that the NOF can be run in.
        Additional properties can be also specified for use in specific modes,
        such as database connection details when using the SQL object
        store.</para>

        <para>The configuration file <filename class="directory"
        moreinfo="none">isis.properties</filename> is always picked up. In
        addition other properties files will be picked up, if present, based
        on the type, viewer, persistor and connection command line switches
        with the filename matching the option. E.g.</para>

        <para>-r (or --persistor) hibernate will cause
        <filename>persistor.properties</filename> and <filename
        class="directory"
        moreinfo="none">persistor_hibernate.properties</filename> to be
        used</para>

        <para>-t (or --type) client will cause <filename class="directory"
        moreinfo="none">client.properties</filename> to be used</para>

        <para>-v (or --viewer) dnd will cause
        <filename>viewer.properties</filename> and <filename class="directory"
        moreinfo="none">viewer_dnd.properties</filename> to be used</para>

        <para>-x (or -- connector) xstream-sockets will cause
        <filename>transport.properties</filename>,
        <filename>transport_sockets.properties</filename>,
        <filename>protocol.properties</filename> and
        <filename>protocol_xstream.properties</filename> to be loaded; because
        of the way that connector is implemented it will also load
        <classname>persistor.properties</classname> and <filename
        class="directory"
        moreinfo="none">persistor_xstream-sockets.properties</filename>
        too.</para>

        <para>In addition a particular file can be selected with the -c
        switch. For example</para>

        <para>-c <filename class="directory"
        moreinfo="none">mysettings.properties</filename></para>

        <para></para>

        <sect2>
          <title>Properties file contents</title>

          <para>Each properties file can contain lists of services and
          fixtures as well as any specific settings (e.g. Hibernate setting).
          Services are defined using the
          <methodname>isis.services</methodname> property, fixtures by the
          <methodname>isis.fixtures</methodname> property.</para>

          <para></para>

          <para>As a shortcut you can specify the prefix for all classes
          listed in the <methodname>services</methodname> property using
          <methodname>services.prefix</methodname> and the
          <methodname>fixtures</methodname> property using
          <methodname>fixtures.prefix</methodname>.</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific"># uncomment to hide splash
#isis.nosplash
isis.locale=en_GB
isis.services.prefix = org.apache.isis.example.expenses
isis.services = resources.ExpenseTypeFactory \
                       , resources.naive.NaiveClaimRepository\
                       , resources.naive.NaiveEmployeeRepository\
                       , resources.naive.NaiveExpenseTypeRepository\
                       , resources.naive.NaiveItemRepository

isis.fixtures.prefix=org.apache.isis.example.expenses.fixture
isis.fixtures=ExpenseTypes, Employees, ExampleClaim, Context</programlisting>

          <para>Other settings that can be set include</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>isis.nosplash</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>isis.locale (e.g. en_GB)</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>See the relevant section for details of settings specific to
          persistence, web viewer etc.</para>

          <para>The <filename class="directory"
          moreinfo="none">logging.properties</filename> file allows control
          over the logging settings. The NOF uses log4j for logging so please
          refer to <ulink
          url="http://logging.apache.org/log4j/docs/documentation.html">Apache</ulink>
          log4j documentation.</para>

          <para></para>

          <para></para>

          <para></para>
        </sect2>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Other Properties</title>

        <sect2 id="locale">
          <title>Locale</title>

          <para>The locale that the system works in can be set by the
          following property:</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">isis.locale = en_GB</programlisting>

          <para>The locale is specified in two parts separated by an
          underscore.</para>

          <para>The first part is the language and is a valid ISO Language
          Code. These codes are the lower-case, two-letter codes as defined by
          ISO-639. You can find a full list of these codes at a number of
          sites, such as: <ulink
          url="???">http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/php/English_list.php</ulink>
          The second part is the country and is a valid ISO Country Code.
          These codes are the upper-case, two-letter codes as defined by
          ISO-3166. You can find a full list of these codes at a number of
          sites, such as: <ulink
          url="???">http://www.iso.ch/iso/en/prods-services/iso3166ma/02iso-3166-code-lists/list-en1.html</ulink></para>

          <para>If no underscore is used then the setting is deemed to be the
          language.</para>

          <para>If no locale is specified the system uses the locale specified
          by the operating system.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>Time zone</title>

          <para>The time zone that the system works in can be set by the
          following property:</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">isis.timezone = Europe/London</programlisting>

          <para>The time zone is normally a geographic area and a location
          separated by a slash (/), such as
          <emphasis>America/New_York</emphasis>,
          <emphasis>Europe/Paris</emphasis> or
          <emphasis>Australia/Perth</emphasis>. These codes can be looked up
          online on sites such as <ulink
          url="http://www.convertit.com/Go/ConvertIt/World_Time/Current_Time.ASP">ConvertIt.com</ulink>
          and <ulink url="http://twiki.org/cgi-bin/xtra/tzdatepick.html">Date
          and Time Gateway</ulink>.</para>

          <para>Alternatively the time zone can be specified in relative
          format of the form <emphasis>GMT-8:00</emphasis> where the relative
          number of hours and minutes can be specified.</para>
        </sect2>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Image Loading</title>

        <para>All images must be held in a directory called <filename
        class="directory" moreinfo="none">images</filename> in the working
        directory, or on the classpath.</para>

        <para>Images for objects are picked up by class name in the form of
        <filename class="directory"
        moreinfo="none">&lt;ClassName&gt;.&lt;extension</filename>&gt; and
        will be case sensitive on Unix/Linux, but case insensitive on
        Windows.</para>

        <para>The names of the images can be overriden by the reflector, which
        can pass back a name of an image that is found from the domain object.
        This provides a mechanism for objects to be shown with images that
        they themselves specify.</para>

        <para><emphasis>Extensions</emphasis> that are currently supported are
        <filename class="directory" moreinfo="none">.gif</filename>, <filename
        class="directory" moreinfo="none">.png</filename>, <filename
        class="directory" moreinfo="none">.jpg</filename> and <filename
        class="directory" moreinfo="none">.jpeg</filename>.</para>

        <para><emphasis>ClassName</emphasis> is either the short form or the
        fully qualified name of the class, and case can be important depending
        on the platform.</para>

        <para>When loading images based on class, if no image is found for the
        current class using the above variations then the process is repeated
        using the name (both short and fully qualified) of the class's
        immediate superclass. This process repeats until there are no more
        superclasses.</para>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <para>There are a number of generic images that are used by the
        framework, and that can be changed to create a different look. These
        are:-</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><literal>empty-field.png</literal></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><literal>logo.jpg</literal></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><literal>small-logo.png</literal></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><literal>transient.png</literal></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><literal>unknown.png</literal></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Exploration Properties</title>

        <sect2>
          <title>Users</title>

          <para>The list of users that can be switched between during
          exploration can be listed, separated by commas, with the following
          property. If no users are specified the default user "exploration"
          will be used and switching between users will not be
          possible.</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">isis.exploration.users=sven, dick, bob</programlisting>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>Exploration options</title>

          <para>To disable the showing of exploration menu items set the
          following property to false (by default exploration options are
          shown).</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">isis.exploration.show=false</programlisting>
        </sect2>
      </sect1>
    </chapter>

    <chapter>
      <title>Webapp</title>

      <para></para>

      <para>The webapp module is a small module that provides reusable servlet
      context listeners and filters to webapp viewers. They include:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><classname>IsisWebAppBootstrapper</classname> which is a
          servlet context listener to bootstrap an Isis runtime and bind to
          the servlet context</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><classname>IsisSessionFilter</classname> which is a filter
          used to creating an IsisSession for each request (the Open session
          in View pattern)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><classname>ResourceServlet</classname> which serves up static
          content from the specified resource</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><classname>StaticContentFilter</classname> which decorates
          static content with headers for caching</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Not every webapp-based viewer is required to use these classes;
      refer to their documentation for exact details of what should reside in
      the web.xml.</para>

      <para></para>
    </chapter>

    <chapter>
      <title>Webserver</title>

      <para></para>

      <para>The webserver module is intended to make it easy to run
      webapp-based viewers, using the webapp as defined in
      <filename>src/main/webapp/WEB-INF/web.xml</filename>.</para>

      <para>This is a useful facility to have during development, but is not
      (expected to be) needed for deployment. In essence all the module does
      is to bundle up Jetty.</para>

      <para>An alternative would be to use <code>mvn jetty:run</code>; this
      module is for when you'd rather just run a standalone program (ie, with
      a <methodname>main()</methodname> in it) without the overhead of
      <emphasis>Maven</emphasis>.</para>

      <para></para>

      <sect1>
        <title></title>

        <para></para>

        <sect2>
          <title>Properties</title>

          <para>The embedded web server (implemented by Jetty) has only one
          properties</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">isis.embedded-web-server.port=8080</programlisting>

          <para>Which specifies the port to use when prototyping.</para>
        </sect2>
      </sect1>
    </chapter>
  </part>

  <part id="prt.DefaultImplementations">
    <title>Default Implementations</title>

    <partintro>
      <abstract>
        <para>The default implementations of the core
        <acronym>API</acronym>s.</para>
      </abstract>

      <para>This part of the guide discusses the default implementations of
      the core <acronym>API</acronym>s. (Alternative implementations have
      their own guides).</para>
    </partintro>

    <chapter>
      <title>Bootstrapping APIs</title>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <note>
        <para>TODO: discuss Installer architecture; do indicate that this
        stuff is going to change with JSR-299</para>
      </note>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <sect1>
        <title>Services</title>

        <para>Services are registered with the Framework at startup via the
        properties file, using the services properties. The
        <methodname>services</methodname> property itself dictates which
        service classes are to be instantiated at startup, for example:</para>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">isis.services = bom.BookingFactory, bom.CustomerFactoryAndRepository, \
  bom.LocationFactoryAndRepository
</programlisting>

        <para>The <methodname>prefix</methodname> property allows you to
        specify the common package once and, hence omit them from the classes
        in the list. The following set of properties is therefore equivalent
        to the previous example.</para>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">isis.services.prefix = bom
isis.services = BookingFactory, CustomerFactoryAndRepository, \
  LocationFactoryAndRepository
</programlisting>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Registering fixtures</title>

        <para>Fixtures are simple classes that are used to set up a adapter
        objects system. The code for a fixture should be placed in the
        <methodname>install</methodname> method, which is run when the system
        installs the fixtures. Fixtures are only installed if the
        <classname>ObjectAdapterPersistor</classname> flags that it is
        uninitialised via its <methodname>isInitialized</methodname> method.
        For the in memory object store this will be every time it is started,
        and for other object stores will only be when they detect they have no
        persistent data.</para>

        <para></para>

        <para>Fixtures are registered with the Framework at startup via the
        properties file, using the fixtures properties. The
        <methodname>fixtures</methodname> property itself dictates which
        fixture classes are to be instantiated at startup, for example:</para>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">isis.fixtures = fixture.BookingsFixture, fixture.PerspectivesFixture</programlisting>

        <para>The <methodname>prefix</methodname> property allows you specify
        the common package name once and, hence omit them from the classes in
        the list. The following set of properties is therefore equivalent to
        the previous example.</para>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">isis.fixtures.prefix = fixture
isis.fixtures = BookingsFixture, PerspectivesFixture</programlisting>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title></title>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>
    </chapter>

    <chapter id="chp.ProgrammingModelApi">
      <title>Programming Model API and Default Implementation</title>

      <para></para>

      <para>***</para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <note>
        <para>At the moment this API is rather fine-grained. We intend to
        introduce higher level abstractions to make it easier to work with. We
        may also split out member sorting into a separate abstraction.</para>
      </note>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <note>
        <para>TODO: tidy up the following paras, were just copied/pasted in
        from APT</para>
      </note>

      <para></para>

      <para>Although we generally recommend that you stick to the conventions
      of the programmingmodel as documented in the Application Library (in
      <filename>applib</filename>), it is in fact possible to customize or
      modify these conventions. A typical case might be to make Isis support
      some of your own annotations. You'll find that some of the viewers and
      object stores also define their own extensions to the standard
      programming model.</para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <para>The metamodel is built up using a collection of
      &lt;&lt;&lt;FacetFactory&gt;&gt;&gt;s. These are used to identify the
      classes and class members, and to decorate these class members with
      semantics. It is easy to write new &lt;&lt;&lt;FacetFactory&gt;&gt;&gt;s
      to support new programming conventions or, indeed, new languages. The
      &lt;&lt;&lt;FacetFactory&gt;&gt;&gt; API is defined in
      {{{../core/metamodel/index.html}metamodel}} module, along with
      implementations to support the Java language. The
      {{{http://groovyobjects.sourceforge.net}Groovy Objects}} sister project
      provides implementations to allow Isis to support domain objects written
      in {{{http://groovy.codehaus.org}Groovy}}.</para>

      <para></para>

      <sect1>
        <title>FacetFactory</title>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Facets</title>

        <para></para>

        <sect2>
          <title>PropertiesAndCollectionsIdentifyingFacet</title>

          <para></para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>InteractionAdvisors</title>

          <para></para>

          <sect3>
            <title>HidingInteractionAdvisor</title>

            <para></para>
          </sect3>

          <sect3>
            <title>DisablingInteractionAdvisor</title>

            <para></para>
          </sect3>

          <sect3>
            <title>ValidatingInteractionAdvisor</title>

            <para></para>

            <para></para>
          </sect3>
        </sect2>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>MetaModel Validator</title>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Other Languages</title>

        <para></para>

        <sect2>
          <title>Groovy Language Support</title>

          <para></para>

          <para></para>

          <para></para>

          <note>
            <para>TODO: tidy up the following paras, were just copied/pasted
            in from APT</para>
          </note>

          <para></para>

          <para>Isis also allows you to develop your domain application in
          Groovy. This support should be considered experimental for the
          moment; although the viewers and fixtures/in-memory object store
          work fine, it has not been fully tested out with other object
          stores. Further details are available in the
          {{{./support/languages/groovy/index.html}groovy}} module.</para>

          <para></para>

          <para></para>
        </sect2>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Alternative Implementations</title>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>"Rolling-your-own" Programming Model</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>
    </chapter>

    <chapter id="chp.ObjectStoreApi">
      <title>Object Store API and Default Implementation</title>

      <abstract>
        <para>***</para>
      </abstract>

      <sect1>
        <title></title>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <note>
          <para>TODO: tidy up the following paras, were just copied/pasted in
          from APT</para>
        </note>

        <para></para>

        <para>The API is defined in {{{../core/runtime/index.html}runtime}}
        module, with just an in-memory object store provided for prototyping
        and testing only. The plugins provide a number of other
        implementations: a simple {{{./xml-persistor/index.html}XML}}
        persistor (for single user apps), a
        {{{./sql-persistor/index.html}SQL}} persistor to persist directly to
        RDBMS (using JDBC), and a
        {{{./berkeley-persistor/index.html}BerkeleyDB}} persistor. In
        addition, the {{{http://jpaobjects.sourceforge.net}JPA Objects}}
        sister projects uses JPA to persist to an RDBMS.</para>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Alternative Implementations</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Writing your own Object Store</title>

        <para></para>

        <para>When a object is persisted the object store's
        <methodname>createCreateObjectCommand</methodname> method is called.
        This create a command object (see GoF Patterns books), which will
        later be processed when the transaction is be commited. All
        persistence actions (create, destroy and save) are collected together
        until this point. This way when a transaction is aborted all commands
        can be thrown away without recourse to the database. Specifically it
        is the <methodname>execute</methodname> method that is called on the
        command, and this command runs an insert command agains the the
        database.</para>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>
    </chapter>

    <chapter id="chp.ProfileStoreApi">
      <title>Profile Store API and Default Implementation</title>

      <abstract>
        <para>***</para>
      </abstract>

      <sect1>
        <title></title>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <para>Information about a user of the system (rather that a user of
        the application domain model) is stored in a
        <classname>UserProfile</classname> object which is got from the
        <classname>UserProfileService</classname>, which in turn is accessible
        from <classname>IsisSession</classname>. There is also convienence
        methods on <classname>IsisContext</classname> to get both the
        <classname>UserProfile</classname> and the
        <classname>UserProfileService</classname>. The user profile details
        the perspectives the user has set up and options that have been
        specified, typically for the user interfaces. The user profile service
        provides a way to create, save and retrieve the user profiles,
        specifically the profile of the current user. The service in turn has
        a <classname>UserProfilePersistor</classname> that is used to do the
        actual persistence.</para>

        <para>Setting up profiles</para>

        <para>Profiles can be created at start up by creating
        <classname>UserProfileFixture</classname> subclasses. Theses are only
        ever loaded once as the fixture installer checks with
        <methodname>UserProfileSevice.isInitialized()</methodname> to see if
        the service is already set up. The profile fixture (which is defined
        in the application library and is therefore not part of the Isis
        framework) loads the profiles into Isis by passing in an
        implementation of ProfilePersistor that provides a way for the
        perspective to make requests of the framework.</para>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <note>
          <para>TODO: tidy up the following paras, were just copied/pasted in
          from APT</para>
        </note>

        <para></para>

        <para>***</para>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Alternative Implementations</title>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title></title>

        <para></para>

        <para>To store profiles (during exploration) for users the a profile
        store must be specified.</para>

        <para>On the command line use -e xml to store them in an XML.</para>

        <para>Without this the profile will simply be kept in memory, and lost
        on exit.</para>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>
    </chapter>

    <chapter id="chp.SecurityApi">
      <title>Security APIs and Default Implementation</title>

      <abstract>
        <para>This chapter covers the authentication and authorization
        APIs</para>
      </abstract>

      <para></para>

      <para>Apache Isis supports authentication and role-based authorization.
      Within the framework the user is represented by a
      <classname>Session</classname> object. From the session object you can
      get the name of the user and their roles.</para>

      <para>The session is used within the distribution mechanism and the
      security manager. The security manager uses the session to determine if
      a user can access or manipulate an object member. The distribution
      mechanism passes the session to the server so the server knows which
      user is accessing it.</para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <para>As with authentication, authorization may be executed via a file,
      LDAP, or database. If no authorization mechanism is specified, all
      domain calls, methods and properties will be available to all
      users.</para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <note>
        <para>TODO: tidy up the following paras, were just copied/pasted in
        from APT</para>
      </note>

      <para><emphasis></emphasis></para>

      <para><emphasis>Apache Isis</emphasis> applications support
      authentication ("who are you"?) and authorization ("what can you do?").
      This allows the set of functionality to be restricted based upon the
      user's role, with no security knowledge needing to be embedded within
      the domain objects. The API is defined in
      {{{../core/runtime/index.html}runtime}}, along with two implementations,
      one file-based and one using LDAP.</para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <para>An <classname>Authoriser</classname> processes an
      <classname>AuthorizationRequest</classname> and if granted generates a
      <classname>Session</classname> object to represent the user.</para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <para>There is an optional capability to authorise the visibility and
      usability of fields independently. Thus a field may be visible to
      certain roles but not editable. In order to configure this against a
      authorization a flag must be added as follows.</para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <sect1>
        <title>Capturing authorization requirements automatically</title>

        <para>As a tool for helping to configure the initial security settings
        there is a 'learn' property.</para>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">isis.authorization.learn=true</programlisting>

        <para>When this is present and set, all methods will be authorised for
        all roles. However as each method is accessed through the user
        interface authorization will be configured for that method and the
        current role. Configuration will be saved in either the file (saved on
        shutdown), database table or LDAP security settings depending upon the
        reflector setup.</para>

        <para>The settings can then be modified to conform to the required
        security settings.</para>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Alternative Implementations</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>
    </chapter>

    <chapter>
      <title>Bytecode Provider APIs</title>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <note>
        <para>TODO: tidy up the following paras, were just copied/pasted in
        from APT</para>
      </note>

      <para></para>

      <para>Isis normally performs lazy loading of references and dirty
      tracking by proxying all domain objects. Two implementations are
      provided, using either cglib or javassist. The application archetype
      automatically configures the use of these proxies. However, some object
      stores (notably, the {{{./plugins/jpa-persistor/index.html}JPA object
      store}}) do not require these proxies (because they add their own
      proxies instead); in which case these can be disabled. Alternatively,
      you may not want to use the bytecode support, in which case you can add
      the appropriate calls for lazy loading and dirty tracking. This area is
      covered in the {{{./applib/index.html}applib}}, but there is also
      module-specific documentation in the
      {{{./core/bytecode-cglib/index.html}bytecode-cglib}} and
      {{{./core/bytecode-javassist/index.html}bytecode-javassist}}
      modules.</para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <sect1>
        <title>Alternative Implementations</title>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>
    </chapter>
  </part>

  <part id="prt.DeploymentGuide">
    <title>Deployment Principles</title>

    <partintro>
      <abstract>
        <para>The principles for deploying an <emphasis>Isis</emphasis>
        application.</para>
      </abstract>

      <para>Assuming that you have developed your domain model and tested it
      as a standalone prototype, this part of the guide describes the basic
      deployment options.</para>

      <para>Alternative implementations (most notably, remoting for
      client/server) that allow for different deployments have their own
      guidance on deployment. The same is also true for viewers that allow for
      different deployments (eg a viewer that supports a mobile phone or
      Eclipse OSGi would likely have its own packaging requirements).</para>
    </partintro>

    <chapter id="chp.DeployingIsisApplications">
      <title>Overview</title>

      <note>
        <para>TODO: tidy up the following paras, were just copied/pasted in
        from APT</para>
      </note>

      <para></para>

      <para>All the following describe setting up the default security
      implementations. *** Mention that there are other implementations</para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <para>For desktop-based viewers the framework provides a
      <classname>ViewerInstaller</classname> <acronym>API</acronym>, defined
      in the <filename>core/runtime</filename> module. This approach is used
      by the <acronym>DnD</acronym> viewer and the <acronym>HTML</acronym>
      viewer, for example.</para>

      <para>Alternatively the viewer can use its own mechanism to get started
      (eg as a webapp) and then simply bootstrap the Isis runtime with a
      couple of lines of code. This is the technique used by the Scimpi webapp
      viewer, by the Wicket viewer and by the Restful viewer.</para>

      <para></para>

      <para>*** x-ref remoting docs as a way of deploying in client/server
      mode.</para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <sect1>
        <title>Setting up perspectives</title>

        <para></para>

        <para>profilestore</para>

        <para>x-ref alternatives/profilestore/xml</para>

        <para></para>

        <para>Perspectives allow the set of services available to a user (eg
        as icons in the DnD viewer) to be customized for that user. Since
        these services represent the "start points" for the user to interact
        with the domain model, they in a sense define an application on a
        per-user basis.</para>

        <para>The perspectives are stored in user-profiles, which are a
        persistence mechanism independent of the object store. (The intent is
        for user profiles to store additional information for use by viewers,
        for example allowing a user to reskin an application or change colors
        or fonts. As of NOF 4.0 the functionality provided is still limited,
        however).</para>

        <para>The key here is that if a user logs in and no perspective exists
        for that user then one will be created for them. The new perspective
        will be a copy of the 'template' perspective, or, if none was defined,
        a perspective containing all the known services. To create a template
        perspective add a perspective fixture that calls
        <methodname>saveAsDefault()</methodname>, rather than
        <methodname>saveForUser()</methodname> for a named user, as shown
        below.</para>

        <programlisting>public class PerspectivesFixture extends UserProfileFixture {
    @Override
    protected void installProfiles() {
        Profile profile = newUserProfile();
        Perspective perspective = profile.newPerspective("ECS");
        perspective.addToServices(LocationFactory.class);
        perspective.addToServices(CustomerRepository.class);
        perspective.addToServices(PaymentMethodFactory.class);
        
        saveAsDefault(profile);
    }
}
</programlisting>

        <para>With that set up, when a new user now logs in they will see
        three service icons on the screen for locations, customers and payment
        methods. On the drag and drop user interface the user can add and
        remove services from their perspective. To remove a service icon
        right-click on the grey border and select the close option. To add a
        service select the Services... option from the application menu
        (accessed by right-clicking on the application background) and drag
        the required service onto the desktop. Unfortunately there is no
        similar mechanism available on the HTML user interface so you will
        need to modify the created perspectives via the DND UI.</para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Adding Security (Authentication and Authorization)</title>

        <para></para>

        <para>x-ref alternatives/security/file</para>

        <para></para>

        <sect2>
          <title></title>

          <para></para>
        </sect2>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Adding support for internationalisation</title>

        <para>All the text that appears to the user comes from the domain
        object model. Any literal text used within the code may be
        externalised, and localised using the standard Java mechanism of
        resource bundles. However as all field and menu names are derived from
        the method names the framework provides a mechanism to adapt these
        names using resource bundles as well.</para>

        <sect2>
          <title>Localisation files</title>

          <para>Create a file for each required language, e.g., <filename
          class="directory" moreinfo="none">i18n_en_GB.properties</filename>
          for English in Great Britain, and place them into the project such
          that they will be included in the class path. For the project
          structures we have already seen the files could be added to the
          <filename class="directory" moreinfo="none">resources</filename>
          directory, as the following example shows.</para>

          <screen format="linespecific">resources/
   <emphasis role="strong">i18n_en_GB.properties
   i18n_de_DE.properties
   i18n_fr_FR.properties</emphasis>
   </screen>

          <para>The following example is part of one of those translation file
          and shows how property and action names and descriptions may be
          specified.</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">example.dom.Contact.property.Phone.name=Tlphone
example.dom.Contact.action.NewPhone.name=Nouveau tlphone
example.dom.Contact.property.FullName.description=Le nom complet du client</programlisting>

          <para>For more details on defining localisation files, <xref
          linkend="i18n-files" />.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>Configuration</title>

          <para>The reflector needs to be decorated with a facet decorator to
          look up the translated names every time the framework needs
          information about the fields and menus. To include the decorator add
          the following to a properties file.</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">isis.reflector.facet-decorators=resource-i18n</programlisting>

          <para>If the application is being accessed via the web (html)
          viewer, then the server will need to perform the localisation, so
          the above property should be included in one of isis.properties read
          by the server; if the application is being accessed by a client
          (e.g. the DND viewer) then the localisation will be performed within
          the client, and the property should be specified in one of the
          properties files read by the client e.g. <filename class="directory"
          moreinfo="none">facet-decorator_i18n.properties</filename>.</para>

          <para>The locale will be picked up automatically from the machine on
          which the code is executing. You may override this by specifying the
          <link linkend="locale">locale</link> in a properties file.</para>
        </sect2>
      </sect1>
    </chapter>

    <chapter>
      <title>Web App Deployment</title>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <sect1>
        <title>Setting up Security</title>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <para>x-ref <xref linkend="chp.SecurityApi" />.</para>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
        <title>Running as a WebApp</title>

        <para>Isis provides three different ways to run as a webapp:</para>

        <sect2>
          <title>Using isis.sh</title>

          <screen format="linespecific">$ isis.sh --type server --viewer html --persistor xml
2007-08-09 12:37:13.671::INFO:  Logging to STDERR via org.mortbay.log.StdErrLog
2007-08-09 12:37:13.801::INFO:  jetty-6.0.2
2007-08-09 12:37:13.954::INFO:  Started SocketConnector @ 0.0.0.0:8080
</screen>

          <para>This command runs the Isis with the HTML viewer, allowing
          multiple clients to access it via a browser. As for the standalone
          version the users need to access the URL
          http://<emphasis>server/logon.app</emphasis> to access the log on
          page.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>Using WebServer bootstrap</title>

          <para>The next mechanism uses the
          <classname>org.apache.isis.webserver.WebServer</classname> bootstrap
          to run Isis. This loads up whatever is in the webapp project's
          <filename>web.xml</filename> file.</para>

          <para><remark>TODO: we don't have a webserver.sh script to show this
          in action; we probably should.</remark></para>

          <para>Ordinarily the web.xml will be configured to run the same HTML
          viewer, so the end result will be the same. However, if necessary
          the remoting servlet can also be configured</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
          <title>Deploying as a WAR</title>

          <para>The final mechanism is to use Maven to package up the webapp
          project as a WAR file, packaging up whatever is in the web.xml file.
          As above, ordinarily the web.xml will be configured to run the same
          HTML viewer, so the end result will be the same. However, if
          necessary the remoting servlet can also be configured</para>

          <para>Packaging up is done using:</para>

          <screen format="linespecific">$ cd webapp
$ mvn clean package</screen>

          <para>This should result in a WAR file in
          <filename>target</filename> directory. This can be deployed to an
          existing servlet containerd</para>
        </sect2>
      </sect1>
    </chapter>

    <chapter>
      <title>Standalone Deployment</title>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <note>
        <para>TODO: discuss sealed/signed JARs to prevent tampering?</para>
      </note>

      <para></para>

      <sect1>
        <title>Setting up Security</title>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <para>x-ref <xref linkend="chp.SecurityApi" />.</para>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>
      </sect1>
    </chapter>
  </part>
</book>
