<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
  
         http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
         
  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
"http://www.apache.org/dtds/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Case Study</title>
		<author email="isis-dev@incubator.apache.org">Apache Isis Contributors</author>
	</properties>

	<body>
		<section
			name="Case Study: How the Irish Government uses Naked Objects to administer social benefits worth over &amp;euro;5bn a year">

			<p>
				The
				<a href="http://www.welfare.ie">Department of Social Protection</a>
				(DSP) is the part of the Irish Government responsible for
				administering more than 40 social benefit schemes, including state
				pensions, child benefit, and unemployment benefit.
			</p>
			<p>As part of a far-reaching Service Delivery Modernisation (SDM)
				programme, aimed at improving customer service, productivity and
				enabling e-government initiatives, the DSP recognised that it needed
				a new generation of enterprise business systems. Each of new
				applications had to deliver specific business benefits. But there
				was
				also an over-arching requirement: improved agility. This was
				articulated in three forms:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Technical agility: the ease with which the architecture could
					accommodate future changes in technology.</li>

				<li>Strategic business agility: the ease with which the system could
					accommodate unforeseen future changes in business requirements.</li>

				<li>Operational business aglity: empowering users to act as
					problem-solvers, not merely process-followers.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>
				Achieving these objectives would require a combination of a new
				enterprise architecture and the adoption of agile development
				techniques. The DSP were persuaded that the single most important
				factor in achieving this agility was a commitment to build a
				business object model or BOM, that encapsulated all business
				behaviour on the business entity objects. They also became aware of
				the
				<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Naked_objects">Naked Objects
					pattern</a>
				(little more than a research idea at that stage) and
				recognised that
				this could help them achieve a higher-quality object model, as well
				as delivering a more empowering style of user interface.
			</p>
			<p>
				A period of experimentation and exploration culminated in
				the first
				pilot project going live in 2002,
				based on their own proprietary
				implementation of the Naked Objects pattern
				(developed under contract
				by
				<a href="http://www.fujitsu.com/ie/casestudies/dsaf.html">Fujitsu</a>
				).
				The project was hugely successful from a business perspective. In
				the meantime the Naked Objects framework had become available;
				recognising that the latter offered a more powerful capability and
				was open source, the DSP subsequently made the decision to switch all
				future application development onto Naked Objects.
			</p>
			<p>
				In June 2004 the DSP awarded a contract to Naked Objects Group, in
				partnership with
				<a href="http://www.bearingpoint.ie">BearingPoint</a>
				, to revise the architecture and develop a series of large-scale
				applications, including the administration of all state pensions
				benefits, child benefit, and the central debt management function.
				These applications all went live during the course of 2006. The
				scope of the SDM platform continues to grow, with new functionality
				released each month and major new projects progressing every year
				since. The applications running on the new architecture are in
				continuous use by more than 700 users. Those applications are
				responsible for administering more than &euro;5bn
				in benefit payments annually.
			</p>
			<p>
				(You can view a
				<a href="./movies/DSFA_CB_Demo.htm">screen movie</a>
				of the DSFA's Child
				Benefit administration running on Naked Objects.)
			</p>
			<subsection name="Benefits"></subsection>
			<p>The primary intended benefit of agility
				(as articulated above) has
				already been clearly achieved. During the
				course of the programme so
				far, the DSP has been faced with
				substantial
				new business
				requirements
				(resulting from changes in legislation,
				government
				re-organisation,
				and various e-government initiatives)
				and the
				new
				architecture and
				applications have proven easy to modify and
				extend.</p>
			<p>Two further benefits are now perceived, across the
				organisation.
				The first is the capability to build rapid prototypes of new
				applications, which help business units not only to articulate their
				requirements, but also to explore alternative business models.</p>
			<p>The
				second is an extremely high level of re-use. At the DSP, the
				primary
				objective was always agility rather than re-use per se. But
				the hope
				was
				that they would establish a 'Common BOM' that would
				provide the core
				capabilities of any new application. In fact this
				has proven to be
				far
				more successful than they dared to hope for, and
				Naked Objects has is
				key
				to this. When the Child Benefit system was
				re-written for the new
				architecture in 2006, it replaced a system
				that had more than 50,000
				lines
				of bespoke business code. The new
				implementation has less than 1000
				lines
				of bespoke business code (in
				the same language): everything else was
				inherited, without
				modification, from the Common BOM written as part
				of
				the Pensions
				project.</p>
			<p>In May 2007, the DSP's Director of
				Information Systems, Niall
				Barry, stated publicly that he was delighted
				with the new systems,
				adding that 'in 30 years of managing IT projects,
				I have never been
				more satisfied'.</p>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
