<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE webpage SYSTEM "./document.dtd">

<webpage title="Main themes" label="themes" date="10-Mar-04">
	
<para>Naked Objects version 1.3 is a development release that contains significant
	 new capabilities.  These will appear in a public stable release (1.4)
as soon as we judge them to be stable. </para>
		
<para>The new capabilities are principally concerned with providing greater support
	for enterprise systems.  There are xx main themes:</para>
	
<list>
	<para><em>Security and authorisation</em> The framework now provides a log-in screen for any
		deployed Naked Object system. (There is no log-in for an Exploration, where the emphasis
		is on simplicity.)  The framework provides User objects, and Role objects, which
		can be accessed by the application. <see label="security">More</see></para>
		
	<para><em>Control</em>  The About objects have been substantially enhanced 
		and simplified. Individual actions or fields can now be rendered invisible, or inoperable
		according to the state of the object, conditional business logic (i.e. business rules),
		the user's role(s) or the user's specific identity. <see label="control">More</see>
		</para>
		
	<para><em>Distribution</em> Support for building distributed systems has been increased.
		<see label="distribution">More</see></para>
		
	<para><em>Persistence</em> [Anything new to say about persistence e.g. the paging]</para>
		
	<para><em>Internet deployment via WebStart</em> Java's WebStart is an ideal complement to
		Naked Objects.  It allows a Naked Objects application (either a Standalone or a Distributed
		application) to be deployed from a web server.  Once the client code has been downloaded
		it is locally cached, and only downloaded again if there is a new version of the application.
		Version 1.3. includes instructions on how to package a Naked Objects application into
		a JNLP file for access via WebStart. <see label="web-start">More</see></para>
		
	<para><em>Contexts</em> Arguably, Naked Objects cuts across the traditional concept of 
		discrete applications.  Nevertheless in an enterprise setting we recognise the need to
		provide the user with multiple contexts.  Contexts are just groupings of 
		Naked Object classes (they may overlap), together with convenient collections of object
		instances of use to a particular individual.  The framework now provides a Context class
		(itself just another Naked Object).  Each user is provided with a default Context, which
		can contain other Contexts as well as other classes and instances. This makes it very
		easy to implement the concept of an 'enterprise portal' using Naked Objects. 
			<see label="contexts">More</see></para>
		
	<para><em>Reference application</em> To coincide with the 1.3 development
		release, we have created a reference application which is an expenses processing system.
		You can launch the application on-line (using Java Webstart) <see label="expenses-demo">here</see>;
		or you can download a stanalone executable version, user documentation, and/or the complete source code from the
		<see label="downloads">Downloads page.</see> This application serves three main purposes.</para>
		
		<para>First, it serves as a demonstration of the capabilities and benefits of the Naked Objects
			approach, particularly for building <see label="ria">Rich Internet Applications</see>. 
			You can read an <see label="expenses-advantages"> explanation of the advantages</see> of this particular application over 
			many existing systems for expenses processing.</para>
			
		<para>Second, it provides an effective reference source for programmers.  We will continue
			to update this reference application, with the intention of making use of each
			new capability added to the framework.</para>
			
		<para>Third, to provide the basis for a real application.  OUr long term intent
			is that this application will match all the capabilities of the established
			commercial packages for expenses processing, but with additional benefits.
			Under the GPL open source license you will be able to freely use, and to modify
			it to your specific requirements.  We also intend to offer the same system under
			a commercial license, with full commercial support.  This will be the first of
			several substantial business applications that we will offer.
			</para>
	
	<para><em>Naked Class</em>  TBD  </para>
		
</list>

</webpage>