<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "./documentation.dtd">

<section numbered="on">
    <title>Logging</title>

    <para> The dot net reflector is currently returning Naked as its
    superclass, and Naked’s superclass is also Naked, so we go into a loop
    when trying to find images for classes. Fixed this by returning a ‘null’
    instead. Have managed to get errors from the Dot Net reflector, which get
    round the bug in J# where reflectively invoked method (using Java’s
    reflection classes) are not working. The type useful error message can be
    seen below. </para>

    <command-listing> Object reference not set to an instance of an object. at
    Officer.actionLogon() in C:\Documents and Settings\rcm\My
    Documents\sdm-exploration\src\bom\officer\Officer.vb:line 341
    </command-listing>

    <para> Split the .net projects into three parts, so there is now a the
    core, a separate dot-net reflection mechanism, and some tests. The tests
    are separate so that they can be compiled and run as a Windows application
    (so there output appears in the Visual Studio console), while the
    reflector compiles into a DLL. I have references these DLL directly from
    the exploration project so that after recompiling the framework the
    exploration will run without having to copy across the DLLs. Added an
    initial logging statement to record the version and build numbers in the
    log (taken from <class>AboutNakedObjects</class>). Now recommend that
    basic logging is configured as below so that basic errors and warnings are
    shown to the user and full logging details are captured to a file. </para>

    <para />

    <property-listing>## log4j 
    # apache's log4j is used to provide system logging. 
    ## log4j.rootCategory=DEBUG, File, Console
    log4j.logger.org.nakedobjects.viewer.skylark=WARN
    log4j.logger.org.nakedobjects.viewer.skylark.value.TextField=WARN
    log4j.logger.org.nakedobjects.viewer.skylark.value.TextFieldBlock=WARN
    log4j.logger.org.nakedobjects.viewer.skylark.value.TextFieldContent=WARN 
    
    # The console appender
    log4j.appender.Console=org.apache.log4j.ConsoleAppender
    log4j.appender.Console.threshold=WARN
    log4j.appender.Console.target=System.out
    log4j.appender.Console.layout=org.apache.log4j.PatternLayout
    log4j.appender.Console.layout.ConversionPattern=%-5r [%-20c{1}] %-5p %m -- %l%n 
    log4j.appender.Console.layout.ConversionPattern=%d [%c{1}] %-5p %m%n
    log4j.appender.Console.layout.ConversionPattern=%-4r %-5p [%t] %37c %3x - %m%n 
    
    log4j.appender.File=org.apache.log4j.FileAppender
    log4j.appender.File.file=nakedobjects.log
    log4j.appender.File.layout=org.apache.log4j.PatternLayout
    log4j.appender.File.layout.ConversionPattern=%d [%-20c{1}] %-5p %m%n
    </property-listing>

</section>