<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE publication SYSTEM "./documentation.dtd">
<publication>
  <title>The Naked Objects Framework</title>

  <subtitle>A programmer's and developer's reference</subtitle>

  <author>Robert Matthews</author>

  <copyright>
    <year>2005</year>

    <holder>Robert Matthews</holder>

    <license>
      <para>Permission is granted to make and distribute verbatim copies of
      this manual provided that the copyright notice and this permission
      notice are preserved on all copies.</para>
    </license>
  </copyright>

  <preamble>
    <!-- Naked Objects manual -->

    <section numbered="off">
        <title>Preface</title>
      
      <para>This manual documents the use and development of Naked Object
      applications using the Naked Objects framework, its associated
      components and tools. The is primarily a reference guide for application
      developers and developers of the framework. For an introduction to Naked
      Objects and the the ideas behind the framework please refer to the book
      <ital>Naked Objects</ital> (by Richard Pawson and Robert Matthews)
      published by Wiley.</para>

      <para>This manual is currently available as PDF document, to be viewed
      using Adobe Acrobat, but will be available as a printed book in due
      course, made available from the nakedobjects web site.</para>

      <para>This edition of the manual is intended for use with version 1.0 of
      the Naked Objects framework, which works with version 1.1, and higher,
      of Java. The latest framework is available from the download's page of
      the naked objects website <weblink
      address="http://www.nakedobjects.org/downloads" />.</para>
    </section>

    <section numbered="off">
        <title></title>
      
      <para>Naked Objects is <ital>free software</ital>, this means that
      everyone is free to use, and free to redistribute it on certain
      conditions. Naked Objects is copyrighted software and has restrictions
      placed on its distribution, but as set out by Free Software Foundation
      these are intended to encourage sharing rather than preventing
      it.</para>

      <para>The simplest way to get hold of a copy of Naked Objects is to
      download it from the naked object website: <weblink
      address="http://www.nakedobjects.org/downloads" />, or to get a copy
      from a colleague or friend. If needed you can order a copy (on CD) from
      us for a nominal fee.</para>

      <para>Contributors to the Naked Objects framework and associated
      software include: Franz Achermann, Jochen Bedersdorfer, Alan Chandler,
      Stephan Eggermont, Dan Haywood, Dave Slaughter, Johan Stover.</para>
    </section>
  </preamble>
  
  <section numbered="on">
      <title>Getting Started</title>
      
      <include file="introduction.xml"/>
      <include file="how no works.xml"/>
        <include file="running an example.xml"/>
  </section>
  
  <section numbered="on">
      <title>Configuration</title>
      
    <include file="logging.xml"/>
    <include file="images.xml"/>
    <include file="viewer properties.xml"/>
  </section>
  
  <section numbered="on">
      <title>Developing with Naked Objects</title>
      
      <include file=""/>
  </section>
  
  <section numbered="on">
      <title>How it Works</title>
      
    <include file="skylark viewer.xml"/>
    <include file="nakedobjects-repository.xml"/>
  </section>
  
  <section numbered="on">
      <title>Other</title>
      
    <include file="framework design introduction.xml"/>
    <include file="configure and running.xml"/>
    <include file="configuration.xml"/>
    <include file="object loader.xml"/>
    <include file="distribution.xml"/>
    <include file="filename-convention.xml"/>
    <include file="security.xml"/>
</section>
  
  
  <section numbered="on">
      <title>Framework Development</title>
      
     
  </section>
  
</publication>