<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"file:./src/docbkx/dtd-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.
-->
<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <title><?eval ${docbkxGuideTitle}?></title>

    <subtitle><?eval ${docbkxGuideSubTitle}?></subtitle>

    <releaseinfo><?eval ${project.version}?></releaseinfo>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Dan</firstname>

        <surname>Haywood</surname>
      </author>

      <author>
        <firstname>Robert</firstname>

        <surname>Matthews</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Permission is granted to make and distribute verbatim copies of
      this manual provided that the copyright notice and this permission
      notice are preserved on all copies.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </bookinfo>

  <toc></toc>

  <chapter>
    <title>Conventions</title>

    <para>*** change into an appendix?</para>

    <para></para>

    <para></para>

    <para>The <emphasis>Isis</emphasis> framework provides a number of tools
    to help resolve problems and debug the system. These are mainly applicable
    to issues within system code, but some of them can be useful when
    developing applications. The framework provides the following:-</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Extensive use of logging through the <ulink
        url="http://logging.apache.org/log4j/docs/">Log4j</ulink> framework,
        an open source logging framework made available as part of the Apache
        Jakarta project ;</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>In addition, the DnD viewer provides debug views that display
    details of components and anything else that implements the
    <classname>DebugInfo</classname> interface. There is further coverage of
    this last feature in the DnD viewer's documentation.</para>

    <para></para>

    <sect1>
      <title>"XxxAware" convention for components</title>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Logging</title>

      <para>Logging using Log4j is used throughout the framework and the
      components the Isis development team have created, and it is recommended
      that you use it too. Logging allows you to look what the framework and
      components have been when you investigate a problem and help to identify
      what parts of the system where doing what before an problem arose. Often
      logging alone is enough to pin point a problem, but if not it help you
      target what to investigate.</para>

      <para>Log4j allows you to log log debug messages, information about the
      system's state, warnings and errors. These events can be displayed on
      the console, written to files, or sent out over the network for remote
      logging. These are output in a user defined format and also can be
      filtered (so only events from certain components are seen). All this is
      configured through a set of properties passed to Log4J.</para>

      <sect2>
        <title>Configuring Logging</title>

        <para>The complete options for outputting and formatting can be found
        in the relavent Log4J documentation (including the API). However, it
        crucial to smooth development of an NOF system that will cover some of
        it here. The NOF configures Log4j using properties files and will
        generally load <filename class="directory"
        moreinfo="none">log4j.properties</filename> or retrieve the properties
        from the that were loaded from <filename class="directory"
        moreinfo="none">isis.properties</filename> after that is loaded for
        framework configuration (these files need to be located in the working
        directory). If you are not using classes within the NOF to start the
        framework then how these properties are loaded could vary. The
        downside of putting the logging properities in the framework
        properties files is that there is no logging until it has been loaded.
        If this is necessary then it is better to use the separate properties
        file.</para>

        <para>The following file, or portion of a file, is a basic
        configuration for logging. It consists of two appenders and a basic
        logging configuration.</para>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">log4j.rootLogger=INFO, Console, File

# The console appender
log4j.appender.Console=org.apache.log4j.ConsoleAppender
log4j.appender.Console.Target=System.out
log4j.appender.Console.layout=org.apache.log4j.PatternLayout
log4j.appender.Console.layout.ConversionPattern=%-5r [%-20c{1} %-10t %-5p]  \t\t%m%n

# The exploration.log file appender
log4j.appender.File=org.apache.log4j.FileAppender
log4j.appender.File.File=exploration.log
log4j.appender.File.layout=org.apache.log4j.PatternLayout
log4j.appender.File.layout.ConversionPattern=%-4r %-5p [%t] %37c %3x - %m%n
log4j.appender.File.Append=false</programlisting>

        <para>The first line sets up logging to show events of level
        <emphasis>INFO</emphasis> and above through the
        <emphasis>Console</emphasis> and <emphasis>File</emphasis> appenders,
        which writes those events to the console and the file <filename
        class="directory" moreinfo="none">exploration.log</filename>
        respectively. The two blocks sepcifiy how to write to the console and
        the file. Other appenders can be used to change where the logs are
        written to. The number of appenders specified is unlimited, although
        there should be at least one. The console below (from Eclipse) shows
        the log. The file will contain the same thing although the formatting
        will be slightly different as the conversion pattern for the two
        appenders is different.</para>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/console-log.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>

        <sect3>
          <title>Logging levels</title>

          <para>The types of events that are logged can be changed. This
          determines how large the files become or how much traffic is put
          over the network, and is reflected in the amount of processing that
          needs to be done to process the events into messages that can be
          written out. Levels in order of increasing verbosity and log size,
          and is decreasing order of severity are:-</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>OFF - no logging</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>FATAL - something very serious has happened that requires
              the system to be shut down.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>ERROR - something serious has happened that might affect
              any subsequent actions.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>WARN - something has not been set up properly, or needs
              attention. Although subsequent action might function correctly,
              they might not function as expected.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>INFO - information to the developer about something that
              has taken place.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>DEBUG - detailed information for the developer.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>So in the above example to increase the logging level to debug
          change the first part of the property to <emphasis>DEBUG</emphasis>
          from <emphasis>INFO</emphasis> as below:</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">log4j.rootLogger=DEBUG, Console, File</programlisting>

          <para>Logging should almost never be set to off, but should at least
          be set to log the errors (unsing level ERROR). Whilst developing we
          recommend that you set your basic level to INFO and switch to DEBUG
          if you need to investigate something.</para>

          <para>Setting the logging level via the properties file applies that
          level at startup and cannot be changed using the properties, ie,
          that level will be used to filter all logged event while the system
          is running. If you are using the Skylark viewer, however, you can
          use the debug options to change the logging level on the client at
          any time. By using Ctrl-Shift-right-click on the desktop you will be
          shown the debug menu and see the following options:-</para>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="left" fileref="images/logging-debug.png"
                         format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>

          <para>The greyed-out option indicates the current level. Selectiing
          one of the other levels will change the logging to that
          level.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>Limiting logging by class</title>

          <para>As well as limiting the level of events that are logged, we
          can also specify which classes we are interested in capturing log
          events for. In Log4j events are organised by loggers, which are set
          up programmatically, but as we create a logger for each class we
          talk about classes.</para>

          <para>To change the levels of events captured according to the class
          where the log event was created we can class based requirements
          after the root logger is specified. To set a logging level for a
          class add a property in the form</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">log4j.logger.&lt;package to log&gt;=&lt;level for package&gt;
log4j.logger.&lt;class to log&gt;=&lt;level for class&gt;</programlisting>

          <para>Events for the specified packages or class will be logged at
          the specified level, overriding the root level set up first. So for
          example the following configuration:</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">log4j.rootLogger=WARN, Console

log4j.logger.org.apache.isis.object=INFO
log4j.logger.org.apache.isis.object.reflect=DEBUG
log4j.logger.org.apache.isis.object.persistence=DEBUG

log4j.logger.org.apache.isis.object.loader.ObjectLoaderImpl=OFF</programlisting>

          <para>will capture warning and errors for all classes (as defined by
          the root logger), and information messages for those classes whose
          package begins with <classname>org.apache.isis.object</classname>.
          In addition those classes beginning with
          <classname>org.apache.isis.object.reflect </classname>or
          <classname>org.apache.isis.object.persistence</classname> will have
          their debug events captured as well. Finally, the class
          <classname>ObjectLoader</classname> will have all of its events
          ignored.</para>

          <para>It is important to make use of this feature when using the
          Skylark viewer as it logs events about it rendering. In Java
          rendering the screen (via the
          <methodname>paint(Graphics)</methodname> method) happens very often
          and can cause the logs to be swamped with superflous events. The
          logger for these events are prepended with the text 'ui.' so we can
          disable all of these events across all the viewing classes by adding
          the following to the properties:</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">log4j.logger.ui=OFF</programlisting>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>Writing XML log files</title>

          <para>By writing out the logs to a file in XML rather than as text
          allows you to look at the log using Chainsaw, a Log4j viewer. This
          tool allows you to quickly look at events in specific classes and
          hide events that are of no interest by setting up simple
          conditions.</para>

          <para>To write out an XML file the same appender as before is used,
          but the layout is changed. The following configuration logs all
          events (DEBUG and greater) to a file with an XML layout.</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">log4j.rootLogger=DEBUG, XmlFile

log4j.appender.XmlFile=org.apache.log4j.FileAppender
log4j.appender.XmlFile.file=isis.log.xml
log4j.appender.XmlFile.layout=org.apache.log4j.xml.XMLLayout
log4j.appender.XmlFile.append=false</programlisting>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>Writing HTML log files</title>

          <para>HTML files can be viewed in a web browser and will display
          nicely in most email clients. Change the appender to use the
          <classname>HTMLLayout</classname> class.</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific">log4j.appender.Snapshot.layout=org.apache.log4j.HTMLLayout</programlisting>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Using logging to get help</title>

        <para>When you are working with someone else it is often useful to
        send details of what is happening including screenshots, code, and
        logs. To make the other person's life easier provide as much
        information as possible:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Detail the version of the framework and the platform (Java
            or .Net) you are using</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Describe the problem in detail</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Provide screenshots (as a <filename class="directory"
            moreinfo="none">.gif</filename> or <filename class="directory"
            moreinfo="none">.png</filename>, avoid jpegs and Word documents)
            that shows the problem</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Provide log files from both the client and the server in an
            XML format so they can be viewed using Chainsaw</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Include your contact details, preferrably you email
            address</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Collate all this information ensuring each file is clearly
        named. Then zip up (or tar) the whole set (as the logs, in particular,
        can be huge) and email the compressed file.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Adding logging to your code</title>

        <para>It is recommended that you also add logging to your code,
        particularly if you are developing a component or extending the
        framework in some way. This way you will be able to see the
        interaction of your classes with those of the NOF. The following lays
        out how the framework uses Log4j, and hence how you should use it to
        be consistent.</para>

        <para>Simple ensure that any class that does any logging makes a
        <classname>Logger</classname> available. By convention the name is
        always <varname>LOG</varname>. The name of the logger should be the
        name of the class in its fully qualified form. To make this easy use
        the constructor that takes a <classname>Class</classname> object and
        pass in your class using as shown here. Don't forget to add an import
        to <classname>org.apache.log4j.Logger</classname>, not the class of
        the same name in the NOF or in Java itself.</para>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">private final static Logger LOG = Logger.getLogger(IsisClass.class);</programlisting>

        <para>Where you wish to add log message add a statement like the
        following, deciding first what level the event should be classified as
        (see above); the available methods are <methodname>debug</methodname>,
        <methodname>info</methodname>, <methodname>warn</methodname>,
        <methodname>error</methodname> and
        <methodname>fatal</methodname>.</para>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">LOG.debug("mark as dirty " + object);

LOG.error("failed to create instance of " + this, e);</programlisting>

        <para>The first statement in this example contains just a message,
        while the second version logs a message and, separately, the complete
        stack trace.</para>

        <sect3>
          <title>Making you classes useful in logs</title>

          <para>To make the most of logging, even if you don't log anything in
          you code, make sure that you declare a
          <methodname>toString</methodname> method in each of you classes.
          This way when a log message is created that references your object
          the message will show your object in detail rather than like
          this:</para>

          <screen format="linespecific">MyObject@33D4</screen>

          <para>A suitable toString can cause it to be rendered more usefully
          such as:</para>

          <screen format="linespecific">MyObject [name=windows,size=34x20]</screen>

          <para></para>

          <para></para>

          <para></para>

          <para></para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Property naming conventions</title>

      <para>Properties used within the framework start with 'isis', which is
      available from the <literal moreinfo="none">Configuration.ROOT</literal>
      constant. Next is the category and optionally a component. Finally is
      the property name (which can be as many levels as needed) for the
      component. Examples are:</para>

      <programlisting format="linespecific">isis.viewer.cli.log
isis.services.prefix
isis.viewer.dnd.specification.view
isis.exploration.users
isis.viewer.html.header</programlisting>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="chp.DeployingIsisApplications">
    <title>Deployment Principles</title>

    <abstract>
      <para>*** The principles for deploying an <emphasis>Isis</emphasis>
      application.</para>
    </abstract>

    <para>Assuming that you have developed your domain model and tested it as
    a standalone prototype, this part of the guide describes the basic
    deployment options.</para>

    <para>Alternative implementations (most notably, remoting for
    client/server) that allow for different deployments have their own
    guidance on deployment. The same is also true for viewers that allow for
    different deployments (eg a viewer that supports a mobile phone or Eclipse
    OSGi would likely have its own packaging requirements).</para>

    <para></para>

    <para></para>

    <para></para>

    <note>
      <para>TODO: tidy up the following paras, were just copied/pasted in from
      APT</para>
    </note>

    <para></para>

    <para>All the following describe setting up the default security
    implementations. *** Mention that there are other implementations</para>

    <para></para>

    <para></para>

    <para>For desktop-based viewers the framework provides a
    <classname>ViewerInstaller</classname> <acronym>API</acronym>, defined in
    the <filename>core/runtime</filename> module. This approach is used by the
    <acronym>DnD</acronym> viewer and the <acronym>HTML</acronym> viewer, for
    example.</para>

    <para>Alternatively the viewer can use its own mechanism to get started
    (eg as a webapp) and then simply bootstrap the Isis runtime with a couple
    of lines of code. This is the technique used by the Scimpi webapp viewer,
    by the Wicket viewer and by the Restful viewer.</para>

    <para></para>

    <para>*** x-ref remoting docs as a way of deploying in client/server
    mode.</para>

    <para></para>

    <para></para>

    <sect1>
      <title>Adding Security (Authentication and Authorization)</title>

      <para></para>

      <para>x-ref alternatives/security/file</para>

      <para></para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Adding support for internationalisation</title>

      <para>All the text that appears to the user comes from the domain object
      model. Any literal text used within the code may be externalised, and
      localised using the standard Java mechanism of resource bundles. However
      as all field and menu names are derived from the method names the
      framework provides a mechanism to adapt these names using resource
      bundles as well.</para>

      <para></para>

      <para>*** FacetDecorator</para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
</book>
