<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE PLAY SYSTEM "play.dtd">

<PLAY>
<TITLE>The Tragedy of Coriolanus</TITLE>

<FM>
<P>ASCII text placed in the public domain by Moby Lexical Tools, 1992.</P>
<P>SGML markup by Jon Bosak, 1992-1994.</P>
<P>XML version by Jon Bosak, 1996-1999.</P>
<P>The XML markup in this version is Copyright &#169; 1999 Jon Bosak.
This work may freely be distributed on condition that it not be
modified or altered in any way.</P>
</FM>

<PERSONAE>
<TITLE>Dramatis Personae</TITLE>

<PERSONA>CAIUS MARCIUS, Afterwards CAIUS MARCIUS CORIOLANUS.</PERSONA>

<PGROUP>
<PERSONA>TITUS LARTIUS</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>COMINIUS</PERSONA>
<GRPDESCR>generals against the Volscians.</GRPDESCR>
</PGROUP>

<PERSONA>MENENIUS AGRIPPA, friend to Coriolanus. </PERSONA>

<PGROUP>
<PERSONA>SICINIUS VELUTUS</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>JUNIUS BRUTUS</PERSONA>
<GRPDESCR>tribunes of the people.</GRPDESCR>
</PGROUP>

<PERSONA>Young MARCUS, son to Coriolanus.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>A Roman Herald. </PERSONA>
<PERSONA>TULLUS AUFIDIUS, general of the Volscians. </PERSONA>
<PERSONA>Lieutenant to Aufidius. </PERSONA>
<PERSONA>Conspirators with Aufidius.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>A Citizen of Antium.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>Two Volscian Guards.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>VOLUMNIA, mother to Coriolanus.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>VIRGILIA, wife to Coriolanus.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>VALERIA, friend to Virgilia.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>Gentlewoman, attending on Virgilia. </PERSONA>
<PERSONA>Roman and Volscian Senators, Patricians, Aediles, Lictors, Soldiers, Citizens, Messengers, Servants to Aufidius, and other Attendants.</PERSONA>
</PERSONAE>

<SCNDESCR>SCENE  Rome and the neighbourhood; Corioli and the neighbourhood; Antium.</SCNDESCR>

<PLAYSUBT>CORIOLANUS</PLAYSUBT>

<ACT><TITLE>ACT I</TITLE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE I.  Rome. A street.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter a company of mutinous Citizens, with staves,
clubs, and other weapons</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Before we proceed any further, hear me speak.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>All</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Speak, speak.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You are all resolved rather to die than to famish?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>All</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Resolved. resolved.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>First, you know Caius Marcius is chief enemy to the people.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>All</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We know't, we know't.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let us kill him, and we'll have corn at our own price.</LINE>
<LINE>Is't a verdict?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>All</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No more talking on't; let it be done: away, away!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>One word, good citizens.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We are accounted poor citizens, the patricians good.</LINE>
<LINE>What authority surfeits on would relieve us: if they</LINE>
<LINE>would yield us but the superfluity, while it were</LINE>
<LINE>wholesome, we might guess they relieved us humanely;</LINE>
<LINE>but they think we are too dear: the leanness that</LINE>
<LINE>afflicts us, the object of our misery, is as an</LINE>
<LINE>inventory to particularise their abundance; our</LINE>
<LINE>sufferance is a gain to them Let us revenge this with</LINE>
<LINE>our pikes, ere we become rakes: for the gods know I</LINE>
<LINE>speak this in hunger for bread, not in thirst for revenge.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Would you proceed especially against Caius Marcius?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>All</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Against him first: he's a very dog to the commonalty.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Consider you what services he has done for his country?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Very well; and could be content to give him good</LINE>
<LINE>report fort, but that he pays himself with being proud.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, but speak not maliciously.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I say unto you, what he hath done famously, he did</LINE>
<LINE>it to that end: though soft-conscienced men can be</LINE>
<LINE>content to say it was for his country he did it to</LINE>
<LINE>please his mother and to be partly proud; which he</LINE>
<LINE>is, even till the altitude of his virtue.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What he cannot help in his nature, you account a</LINE>
<LINE>vice in him. You must in no way say he is covetous.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If I must not, I need not be barren of accusations;</LINE>
<LINE>he hath faults, with surplus, to tire in repetition.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Shouts within</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>What shouts are these? The other side o' the city</LINE>
<LINE>is risen: why stay we prating here? to the Capitol!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>All</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, come.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Soft! who comes here?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter MENENIUS AGRIPPA</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Worthy Menenius Agrippa; one that hath always loved</LINE>
<LINE>the people.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He's one honest enough: would all the rest were so!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What work's, my countrymen, in hand? where go you</LINE>
<LINE>With bats and clubs? The matter? speak, I pray you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Our business is not unknown to the senate; they have</LINE>
<LINE>had inkling this fortnight what we intend to do,</LINE>
<LINE>which now we'll show 'em in deeds. They say poor</LINE>
<LINE>suitors have strong breaths: they shall know we</LINE>
<LINE>have strong arms too.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, masters, my good friends, mine honest neighbours,</LINE>
<LINE>Will you undo yourselves?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We cannot, sir, we are undone already.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I tell you, friends, most charitable care</LINE>
<LINE>Have the patricians of you. For your wants,</LINE>
<LINE>Your suffering in this dearth, you may as well</LINE>
<LINE>Strike at the heaven with your staves as lift them</LINE>
<LINE>Against the Roman state, whose course will on</LINE>
<LINE>The way it takes, cracking ten thousand curbs</LINE>
<LINE>Of more strong link asunder than can ever</LINE>
<LINE>Appear in your impediment. For the dearth,</LINE>
<LINE>The gods, not the patricians, make it, and</LINE>
<LINE>Your knees to them, not arms, must help. Alack,</LINE>
<LINE>You are transported by calamity</LINE>
<LINE>Thither where more attends you, and you slander</LINE>
<LINE>The helms o' the state, who care for you like fathers,</LINE>
<LINE>When you curse them as enemies.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Care for us! True, indeed! They ne'er cared for us</LINE>
<LINE>yet: suffer us to famish, and their store-houses</LINE>
<LINE>crammed with grain; make edicts for usury, to</LINE>
<LINE>support usurers; repeal daily any wholesome act</LINE>
<LINE>established against the rich, and provide more</LINE>
<LINE>piercing statutes daily, to chain up and restrain</LINE>
<LINE>the poor. If the wars eat us not up, they will; and</LINE>
<LINE>there's all the love they bear us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Either you must</LINE>
<LINE>Confess yourselves wondrous malicious,</LINE>
<LINE>Or be accused of folly. I shall tell you</LINE>
<LINE>A pretty tale: it may be you have heard it;</LINE>
<LINE>But, since it serves my purpose, I will venture</LINE>
<LINE>To stale 't a little more.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, I'll hear it, sir: yet you must not think to</LINE>
<LINE>fob off our disgrace with a tale: but, an 't please</LINE>
<LINE>you, deliver.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>There was a time when all the body's members</LINE>
<LINE>Rebell'd against the belly, thus accused it:</LINE>
<LINE>That only like a gulf it did remain</LINE>
<LINE>I' the midst o' the body, idle and unactive,</LINE>
<LINE>Still cupboarding the viand, never bearing</LINE>
<LINE>Like labour with the rest, where the other instruments</LINE>
<LINE>Did see and hear, devise, instruct, walk, feel,</LINE>
<LINE>And, mutually participate, did minister</LINE>
<LINE>Unto the appetite and affection common</LINE>
<LINE>Of the whole body. The belly answer'd--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, sir, what answer made the belly?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sir, I shall tell you. With a kind of smile,</LINE>
<LINE>Which ne'er came from the lungs, but even thus--</LINE>
<LINE>For, look you, I may make the belly smile</LINE>
<LINE>As well as speak--it tauntingly replied</LINE>
<LINE>To the discontented members, the mutinous parts</LINE>
<LINE>That envied his receipt; even so most fitly</LINE>
<LINE>As you malign our senators for that</LINE>
<LINE>They are not such as you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Your belly's answer? What!</LINE>
<LINE>The kingly-crowned head, the vigilant eye,</LINE>
<LINE>The counsellor heart, the arm our soldier,</LINE>
<LINE>Our steed the leg, the tongue our trumpeter.</LINE>
<LINE>With other muniments and petty helps</LINE>
<LINE>In this our fabric, if that they--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What then?</LINE>
<LINE>'Fore me, this fellow speaks! What then? what then?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Should by the cormorant belly be restrain'd,</LINE>
<LINE>Who is the sink o' the body,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, what then?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The former agents, if they did complain,</LINE>
<LINE>What could the belly answer?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will tell you</LINE>
<LINE>If you'll bestow a small--of what you have little--</LINE>
<LINE>Patience awhile, you'll hear the belly's answer.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ye're long about it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Note me this, good friend;</LINE>
<LINE>Your most grave belly was deliberate,</LINE>
<LINE>Not rash like his accusers, and thus answer'd:</LINE>
<LINE>'True is it, my incorporate friends,' quoth he,</LINE>
<LINE>'That I receive the general food at first,</LINE>
<LINE>Which you do live upon; and fit it is,</LINE>
<LINE>Because I am the store-house and the shop</LINE>
<LINE>Of the whole body: but, if you do remember,</LINE>
<LINE>I send it through the rivers of your blood,</LINE>
<LINE>Even to the court, the heart, to the seat o' the brain;</LINE>
<LINE>And, through the cranks and offices of man,</LINE>
<LINE>The strongest nerves and small inferior veins</LINE>
<LINE>From me receive that natural competency</LINE>
<LINE>Whereby they live: and though that all at once,</LINE>
<LINE>You, my good friends,'--this says the belly, mark me,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, sir; well, well.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Though all at once cannot</LINE>
<LINE>See what I do deliver out to each,</LINE>
<LINE>Yet I can make my audit up, that all</LINE>
<LINE>From me do back receive the flour of all,</LINE>
<LINE>And leave me but the bran.' What say you to't?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It was an answer: how apply you this?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The senators of Rome are this good belly,</LINE>
<LINE>And you the mutinous members; for examine</LINE>
<LINE>Their counsels and their cares, digest things rightly</LINE>
<LINE>Touching the weal o' the common, you shall find</LINE>
<LINE>No public benefit which you receive</LINE>
<LINE>But it proceeds or comes from them to you</LINE>
<LINE>And no way from yourselves. What do you think,</LINE>
<LINE>You, the great toe of this assembly?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I the great toe! why the great toe?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>For that, being one o' the lowest, basest, poorest,</LINE>
<LINE>Of this most wise rebellion, thou go'st foremost:</LINE>
<LINE>Thou rascal, that art worst in blood to run,</LINE>
<LINE>Lead'st first to win some vantage.</LINE>
<LINE>But make you ready your stiff bats and clubs:</LINE>
<LINE>Rome and her rats are at the point of battle;</LINE>
<LINE>The one side must have bale.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter CAIUS MARCIUS</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Hail, noble Marcius!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thanks. What's the matter, you dissentious rogues,</LINE>
<LINE>That, rubbing the poor itch of your opinion,</LINE>
<LINE>Make yourselves scabs?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We have ever your good word.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He that will give good words to thee will flatter</LINE>
<LINE>Beneath abhorring. What would you have, you curs,</LINE>
<LINE>That like nor peace nor war? the one affrights you,</LINE>
<LINE>The other makes you proud. He that trusts to you,</LINE>
<LINE>Where he should find you lions, finds you hares;</LINE>
<LINE>Where foxes, geese: you are no surer, no,</LINE>
<LINE>Than is the coal of fire upon the ice,</LINE>
<LINE>Or hailstone in the sun. Your virtue is</LINE>
<LINE>To make him worthy whose offence subdues him</LINE>
<LINE>And curse that justice did it.</LINE>
<LINE>Who deserves greatness</LINE>
<LINE>Deserves your hate; and your affections are</LINE>
<LINE>A sick man's appetite, who desires most that</LINE>
<LINE>Which would increase his evil. He that depends</LINE>
<LINE>Upon your favours swims with fins of lead</LINE>
<LINE>And hews down oaks with rushes. Hang ye! Trust Ye?</LINE>
<LINE>With every minute you do change a mind,</LINE>
<LINE>And call him noble that was now your hate,</LINE>
<LINE>Him vile that was your garland. What's the matter,</LINE>
<LINE>That in these several places of the city</LINE>
<LINE>You cry against the noble senate, who,</LINE>
<LINE>Under the gods, keep you in awe, which else</LINE>
<LINE>Would feed on one another? What's their seeking?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>For corn at their own rates; whereof, they say,</LINE>
<LINE>The city is well stored.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hang 'em! They say!</LINE>
<LINE>They'll sit by the fire, and presume to know</LINE>
<LINE>What's done i' the Capitol; who's like to rise,</LINE>
<LINE>Who thrives and who declines; side factions</LINE>
<LINE>and give out</LINE>
<LINE>Conjectural marriages; making parties strong</LINE>
<LINE>And feebling such as stand not in their liking</LINE>
<LINE>Below their cobbled shoes. They say there's</LINE>
<LINE>grain enough!</LINE>
<LINE>Would the nobility lay aside their ruth,</LINE>
<LINE>And let me use my sword, I'll make a quarry</LINE>
<LINE>With thousands of these quarter'd slaves, as high</LINE>
<LINE>As I could pick my lance.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, these are almost thoroughly persuaded;</LINE>
<LINE>For though abundantly they lack discretion,</LINE>
<LINE>Yet are they passing cowardly. But, I beseech you,</LINE>
<LINE>What says the other troop?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>They are dissolved: hang 'em!</LINE>
<LINE>They said they were an-hungry; sigh'd forth proverbs,</LINE>
<LINE>That hunger broke stone walls, that dogs must eat,</LINE>
<LINE>That meat was made for mouths, that the gods sent not</LINE>
<LINE>Corn for the rich men only: with these shreds</LINE>
<LINE>They vented their complainings; which being answer'd,</LINE>
<LINE>And a petition granted them, a strange one--</LINE>
<LINE>To break the heart of generosity,</LINE>
<LINE>And make bold power look pale--they threw their caps</LINE>
<LINE>As they would hang them on the horns o' the moon,</LINE>
<LINE>Shouting their emulation.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What is granted them?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Five tribunes to defend their vulgar wisdoms,</LINE>
<LINE>Of their own choice: one's Junius Brutus,</LINE>
<LINE>Sicinius Velutus, and I know not--'Sdeath!</LINE>
<LINE>The rabble should have first unroof'd the city,</LINE>
<LINE>Ere so prevail'd with me: it will in time</LINE>
<LINE>Win upon power and throw forth greater themes</LINE>
<LINE>For insurrection's arguing.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This is strange.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Go, get you home, you fragments!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter a Messenger, hastily</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Messenger</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where's Caius Marcius?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here: what's the matter?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Messenger</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The news is, sir, the Volsces are in arms.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am glad on 't: then we shall ha' means to vent</LINE>
<LINE>Our musty superfluity. See, our best elders.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter COMINIUS, TITUS LARTIUS, and other Senators;
JUNIUS BRUTUS and SICINIUS VELUTUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Marcius, 'tis true that you have lately told us;</LINE>
<LINE>The Volsces are in arms.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>They have a leader,</LINE>
<LINE>Tullus Aufidius, that will put you to 't.</LINE>
<LINE>I sin in envying his nobility,</LINE>
<LINE>And were I any thing but what I am,</LINE>
<LINE>I would wish me only he.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You have fought together.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Were half to half the world by the ears and he.</LINE>
<LINE>Upon my party, I'ld revolt to make</LINE>
<LINE>Only my wars with him: he is a lion</LINE>
<LINE>That I am proud to hunt.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then, worthy Marcius,</LINE>
<LINE>Attend upon Cominius to these wars.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is your former promise.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sir, it is;</LINE>
<LINE>And I am constant. Titus Lartius, thou</LINE>
<LINE>Shalt see me once more strike at Tullus' face.</LINE>
<LINE>What, art thou stiff? stand'st out?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TITUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, Caius Marcius;</LINE>
<LINE>I'll lean upon one crutch and fight with t'other,</LINE>
<LINE>Ere stay behind this business.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, true-bred!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Your company to the Capitol; where, I know,</LINE>
<LINE>Our greatest friends attend us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TITUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>To COMINIUS</STAGEDIR>                Lead you on.</LINE>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>To MARCIUS</STAGEDIR>  Follow Cominius; we must follow you;</LINE>
<LINE>Right worthy you priority.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Noble Marcius!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>To the Citizens</STAGEDIR>  Hence to your homes; be gone!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, let them follow:</LINE>
<LINE>The Volsces have much corn; take these rats thither</LINE>
<LINE>To gnaw their garners. Worshipful mutiners,</LINE>
<LINE>Your valour puts well forth: pray, follow.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Citizens steal away. Exeunt all but SICINIUS
and BRUTUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Was ever man so proud as is this Marcius?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He has no equal.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>When we were chosen tribunes for the people,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Mark'd you his lip and eyes?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay. but his taunts.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Being moved, he will not spare to gird the gods.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Be-mock the modest moon.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The present wars devour him: he is grown</LINE>
<LINE>Too proud to be so valiant.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Such a nature,</LINE>
<LINE>Tickled with good success, disdains the shadow</LINE>
<LINE>Which he treads on at noon: but I do wonder</LINE>
<LINE>His insolence can brook to be commanded</LINE>
<LINE>Under Cominius.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Fame, at the which he aims,</LINE>
<LINE>In whom already he's well graced, can not</LINE>
<LINE>Better be held nor more attain'd than by</LINE>
<LINE>A place below the first: for what miscarries</LINE>
<LINE>Shall be the general's fault, though he perform</LINE>
<LINE>To the utmost of a man, and giddy censure</LINE>
<LINE>Will then cry out of Marcius 'O if he</LINE>
<LINE>Had borne the business!'</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Besides, if things go well,</LINE>
<LINE>Opinion that so sticks on Marcius shall</LINE>
<LINE>Of his demerits rob Cominius.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come:</LINE>
<LINE>Half all Cominius' honours are to Marcius.</LINE>
<LINE>Though Marcius earned them not, and all his faults</LINE>
<LINE>To Marcius shall be honours, though indeed</LINE>
<LINE>In aught he merit not.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let's hence, and hear</LINE>
<LINE>How the dispatch is made, and in what fashion,</LINE>
<LINE>More than his singularity, he goes</LINE>
<LINE>Upon this present action.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Lets along.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE II.  Corioli. The Senate-house.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter TULLUS AUFIDIUS and certain Senators</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So, your opinion is, Aufidius,</LINE>
<LINE>That they of Rome are entered in our counsels</LINE>
<LINE>And know how we proceed.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is it not yours?</LINE>
<LINE>What ever have been thought on in this state,</LINE>
<LINE>That could be brought to bodily act ere Rome</LINE>
<LINE>Had circumvention? 'Tis not four days gone</LINE>
<LINE>Since I heard thence; these are the words: I think</LINE>
<LINE>I have the letter here; yes, here it is.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Reads</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>'They have press'd a power, but it is not known</LINE>
<LINE>Whether for east or west: the dearth is great;</LINE>
<LINE>The people mutinous; and it is rumour'd,</LINE>
<LINE>Cominius, Marcius your old enemy,</LINE>
<LINE>Who is of Rome worse hated than of you,</LINE>
<LINE>And Titus Lartius, a most valiant Roman,</LINE>
<LINE>These three lead on this preparation</LINE>
<LINE>Whither 'tis bent: most likely 'tis for you:</LINE>
<LINE>Consider of it.'</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Our army's in the field</LINE>
<LINE>We never yet made doubt but Rome was ready</LINE>
<LINE>To answer us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nor did you think it folly</LINE>
<LINE>To keep your great pretences veil'd till when</LINE>
<LINE>They needs must show themselves; which</LINE>
<LINE>in the hatching,</LINE>
<LINE>It seem'd, appear'd to Rome. By the discovery.</LINE>
<LINE>We shall be shorten'd in our aim, which was</LINE>
<LINE>To take in many towns ere almost Rome</LINE>
<LINE>Should know we were afoot.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Noble Aufidius,</LINE>
<LINE>Take your commission; hie you to your bands:</LINE>
<LINE>Let us alone to guard Corioli:</LINE>
<LINE>If they set down before 's, for the remove</LINE>
<LINE>Bring your army; but, I think, you'll find</LINE>
<LINE>They've not prepared for us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, doubt not that;</LINE>
<LINE>I speak from certainties. Nay, more,</LINE>
<LINE>Some parcels of their power are forth already,</LINE>
<LINE>And only hitherward. I leave your honours.</LINE>
<LINE>If we and Caius Marcius chance to meet,</LINE>
<LINE>'Tis sworn between us we shall ever strike</LINE>
<LINE>Till one can do no more.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>All</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The gods assist you!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And keep your honours safe!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Farewell.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Farewell.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>All</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Farewell.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE III.  Rome. A room in Marcius' house.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter VOLUMNIA and VIRGILIA they set them down
on two low stools, and sew</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I pray you, daughter, sing; or express yourself in a</LINE>
<LINE>more comfortable sort: if my son were my husband, I</LINE>
<LINE>should freelier rejoice in that absence wherein he</LINE>
<LINE>won honour than in the embracements of his bed where</LINE>
<LINE>he would show most love. When yet he was but</LINE>
<LINE>tender-bodied and the only son of my womb, when</LINE>
<LINE>youth with comeliness plucked all gaze his way, when</LINE>
<LINE>for a day of kings' entreaties a mother should not</LINE>
<LINE>sell him an hour from her beholding, I, considering</LINE>
<LINE>how honour would become such a person. that it was</LINE>
<LINE>no better than picture-like to hang by the wall, if</LINE>
<LINE>renown made it not stir, was pleased to let him seek</LINE>
<LINE>danger where he was like to find fame. To a cruel</LINE>
<LINE>war I sent him; from whence he returned, his brows</LINE>
<LINE>bound with oak. I tell thee, daughter, I sprang not</LINE>
<LINE>more in joy at first hearing he was a man-child</LINE>
<LINE>than now in first seeing he had proved himself a</LINE>
<LINE>man.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VIRGILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But had he died in the business, madam; how then?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then his good report should have been my son; I</LINE>
<LINE>therein would have found issue. Hear me profess</LINE>
<LINE>sincerely: had I a dozen sons, each in my love</LINE>
<LINE>alike and none less dear than thine and my good</LINE>
<LINE>Marcius, I had rather had eleven die nobly for their</LINE>
<LINE>country than one voluptuously surfeit out of action.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter a Gentlewoman</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Gentlewoman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Madam, the Lady Valeria is come to visit you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VIRGILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Beseech you, give me leave to retire myself.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Indeed, you shall not.</LINE>
<LINE>Methinks I hear hither your husband's drum,</LINE>
<LINE>See him pluck Aufidius down by the hair,</LINE>
<LINE>As children from a bear, the Volsces shunning him:</LINE>
<LINE>Methinks I see him stamp thus, and call thus:</LINE>
<LINE>'Come on, you cowards! you were got in fear,</LINE>
<LINE>Though you were born in Rome:' his bloody brow</LINE>
<LINE>With his mail'd hand then wiping, forth he goes,</LINE>
<LINE>Like to a harvest-man that's task'd to mow</LINE>
<LINE>Or all or lose his hire.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VIRGILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>His bloody brow! O Jupiter, no blood!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Away, you fool! it more becomes a man</LINE>
<LINE>Than gilt his trophy: the breasts of Hecuba,</LINE>
<LINE>When she did suckle Hector, look'd not lovelier</LINE>
<LINE>Than Hector's forehead when it spit forth blood</LINE>
<LINE>At Grecian sword, contemning. Tell Valeria,</LINE>
<LINE>We are fit to bid her welcome.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit Gentlewoman</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VIRGILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Heavens bless my lord from fell Aufidius!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He'll beat Aufidius 'head below his knee</LINE>
<LINE>And tread upon his neck.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter VALERIA, with an Usher and Gentlewoman</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My ladies both, good day to you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sweet madam.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VIRGILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am glad to see your ladyship.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How do you both? you are manifest house-keepers.</LINE>
<LINE>What are you sewing here? A fine spot, in good</LINE>
<LINE>faith. How does your little son?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VIRGILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I thank your ladyship; well, good madam.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He had rather see the swords, and hear a drum, than</LINE>
<LINE>look upon his school-master.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O' my word, the father's son: I'll swear,'tis a</LINE>
<LINE>very pretty boy. O' my troth, I looked upon him o'</LINE>
<LINE>Wednesday half an hour together: has such a</LINE>
<LINE>confirmed countenance. I saw him run after a gilded</LINE>
<LINE>butterfly: and when he caught it, he let it go</LINE>
<LINE>again; and after it again; and over and over he</LINE>
<LINE>comes, and again; catched it again; or whether his</LINE>
<LINE>fall enraged him, or how 'twas, he did so set his</LINE>
<LINE>teeth and tear it; O, I warrant it, how he mammocked</LINE>
<LINE>it!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>One on 's father's moods.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Indeed, la, 'tis a noble child.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VIRGILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A crack, madam.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, lay aside your stitchery; I must have you play</LINE>
<LINE>the idle husewife with me this afternoon.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VIRGILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, good madam; I will not out of doors.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not out of doors!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>She shall, she shall.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VIRGILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Indeed, no, by your patience; I'll not over the</LINE>
<LINE>threshold till my lord return from the wars.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Fie, you confine yourself most unreasonably: come,</LINE>
<LINE>you must go visit the good lady that lies in.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VIRGILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will wish her speedy strength, and visit her with</LINE>
<LINE>my prayers; but I cannot go thither.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, I pray you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VIRGILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis not to save labour, nor that I want love.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You would be another Penelope: yet, they say, all</LINE>
<LINE>the yarn she spun in Ulysses' absence did but fill</LINE>
<LINE>Ithaca full of moths. Come; I would your cambric</LINE>
<LINE>were sensible as your finger, that you might leave</LINE>
<LINE>pricking it for pity. Come, you shall go with us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VIRGILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, good madam, pardon me; indeed, I will not forth.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>In truth, la, go with me; and I'll tell you</LINE>
<LINE>excellent news of your husband.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VIRGILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, good madam, there can be none yet.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Verily, I do not jest with you; there came news from</LINE>
<LINE>him last night.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VIRGILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Indeed, madam?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>In earnest, it's true; I heard a senator speak it.</LINE>
<LINE>Thus it is: the Volsces have an army forth; against</LINE>
<LINE>whom Cominius the general is gone, with one part of</LINE>
<LINE>our Roman power: your lord and Titus Lartius are set</LINE>
<LINE>down before their city Corioli; they nothing doubt</LINE>
<LINE>prevailing and to make it brief wars. This is true,</LINE>
<LINE>on mine honour; and so, I pray, go with us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VIRGILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Give me excuse, good madam; I will obey you in every</LINE>
<LINE>thing hereafter.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let her alone, lady: as she is now, she will but</LINE>
<LINE>disease our better mirth.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>In troth, I think she would. Fare you well, then.</LINE>
<LINE>Come, good sweet lady. Prithee, Virgilia, turn thy</LINE>
<LINE>solemness out o' door. and go along with us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VIRGILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, at a word, madam; indeed, I must not. I wish</LINE>
<LINE>you much mirth.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, then, farewell.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE IV.  Before Corioli.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter, with drum and colours, MARCIUS, TITUS
LARTIUS, Captains and Soldiers. To them a
Messenger</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yonder comes news. A wager they have met.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LARTIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My horse to yours, no.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis done.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LARTIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Agreed.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Say, has our general met the enemy?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Messenger</SPEAKER>
<LINE>They lie in view; but have not spoke as yet.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LARTIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So, the good horse is mine.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I'll buy him of you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LARTIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, I'll nor sell nor give him: lend you him I will</LINE>
<LINE>For half a hundred years. Summon the town.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How far off lie these armies?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Messenger</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Within this mile and half.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then shall we hear their 'larum, and they ours.</LINE>
<LINE>Now, Mars, I prithee, make us quick in work,</LINE>
<LINE>That we with smoking swords may march from hence,</LINE>
<LINE>To help our fielded friends! Come, blow thy blast.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>They sound a parley. Enter two Senators with others
on the walls</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Tutus Aufidius, is he within your walls?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, nor a man that fears you less than he,</LINE>
<LINE>That's lesser than a little.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Drums afar off</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Hark! our drums</LINE>
<LINE>Are bringing forth our youth. We'll break our walls,</LINE>
<LINE>Rather than they shall pound us up: our gates,</LINE>
<LINE>Which yet seem shut, we, have but pinn'd with rushes;</LINE>
<LINE>They'll open of themselves.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Alarum afar off</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Hark you. far off!</LINE>
<LINE>There is Aufidius; list, what work he makes</LINE>
<LINE>Amongst your cloven army.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, they are at it!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LARTIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Their noise be our instruction. Ladders, ho!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter the army of the Volsces</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>They fear us not, but issue forth their city.</LINE>
<LINE>Now put your shields before your hearts, and fight</LINE>
<LINE>With hearts more proof than shields. Advance,</LINE>
<LINE>brave Titus:</LINE>
<LINE>They do disdain us much beyond our thoughts,</LINE>
<LINE>Which makes me sweat with wrath. Come on, my fellows:</LINE>
<LINE>He that retires I'll take him for a Volsce,</LINE>
<LINE>And he shall feel mine edge.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Alarum. The Romans are beat back to their
trenches. Re-enter MARCIUS cursing</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>All the contagion of the south light on you,</LINE>
<LINE>You shames of Rome! you herd of--Boils and plagues</LINE>
<LINE>Plaster you o'er, that you may be abhorr'd</LINE>
<LINE>Further than seen and one infect another</LINE>
<LINE>Against the wind a mile! You souls of geese,</LINE>
<LINE>That bear the shapes of men, how have you run</LINE>
<LINE>From slaves that apes would beat! Pluto and hell!</LINE>
<LINE>All hurt behind; backs red, and faces pale</LINE>
<LINE>With flight and agued fear! Mend and charge home,</LINE>
<LINE>Or, by the fires of heaven, I'll leave the foe</LINE>
<LINE>And make my wars on you: look to't: come on;</LINE>
<LINE>If you'll stand fast, we'll beat them to their wives,</LINE>
<LINE>As they us to our trenches followed.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Another alarum. The Volsces fly, and MARCIUS
follows them to the gates</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>So, now the gates are ope: now prove good seconds:</LINE>
<LINE>'Tis for the followers fortune widens them,</LINE>
<LINE>Not for the fliers: mark me, and do the like.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enters the gates</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Soldier</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Fool-hardiness; not I.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Soldier</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nor I.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>MARCIUS is shut in</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Soldier</SPEAKER>
<LINE>See, they have shut him in.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>All</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To the pot, I warrant him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Alarum continues</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Re-enter TITUS LARTIUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LARTIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What is become of Marcius?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>All</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Slain, sir, doubtless.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Soldier</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Following the fliers at the very heels,</LINE>
<LINE>With them he enters; who, upon the sudden,</LINE>
<LINE>Clapp'd to their gates: he is himself alone,</LINE>
<LINE>To answer all the city.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LARTIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O noble fellow!</LINE>
<LINE>Who sensibly outdares his senseless sword,</LINE>
<LINE>And, when it bows, stands up. Thou art left, Marcius:</LINE>
<LINE>A carbuncle entire, as big as thou art,</LINE>
<LINE>Were not so rich a jewel. Thou wast a soldier</LINE>
<LINE>Even to Cato's wish, not fierce and terrible</LINE>
<LINE>Only in strokes; but, with thy grim looks and</LINE>
<LINE>The thunder-like percussion of thy sounds,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou madst thine enemies shake, as if the world</LINE>
<LINE>Were feverous and did tremble.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Re-enter MARCIUS, bleeding, assaulted by the enemy</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Soldier</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Look, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LARTIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O,'tis Marcius!</LINE>
<LINE>Let's fetch him off, or make remain alike.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>They fight, and all enter the city</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE V.  Corioli. A street.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter certain Romans, with spoils</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Roman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This will I carry to Rome.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Roman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And I this.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Roman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A murrain on't! I took this for silver.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Alarum continues still afar off</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Enter MARCIUS and TITUS LARTIUS with a trumpet</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>See here these movers that do prize their hours</LINE>
<LINE>At a crack'd drachm! Cushions, leaden spoons,</LINE>
<LINE>Irons of a doit, doublets that hangmen would</LINE>
<LINE>Bury with those that wore them, these base slaves,</LINE>
<LINE>Ere yet the fight be done, pack up: down with them!</LINE>
<LINE>And hark, what noise the general makes! To him!</LINE>
<LINE>There is the man of my soul's hate, Aufidius,</LINE>
<LINE>Piercing our Romans: then, valiant Titus, take</LINE>
<LINE>Convenient numbers to make good the city;</LINE>
<LINE>Whilst I, with those that have the spirit, will haste</LINE>
<LINE>To help Cominius.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LARTIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Worthy sir, thou bleed'st;</LINE>
<LINE>Thy exercise hath been too violent for</LINE>
<LINE>A second course of fight.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sir, praise me not;</LINE>
<LINE>My work hath yet not warm'd me: fare you well:</LINE>
<LINE>The blood I drop is rather physical</LINE>
<LINE>Than dangerous to me: to Aufidius thus</LINE>
<LINE>I will appear, and fight.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LARTIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now the fair goddess, Fortune,</LINE>
<LINE>Fall deep in love with thee; and her great charms</LINE>
<LINE>Misguide thy opposers' swords! Bold gentleman,</LINE>
<LINE>Prosperity be thy page!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thy friend no less</LINE>
<LINE>Than those she placeth highest! So, farewell.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LARTIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thou worthiest Marcius!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit MARCIUS</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Go, sound thy trumpet in the market-place;</LINE>
<LINE>Call thither all the officers o' the town,</LINE>
<LINE>Where they shall know our mind: away!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE VI.  Near the camp of Cominius.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter COMINIUS, as it were in retire,
with soldiers</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Breathe you, my friends: well fought;</LINE>
<LINE>we are come off</LINE>
<LINE>Like Romans, neither foolish in our stands,</LINE>
<LINE>Nor cowardly in retire: believe me, sirs,</LINE>
<LINE>We shall be charged again. Whiles we have struck,</LINE>
<LINE>By interims and conveying gusts we have heard</LINE>
<LINE>The charges of our friends. Ye Roman gods!</LINE>
<LINE>Lead their successes as we wish our own,</LINE>
<LINE>That both our powers, with smiling</LINE>
<LINE>fronts encountering,</LINE>
<LINE>May give you thankful sacrifice.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter a Messenger</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Thy news?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Messenger</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The citizens of Corioli have issued,</LINE>
<LINE>And given to Lartius and to Marcius battle:</LINE>
<LINE>I saw our party to their trenches driven,</LINE>
<LINE>And then I came away.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Though thou speak'st truth,</LINE>
<LINE>Methinks thou speak'st not well.</LINE>
<LINE>How long is't since?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Messenger</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Above an hour, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis not a mile; briefly we heard their drums:</LINE>
<LINE>How couldst thou in a mile confound an hour,</LINE>
<LINE>And bring thy news so late?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Messenger</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Spies of the Volsces</LINE>
<LINE>Held me in chase, that I was forced to wheel</LINE>
<LINE>Three or four miles about, else had I, sir,</LINE>
<LINE>Half an hour since brought my report.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Who's yonder,</LINE>
<LINE>That does appear as he were flay'd? O gods</LINE>
<LINE>He has the stamp of Marcius; and I have</LINE>
<LINE>Before-time seen him thus.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>Within</STAGEDIR>                 Come I too late?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The shepherd knows not thunder from a tabour</LINE>
<LINE>More than I know the sound of Marcius' tongue</LINE>
<LINE>From every meaner man.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter MARCIUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come I too late?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, if you come not in the blood of others,</LINE>
<LINE>But mantled in your own.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, let me clip ye</LINE>
<LINE>In arms as sound as when I woo'd, in heart</LINE>
<LINE>As merry as when our nuptial day was done,</LINE>
<LINE>And tapers burn'd to bedward!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Flower of warriors,</LINE>
<LINE>How is it with Titus Lartius?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>As with a man busied about decrees:</LINE>
<LINE>Condemning some to death, and some to exile;</LINE>
<LINE>Ransoming him, or pitying, threatening the other;</LINE>
<LINE>Holding Corioli in the name of Rome,</LINE>
<LINE>Even like a fawning greyhound in the leash,</LINE>
<LINE>To let him slip at will.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where is that slave</LINE>
<LINE>Which told me they had beat you to your trenches?</LINE>
<LINE>Where is he? call him hither.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let him alone;</LINE>
<LINE>He did inform the truth: but for our gentlemen,</LINE>
<LINE>The common file--a plague! tribunes for them!--</LINE>
<LINE>The mouse ne'er shunn'd the cat as they did budge</LINE>
<LINE>From rascals worse than they.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But how prevail'd you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Will the time serve to tell? I do not think.</LINE>
<LINE>Where is the enemy? are you lords o' the field?</LINE>
<LINE>If not, why cease you till you are so?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Marcius,</LINE>
<LINE>We have at disadvantage fought and did</LINE>
<LINE>Retire to win our purpose.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How lies their battle? know you on which side</LINE>
<LINE>They have placed their men of trust?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>As I guess, Marcius,</LINE>
<LINE>Their bands i' the vaward are the Antiates,</LINE>
<LINE>Of their best trust; o'er them Aufidius,</LINE>
<LINE>Their very heart of hope.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do beseech you,</LINE>
<LINE>By all the battles wherein we have fought,</LINE>
<LINE>By the blood we have shed together, by the vows</LINE>
<LINE>We have made to endure friends, that you directly</LINE>
<LINE>Set me against Aufidius and his Antiates;</LINE>
<LINE>And that you not delay the present, but,</LINE>
<LINE>Filling the air with swords advanced and darts,</LINE>
<LINE>We prove this very hour.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Though I could wish</LINE>
<LINE>You were conducted to a gentle bath</LINE>
<LINE>And balms applied to, you, yet dare I never</LINE>
<LINE>Deny your asking: take your choice of those</LINE>
<LINE>That best can aid your action.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Those are they</LINE>
<LINE>That most are willing. If any such be here--</LINE>
<LINE>As it were sin to doubt--that love this painting</LINE>
<LINE>Wherein you see me smear'd; if any fear</LINE>
<LINE>Lesser his person than an ill report;</LINE>
<LINE>If any think brave death outweighs bad life</LINE>
<LINE>And that his country's dearer than himself;</LINE>
<LINE>Let him alone, or so many so minded,</LINE>
<LINE>Wave thus, to express his disposition,</LINE>
<LINE>And follow Marcius.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>They all shout and wave their swords, take him up in
their arms, and cast up their caps</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>O, me alone! make you a sword of me?</LINE>
<LINE>If these shows be not outward, which of you</LINE>
<LINE>But is four Volsces? none of you but is</LINE>
<LINE>Able to bear against the great Aufidius</LINE>
<LINE>A shield as hard as his. A certain number,</LINE>
<LINE>Though thanks to all, must I select</LINE>
<LINE>from all: the rest</LINE>
<LINE>Shall bear the business in some other fight,</LINE>
<LINE>As cause will be obey'd. Please you to march;</LINE>
<LINE>And four shall quickly draw out my command,</LINE>
<LINE>Which men are best inclined.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>March on, my fellows:</LINE>
<LINE>Make good this ostentation, and you shall</LINE>
<LINE>Divide in all with us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE VII.  The gates of Corioli.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>TITUS LARTIUS, having set a guard upon
Corioli, going with drum and trumpet toward
COMINIUS and CAIUS MARCIUS, enters with
Lieutenant, other Soldiers, and a Scout</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LARTIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So, let the ports be guarded: keep your duties,</LINE>
<LINE>As I have set them down. If I do send, dispatch</LINE>
<LINE>Those centuries to our aid: the rest will serve</LINE>
<LINE>For a short holding: if we lose the field,</LINE>
<LINE>We cannot keep the town.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Lieutenant</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Fear not our care, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LARTIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hence, and shut your gates upon's.</LINE>
<LINE>Our guider, come; to the Roman camp conduct us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE VIII.  A field of battle.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Alarum as in battle. Enter, from opposite sides,
MARCIUS and AUFIDIUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I'll fight with none but thee; for I do hate thee</LINE>
<LINE>Worse than a promise-breaker.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We hate alike:</LINE>
<LINE>Not Afric owns a serpent I abhor</LINE>
<LINE>More than thy fame and envy. Fix thy foot.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let the first budger die the other's slave,</LINE>
<LINE>And the gods doom him after!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If I fly, Marcius,</LINE>
<LINE>Holloa me like a hare.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Within these three hours, Tullus,</LINE>
<LINE>Alone I fought in your Corioli walls,</LINE>
<LINE>And made what work I pleased: 'tis not my blood</LINE>
<LINE>Wherein thou seest me mask'd; for thy revenge</LINE>
<LINE>Wrench up thy power to the highest.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Wert thou the Hector</LINE>
<LINE>That was the whip of your bragg'd progeny,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou shouldst not scape me here.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>They fight, and certain Volsces come to the aid of
AUFIDIUS. MARCIUS fights till they be driven in
breathless</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Officious, and not valiant, you have shamed me</LINE>
<LINE>In your condemned seconds.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE IX.  The Roman camp.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Flourish. Alarum. A retreat is sounded. Flourish.
Enter, from one side, COMINIUS with the Romans; from
the other side, MARCIUS, with his arm in a scarf</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If I should tell thee o'er this thy day's work,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou'ldst not believe thy deeds: but I'll report it</LINE>
<LINE>Where senators shall mingle tears with smiles,</LINE>
<LINE>Where great patricians shall attend and shrug,</LINE>
<LINE>I' the end admire, where ladies shall be frighted,</LINE>
<LINE>And, gladly quaked, hear more; where the</LINE>
<LINE>dull tribunes,</LINE>
<LINE>That, with the fusty plebeians, hate thine honours,</LINE>
<LINE>Shall say against their hearts 'We thank the gods</LINE>
<LINE>Our Rome hath such a soldier.'</LINE>
<LINE>Yet camest thou to a morsel of this feast,</LINE>
<LINE>Having fully dined before.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter TITUS LARTIUS, with his power,
from the pursuit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LARTIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O general,</LINE>
<LINE>Here is the steed, we the caparison:</LINE>
<LINE>Hadst thou beheld--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pray now, no more: my mother,</LINE>
<LINE>Who has a charter to extol her blood,</LINE>
<LINE>When she does praise me grieves me. I have done</LINE>
<LINE>As you have done; that's what I can; induced</LINE>
<LINE>As you have been; that's for my country:</LINE>
<LINE>He that has but effected his good will</LINE>
<LINE>Hath overta'en mine act.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You shall not be</LINE>
<LINE>The grave of your deserving; Rome must know</LINE>
<LINE>The value of her own: 'twere a concealment</LINE>
<LINE>Worse than a theft, no less than a traducement,</LINE>
<LINE>To hide your doings; and to silence that,</LINE>
<LINE>Which, to the spire and top of praises vouch'd,</LINE>
<LINE>Would seem but modest: therefore, I beseech you</LINE>
<LINE>In sign of what you are, not to reward</LINE>
<LINE>What you have done--before our army hear me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have some wounds upon me, and they smart</LINE>
<LINE>To hear themselves remember'd.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Should they not,</LINE>
<LINE>Well might they fester 'gainst ingratitude,</LINE>
<LINE>And tent themselves with death. Of all the horses,</LINE>
<LINE>Whereof we have ta'en good and good store, of all</LINE>
<LINE>The treasure in this field achieved and city,</LINE>
<LINE>We render you the tenth, to be ta'en forth,</LINE>
<LINE>Before the common distribution, at</LINE>
<LINE>Your only choice.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I thank you, general;</LINE>
<LINE>But cannot make my heart consent to take</LINE>
<LINE>A bribe to pay my sword: I do refuse it;</LINE>
<LINE>And stand upon my common part with those</LINE>
<LINE>That have beheld the doing.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>A long flourish. They all cry 'Marcius! Marcius!'
cast up their caps and lances: COMINIUS and LARTIUS
stand bare</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>May these same instruments, which you profane,</LINE>
<LINE>Never sound more! when drums and trumpets shall</LINE>
<LINE>I' the field prove flatterers, let courts and cities be</LINE>
<LINE>Made all of false-faced soothing!</LINE>
<LINE>When steel grows soft as the parasite's silk,</LINE>
<LINE>Let him be made a coverture for the wars!</LINE>
<LINE>No more, I say! For that I have not wash'd</LINE>
<LINE>My nose that bled, or foil'd some debile wretch.--</LINE>
<LINE>Which, without note, here's many else have done,--</LINE>
<LINE>You shout me forth</LINE>
<LINE>In acclamations hyperbolical;</LINE>
<LINE>As if I loved my little should be dieted</LINE>
<LINE>In praises sauced with lies.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Too modest are you;</LINE>
<LINE>More cruel to your good report than grateful</LINE>
<LINE>To us that give you truly: by your patience,</LINE>
<LINE>If 'gainst yourself you be incensed, we'll put you,</LINE>
<LINE>Like one that means his proper harm, in manacles,</LINE>
<LINE>Then reason safely with you. Therefore, be it known,</LINE>
<LINE>As to us, to all the world, that Caius Marcius</LINE>
<LINE>Wears this war's garland: in token of the which,</LINE>
<LINE>My noble steed, known to the camp, I give him,</LINE>
<LINE>With all his trim belonging; and from this time,</LINE>
<LINE>For what he did before Corioli, call him,</LINE>
<LINE>With all the applause and clamour of the host,</LINE>
<LINE>CAIUS MARCIUS CORIOLANUS! Bear</LINE>
<LINE>The addition nobly ever!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Flourish. Trumpets sound, and drums</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>All</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Caius Marcius Coriolanus!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will go wash;</LINE>
<LINE>And when my face is fair, you shall perceive</LINE>
<LINE>Whether I blush or no: howbeit, I thank you.</LINE>
<LINE>I mean to stride your steed, and at all times</LINE>
<LINE>To undercrest your good addition</LINE>
<LINE>To the fairness of my power.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So, to our tent;</LINE>
<LINE>Where, ere we do repose us, we will write</LINE>
<LINE>To Rome of our success. You, Titus Lartius,</LINE>
<LINE>Must to Corioli back: send us to Rome</LINE>
<LINE>The best, with whom we may articulate,</LINE>
<LINE>For their own good and ours.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LARTIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I shall, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The gods begin to mock me. I, that now</LINE>
<LINE>Refused most princely gifts, am bound to beg</LINE>
<LINE>Of my lord general.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Take't; 'tis yours. What is't?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I sometime lay here in Corioli</LINE>
<LINE>At a poor man's house; he used me kindly:</LINE>
<LINE>He cried to me; I saw him prisoner;</LINE>
<LINE>But then Aufidius was within my view,</LINE>
<LINE>And wrath o'erwhelm'd my pity: I request you</LINE>
<LINE>To give my poor host freedom.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, well begg'd!</LINE>
<LINE>Were he the butcher of my son, he should</LINE>
<LINE>Be free as is the wind. Deliver him, Titus.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LARTIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Marcius, his name?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>By Jupiter! forgot.</LINE>
<LINE>I am weary; yea, my memory is tired.</LINE>
<LINE>Have we no wine here?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Go we to our tent:</LINE>
<LINE>The blood upon your visage dries; 'tis time</LINE>
<LINE>It should be look'd to: come.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE X.  The camp of the Volsces.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>A flourish. Cornets. Enter TULLUS AUFIDIUS,
bloody, with two or three Soldiers</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The town is ta'en!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Soldier</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Twill be deliver'd back on good condition.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Condition!</LINE>
<LINE>I would I were a Roman; for I cannot,</LINE>
<LINE>Being a Volsce, be that I am. Condition!</LINE>
<LINE>What good condition can a treaty find</LINE>
<LINE>I' the part that is at mercy? Five times, Marcius,</LINE>
<LINE>I have fought with thee: so often hast thou beat me,</LINE>
<LINE>And wouldst do so, I think, should we encounter</LINE>
<LINE>As often as we eat. By the elements,</LINE>
<LINE>If e'er again I meet him beard to beard,</LINE>
<LINE>He's mine, or I am his: mine emulation</LINE>
<LINE>Hath not that honour in't it had; for where</LINE>
<LINE>I thought to crush him in an equal force,</LINE>
<LINE>True sword to sword, I'll potch at him some way</LINE>
<LINE>Or wrath or craft may get him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Soldier</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He's the devil.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Bolder, though not so subtle. My valour's poison'd</LINE>
<LINE>With only suffering stain by him; for him</LINE>
<LINE>Shall fly out of itself: nor sleep nor sanctuary,</LINE>
<LINE>Being naked, sick, nor fane nor Capitol,</LINE>
<LINE>The prayers of priests nor times of sacrifice,</LINE>
<LINE>Embarquements all of fury, shall lift up</LINE>
<LINE>Their rotten privilege and custom 'gainst</LINE>
<LINE>My hate to Marcius: where I find him, were it</LINE>
<LINE>At home, upon my brother's guard, even there,</LINE>
<LINE>Against the hospitable canon, would I</LINE>
<LINE>Wash my fierce hand in's heart. Go you to the city;</LINE>
<LINE>Learn how 'tis held; and what they are that must</LINE>
<LINE>Be hostages for Rome.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Soldier</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Will not you go?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am attended at the cypress grove: I pray you--</LINE>
<LINE>'Tis south the city mills--bring me word thither</LINE>
<LINE>How the world goes, that to the pace of it</LINE>
<LINE>I may spur on my journey.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Soldier</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I shall, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

</ACT>

<ACT><TITLE>ACT II</TITLE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE I.  Rome. A public place.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter MENENIUS with the two Tribunes of the people,
SICINIUS and BRUTUS.</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The augurer tells me we shall have news to-night.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good or bad?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not according to the prayer of the people, for they</LINE>
<LINE>love not Marcius.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nature teaches beasts to know their friends.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pray you, who does the wolf love?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The lamb.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, to devour him; as the hungry plebeians would the</LINE>
<LINE>noble Marcius.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He's a lamb indeed, that baes like a bear.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He's a bear indeed, that lives like a lamb. You two</LINE>
<LINE>are old men: tell me one thing that I shall ask you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Both</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>In what enormity is Marcius poor in, that you two</LINE>
<LINE>have not in abundance?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He's poor in no one fault, but stored with all.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Especially in pride.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And topping all others in boasting.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This is strange now: do you two know how you are</LINE>
<LINE>censured here in the city, I mean of us o' the</LINE>
<LINE>right-hand file? do you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Both</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, how are we censured?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Because you talk of pride now,--will you not be angry?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Both</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, well, sir, well.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, 'tis no great matter; for a very little thief of</LINE>
<LINE>occasion will rob you of a great deal of patience:</LINE>
<LINE>give your dispositions the reins, and be angry at</LINE>
<LINE>your pleasures; at the least if you take it as a</LINE>
<LINE>pleasure to you in being so. You blame Marcius for</LINE>
<LINE>being proud?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We do it not alone, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know you can do very little alone; for your helps</LINE>
<LINE>are many, or else your actions would grow wondrous</LINE>
<LINE>single: your abilities are too infant-like for</LINE>
<LINE>doing much alone. You talk of pride: O that you</LINE>
<LINE>could turn your eyes toward the napes of your necks,</LINE>
<LINE>and make but an interior survey of your good selves!</LINE>
<LINE>O that you could!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What then, sir?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, then you should discover a brace of unmeriting,</LINE>
<LINE>proud, violent, testy magistrates, alias fools, as</LINE>
<LINE>any in Rome.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Menenius, you are known well enough too.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am known to be a humorous patrician, and one that</LINE>
<LINE>loves a cup of hot wine with not a drop of allaying</LINE>
<LINE>Tiber in't; said to be something imperfect in</LINE>
<LINE>favouring the first complaint; hasty and tinder-like</LINE>
<LINE>upon too trivial motion; one that converses more</LINE>
<LINE>with the buttock of the night than with the forehead</LINE>
<LINE>of the morning: what I think I utter, and spend my</LINE>
<LINE>malice in my breath. Meeting two such wealsmen as</LINE>
<LINE>you are--I cannot call you Lycurguses--if the drink</LINE>
<LINE>you give me touch my palate adversely, I make a</LINE>
<LINE>crooked face at it. I can't say your worships have</LINE>
<LINE>delivered the matter well, when I find the ass in</LINE>
<LINE>compound with the major part of your syllables: and</LINE>
<LINE>though I must be content to bear with those that say</LINE>
<LINE>you are reverend grave men, yet they lie deadly that</LINE>
<LINE>tell you you have good faces. If you see this in</LINE>
<LINE>the map of my microcosm, follows it that I am known</LINE>
<LINE>well enough too? what barm can your bisson</LINE>
<LINE>conspectuities glean out of this character, if I be</LINE>
<LINE>known well enough too?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, sir, come, we know you well enough.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You know neither me, yourselves nor any thing. You</LINE>
<LINE>are ambitious for poor knaves' caps and legs: you</LINE>
<LINE>wear out a good wholesome forenoon in hearing a</LINE>
<LINE>cause between an orange wife and a fosset-seller;</LINE>
<LINE>and then rejourn the controversy of three pence to a</LINE>
<LINE>second day of audience. When you are hearing a</LINE>
<LINE>matter between party and party, if you chance to be</LINE>
<LINE>pinched with the colic, you make faces like</LINE>
<LINE>mummers; set up the bloody flag against all</LINE>
<LINE>patience; and, in roaring for a chamber-pot,</LINE>
<LINE>dismiss the controversy bleeding the more entangled</LINE>
<LINE>by your hearing: all the peace you make in their</LINE>
<LINE>cause is, calling both the parties knaves. You are</LINE>
<LINE>a pair of strange ones.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, come, you are well understood to be a</LINE>
<LINE>perfecter giber for the table than a necessary</LINE>
<LINE>bencher in the Capitol.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Our very priests must become mockers, if they shall</LINE>
<LINE>encounter such ridiculous subjects as you are. When</LINE>
<LINE>you speak best unto the purpose, it is not worth the</LINE>
<LINE>wagging of your beards; and your beards deserve not</LINE>
<LINE>so honourable a grave as to stuff a botcher's</LINE>
<LINE>cushion, or to be entombed in an ass's pack-</LINE>
<LINE>saddle. Yet you must be saying, Marcius is proud;</LINE>
<LINE>who in a cheap estimation, is worth predecessors</LINE>
<LINE>since Deucalion, though peradventure some of the</LINE>
<LINE>best of 'em were hereditary hangmen. God-den to</LINE>
<LINE>your worships: more of your conversation would</LINE>
<LINE>infect my brain, being the herdsmen of the beastly</LINE>
<LINE>plebeians: I will be bold to take my leave of you.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>BRUTUS and SICINIUS go aside</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Enter VOLUMNIA, VIRGILIA, and VALERIA</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>How now, my as fair as noble ladies,--and the moon,</LINE>
<LINE>were she earthly, no nobler,--whither do you follow</LINE>
<LINE>your eyes so fast?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Honourable Menenius, my boy Marcius approaches; for</LINE>
<LINE>the love of Juno, let's go.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ha! Marcius coming home!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, worthy Menenius; and with most prosperous</LINE>
<LINE>approbation.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Take my cap, Jupiter, and I thank thee. Hoo!</LINE>
<LINE>Marcius coming home!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<SPEAKER>VIRGILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay,'tis true.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Look, here's a letter from him: the state hath</LINE>
<LINE>another, his wife another; and, I think, there's one</LINE>
<LINE>at home for you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will make my very house reel tonight: a letter for</LINE>
<LINE>me!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VIRGILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yes, certain, there's a letter for you; I saw't.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A letter for me! it gives me an estate of seven</LINE>
<LINE>years' health; in which time I will make a lip at</LINE>
<LINE>the physician: the most sovereign prescription in</LINE>
<LINE>Galen is but empiricutic, and, to this preservative,</LINE>
<LINE>of no better report than a horse-drench. Is he</LINE>
<LINE>not wounded? he was wont to come home wounded.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VIRGILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, no, no, no.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, he is wounded; I thank the gods for't.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So do I too, if it be not too much: brings a'</LINE>
<LINE>victory in his pocket? the wounds become him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>On's brows: Menenius, he comes the third time home</LINE>
<LINE>with the oaken garland.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Has he disciplined Aufidius soundly?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Titus Lartius writes, they fought together, but</LINE>
<LINE>Aufidius got off.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And 'twas time for him too, I'll warrant him that:</LINE>
<LINE>an he had stayed by him, I would not have been so</LINE>
<LINE>fidiused for all the chests in Corioli, and the gold</LINE>
<LINE>that's in them. Is the senate possessed of this?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good ladies, let's go. Yes, yes, yes; the senate</LINE>
<LINE>has letters from the general, wherein he gives my</LINE>
<LINE>son the whole name of the war: he hath in this</LINE>
<LINE>action outdone his former deeds doubly</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VALERIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>In troth, there's wondrous things spoke of him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Wondrous! ay, I warrant you, and not without his</LINE>
<LINE>true purchasing.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VIRGILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The gods grant them true!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>True! pow, wow.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>True! I'll be sworn they are true.</LINE>
<LINE>Where is he wounded?</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>To the Tribunes</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>God save your good worships! Marcius is coming</LINE>
<LINE>home: he has more cause to be proud. Where is he wounded?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I' the shoulder and i' the left arm there will be</LINE>
<LINE>large cicatrices to show the people, when he shall</LINE>
<LINE>stand for his place. He received in the repulse of</LINE>
<LINE>Tarquin seven hurts i' the body.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>One i' the neck, and two i' the thigh,--there's</LINE>
<LINE>nine that I know.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He had, before this last expedition, twenty-five</LINE>
<LINE>wounds upon him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now it's twenty-seven: every gash was an enemy's grave.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>A shout and flourish</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Hark! the trumpets.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>These are the ushers of Marcius: before him he</LINE>
<LINE>carries noise, and behind him he leaves tears:</LINE>
<LINE>Death, that dark spirit, in 's nervy arm doth lie;</LINE>
<LINE>Which, being advanced, declines, and then men die.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>A sennet. Trumpets sound. Enter COMINIUS the
general, and TITUS LARTIUS; between them, CORIOLANUS,
crowned with an oaken garland; with Captains and
Soldiers, and a Herald</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Herald</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Know, Rome, that all alone Marcius did fight</LINE>
<LINE>Within Corioli gates: where he hath won,</LINE>
<LINE>With fame, a name to Caius Marcius; these</LINE>
<LINE>In honour follows Coriolanus.</LINE>
<LINE>Welcome to Rome, renowned Coriolanus!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Flourish</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>All</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Welcome to Rome, renowned Coriolanus!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No more of this; it does offend my heart:</LINE>
<LINE>Pray now, no more.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Look, sir, your mother!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O,</LINE>
<LINE>You have, I know, petition'd all the gods</LINE>
<LINE>For my prosperity!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Kneels</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, my good soldier, up;</LINE>
<LINE>My gentle Marcius, worthy Caius, and</LINE>
<LINE>By deed-achieving honour newly named,--</LINE>
<LINE>What is it?--Coriolanus must I call thee?--</LINE>
<LINE>But O, thy wife!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My gracious silence, hail!</LINE>
<LINE>Wouldst thou have laugh'd had I come coffin'd home,</LINE>
<LINE>That weep'st to see me triumph? Ay, my dear,</LINE>
<LINE>Such eyes the widows in Corioli wear,</LINE>
<LINE>And mothers that lack sons.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now, the gods crown thee!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And live you yet?</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>To VALERIA</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>O my sweet lady, pardon.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know not where to turn: O, welcome home:</LINE>
<LINE>And welcome, general: and ye're welcome all.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A hundred thousand welcomes. I could weep</LINE>
<LINE>And I could laugh, I am light and heavy. Welcome.</LINE>
<LINE>A curse begin at very root on's heart,</LINE>
<LINE>That is not glad to see thee! You are three</LINE>
<LINE>That Rome should dote on: yet, by the faith of men,</LINE>
<LINE>We have some old crab-trees here</LINE>
<LINE>at home that will not</LINE>
<LINE>Be grafted to your relish. Yet welcome, warriors:</LINE>
<LINE>We call a nettle but a nettle and</LINE>
<LINE>The faults of fools but folly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ever right.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Menenius ever, ever.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Herald</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Give way there, and go on!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>To VOLUMNIA and VIRGILIA</STAGEDIR>  Your hand, and yours:</LINE>
<LINE>Ere in our own house I do shade my head,</LINE>
<LINE>The good patricians must be visited;</LINE>
<LINE>From whom I have received not only greetings,</LINE>
<LINE>But with them change of honours.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have lived</LINE>
<LINE>To see inherited my very wishes</LINE>
<LINE>And the buildings of my fancy: only</LINE>
<LINE>There's one thing wanting, which I doubt not but</LINE>
<LINE>Our Rome will cast upon thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Know, good mother,</LINE>
<LINE>I had rather be their servant in my way,</LINE>
<LINE>Than sway with them in theirs.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>On, to the Capitol!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Flourish. Cornets. Exeunt in state, as before.
BRUTUS and SICINIUS come forward</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>All tongues speak of him, and the bleared sights</LINE>
<LINE>Are spectacled to see him: your prattling nurse</LINE>
<LINE>Into a rapture lets her baby cry</LINE>
<LINE>While she chats him: the kitchen malkin pins</LINE>
<LINE>Her richest lockram 'bout her reechy neck,</LINE>
<LINE>Clambering the walls to eye him: stalls, bulks, windows,</LINE>
<LINE>Are smother'd up, leads fill'd, and ridges horsed</LINE>
<LINE>With variable complexions, all agreeing</LINE>
<LINE>In earnestness to see him: seld-shown flamens</LINE>
<LINE>Do press among the popular throngs and puff</LINE>
<LINE>To win a vulgar station: or veil'd dames</LINE>
<LINE>Commit the war of white and damask in</LINE>
<LINE>Their nicely-gawded cheeks to the wanton spoil</LINE>
<LINE>Of Phoebus' burning kisses: such a pother</LINE>
<LINE>As if that whatsoever god who leads him</LINE>
<LINE>Were slily crept into his human powers</LINE>
<LINE>And gave him graceful posture.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>On the sudden,</LINE>
<LINE>I warrant him consul.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then our office may,</LINE>
<LINE>During his power, go sleep.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He cannot temperately transport his honours</LINE>
<LINE>From where he should begin and end, but will</LINE>
<LINE>Lose those he hath won.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>In that there's comfort.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Doubt not</LINE>
<LINE>The commoners, for whom we stand, but they</LINE>
<LINE>Upon their ancient malice will forget</LINE>
<LINE>With the least cause these his new honours, which</LINE>
<LINE>That he will give them make I as little question</LINE>
<LINE>As he is proud to do't.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I heard him swear,</LINE>
<LINE>Were he to stand for consul, never would he</LINE>
<LINE>Appear i' the market-place nor on him put</LINE>
<LINE>The napless vesture of humility;</LINE>
<LINE>Nor showing, as the manner is, his wounds</LINE>
<LINE>To the people, beg their stinking breaths.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis right.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It was his word: O, he would miss it rather</LINE>
<LINE>Than carry it but by the suit of the gentry to him,</LINE>
<LINE>And the desire of the nobles.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I wish no better</LINE>
<LINE>Than have him hold that purpose and to put it</LINE>
<LINE>In execution.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis most like he will.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It shall be to him then as our good wills,</LINE>
<LINE>A sure destruction.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So it must fall out</LINE>
<LINE>To him or our authorities. For an end,</LINE>
<LINE>We must suggest the people in what hatred</LINE>
<LINE>He still hath held them; that to's power he would</LINE>
<LINE>Have made them mules, silenced their pleaders and</LINE>
<LINE>Dispropertied their freedoms, holding them,</LINE>
<LINE>In human action and capacity,</LINE>
<LINE>Of no more soul nor fitness for the world</LINE>
<LINE>Than camels in the war, who have their provand</LINE>
<LINE>Only for bearing burdens, and sore blows</LINE>
<LINE>For sinking under them.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This, as you say, suggested</LINE>
<LINE>At some time when his soaring insolence</LINE>
<LINE>Shall touch the people--which time shall not want,</LINE>
<LINE>If he be put upon 't; and that's as easy</LINE>
<LINE>As to set dogs on sheep--will be his fire</LINE>
<LINE>To kindle their dry stubble; and their blaze</LINE>
<LINE>Shall darken him for ever.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter a Messenger</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What's the matter?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Messenger</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You are sent for to the Capitol. 'Tis thought</LINE>
<LINE>That Marcius shall be consul:</LINE>
<LINE>I have seen the dumb men throng to see him and</LINE>
<LINE>The blind to bear him speak: matrons flung gloves,</LINE>
<LINE>Ladies and maids their scarfs and handkerchers,</LINE>
<LINE>Upon him as he pass'd: the nobles bended,</LINE>
<LINE>As to Jove's statue, and the commons made</LINE>
<LINE>A shower and thunder with their caps and shouts:</LINE>
<LINE>I never saw the like.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let's to the Capitol;</LINE>
<LINE>And carry with us ears and eyes for the time,</LINE>
<LINE>But hearts for the event.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Have with you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE  II.  The same. The Capitol.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter two Officers, to lay cushions</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Officer</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, come, they are almost here. How many stand</LINE>
<LINE>for consulships?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Officer</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Three, they say: but 'tis thought of every one</LINE>
<LINE>Coriolanus will carry it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Officer</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That's a brave fellow; but he's vengeance proud, and</LINE>
<LINE>loves not the common people.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Officer</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Faith, there had been many great men that have</LINE>
<LINE>flattered the people, who ne'er loved them; and there</LINE>
<LINE>be many that they have loved, they know not</LINE>
<LINE>wherefore: so that, if they love they know not why,</LINE>
<LINE>they hate upon no better a ground: therefore, for</LINE>
<LINE>Coriolanus neither to care whether they love or hate</LINE>
<LINE>him manifests the true knowledge he has in their</LINE>
<LINE>disposition; and out of his noble carelessness lets</LINE>
<LINE>them plainly see't.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Officer</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If he did not care whether he had their love or no,</LINE>
<LINE>he waved indifferently 'twixt doing them neither</LINE>
<LINE>good nor harm: but he seeks their hate with greater</LINE>
<LINE>devotion than can render it him; and leaves</LINE>
<LINE>nothing undone that may fully discover him their</LINE>
<LINE>opposite. Now, to seem to affect the malice and</LINE>
<LINE>displeasure of the people is as bad as that which he</LINE>
<LINE>dislikes, to flatter them for their love.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Officer</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He hath deserved worthily of his country: and his</LINE>
<LINE>ascent is not by such easy degrees as those who,</LINE>
<LINE>having been supple and courteous to the people,</LINE>
<LINE>bonneted, without any further deed to have them at</LINE>
<LINE>an into their estimation and report: but he hath so</LINE>
<LINE>planted his honours in their eyes, and his actions</LINE>
<LINE>in their hearts, that for their tongues to be</LINE>
<LINE>silent, and not confess so much, were a kind of</LINE>
<LINE>ingrateful injury; to report otherwise, were a</LINE>
<LINE>malice, that, giving itself the lie, would pluck</LINE>
<LINE>reproof and rebuke from every ear that heard it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Officer</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No more of him; he is a worthy man: make way, they</LINE>
<LINE>are coming.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>A sennet. Enter, with actors before them, COMINIUS
the consul, MENENIUS, CORIOLANUS, Senators,
SICINIUS and BRUTUS. The Senators take their
places; the Tribunes take their Places by
themselves. CORIOLANUS stands</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Having determined of the Volsces and</LINE>
<LINE>To send for Titus Lartius, it remains,</LINE>
<LINE>As the main point of this our after-meeting,</LINE>
<LINE>To gratify his noble service that</LINE>
<LINE>Hath thus stood for his country: therefore,</LINE>
<LINE>please you,</LINE>
<LINE>Most reverend and grave elders, to desire</LINE>
<LINE>The present consul, and last general</LINE>
<LINE>In our well-found successes, to report</LINE>
<LINE>A little of that worthy work perform'd</LINE>
<LINE>By Caius Marcius Coriolanus, whom</LINE>
<LINE>We met here both to thank and to remember</LINE>
<LINE>With honours like himself.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Speak, good Cominius:</LINE>
<LINE>Leave nothing out for length, and make us think</LINE>
<LINE>Rather our state's defective for requital</LINE>
<LINE>Than we to stretch it out.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>To the Tribunes</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Masters o' the people,</LINE>
<LINE>We do request your kindest ears, and after,</LINE>
<LINE>Your loving motion toward the common body,</LINE>
<LINE>To yield what passes here.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We are convented</LINE>
<LINE>Upon a pleasing treaty, and have hearts</LINE>
<LINE>Inclinable to honour and advance</LINE>
<LINE>The theme of our assembly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Which the rather</LINE>
<LINE>We shall be blest to do, if he remember</LINE>
<LINE>A kinder value of the people than</LINE>
<LINE>He hath hereto prized them at.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That's off, that's off;</LINE>
<LINE>I would you rather had been silent. Please you</LINE>
<LINE>To hear Cominius speak?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Most willingly;</LINE>
<LINE>But yet my caution was more pertinent</LINE>
<LINE>Than the rebuke you give it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He loves your people</LINE>
<LINE>But tie him not to be their bedfellow.</LINE>
<LINE>Worthy Cominius, speak.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>CORIOLANUS offers to go away</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Nay, keep your place.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sit, Coriolanus; never shame to hear</LINE>
<LINE>What you have nobly done.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Your horror's pardon:</LINE>
<LINE>I had rather have my wounds to heal again</LINE>
<LINE>Than hear say how I got them.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sir, I hope</LINE>
<LINE>My words disbench'd you not.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, sir: yet oft,</LINE>
<LINE>When blows have made me stay, I fled from words.</LINE>
<LINE>You soothed not, therefore hurt not: but</LINE>
<LINE>your people,</LINE>
<LINE>I love them as they weigh.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pray now, sit down.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I had rather have one scratch my head i' the sun</LINE>
<LINE>When the alarum were struck than idly sit</LINE>
<LINE>To hear my nothings monster'd.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Masters of the people,</LINE>
<LINE>Your multiplying spawn how can he flatter--</LINE>
<LINE>That's thousand to one good one--when you now see</LINE>
<LINE>He had rather venture all his limbs for honour</LINE>
<LINE>Than one on's ears to hear it? Proceed, Cominius.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I shall lack voice: the deeds of Coriolanus</LINE>
<LINE>Should not be utter'd feebly. It is held</LINE>
<LINE>That valour is the chiefest virtue, and</LINE>
<LINE>Most dignifies the haver: if it be,</LINE>
<LINE>The man I speak of cannot in the world</LINE>
<LINE>Be singly counterpoised. At sixteen years,</LINE>
<LINE>When Tarquin made a head for Rome, he fought</LINE>
<LINE>Beyond the mark of others: our then dictator,</LINE>
<LINE>Whom with all praise I point at, saw him fight,</LINE>
<LINE>When with his Amazonian chin he drove</LINE>
<LINE>The bristled lips before him: be bestrid</LINE>
<LINE>An o'er-press'd Roman and i' the consul's view</LINE>
<LINE>Slew three opposers: Tarquin's self he met,</LINE>
<LINE>And struck him on his knee: in that day's feats,</LINE>
<LINE>When he might act the woman in the scene,</LINE>
<LINE>He proved best man i' the field, and for his meed</LINE>
<LINE>Was brow-bound with the oak. His pupil age</LINE>
<LINE>Man-enter'd thus, he waxed like a sea,</LINE>
<LINE>And in the brunt of seventeen battles since</LINE>
<LINE>He lurch'd all swords of the garland. For this last,</LINE>
<LINE>Before and in Corioli, let me say,</LINE>
<LINE>I cannot speak him home: he stopp'd the fliers;</LINE>
<LINE>And by his rare example made the coward</LINE>
<LINE>Turn terror into sport: as weeds before</LINE>
<LINE>A vessel under sail, so men obey'd</LINE>
<LINE>And fell below his stem: his sword, death's stamp,</LINE>
<LINE>Where it did mark, it took; from face to foot</LINE>
<LINE>He was a thing of blood, whose every motion</LINE>
<LINE>Was timed with dying cries: alone he enter'd</LINE>
<LINE>The mortal gate of the city, which he painted</LINE>
<LINE>With shunless destiny; aidless came off,</LINE>
<LINE>And with a sudden reinforcement struck</LINE>
<LINE>Corioli like a planet: now all's his:</LINE>
<LINE>When, by and by, the din of war gan pierce</LINE>
<LINE>His ready sense; then straight his doubled spirit</LINE>
<LINE>Re-quicken'd what in flesh was fatigate,</LINE>
<LINE>And to the battle came he; where he did</LINE>
<LINE>Run reeking o'er the lives of men, as if</LINE>
<LINE>'Twere a perpetual spoil: and till we call'd</LINE>
<LINE>Both field and city ours, he never stood</LINE>
<LINE>To ease his breast with panting.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Worthy man!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He cannot but with measure fit the honours</LINE>
<LINE>Which we devise him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Our spoils he kick'd at,</LINE>
<LINE>And look'd upon things precious as they were</LINE>
<LINE>The common muck of the world: he covets less</LINE>
<LINE>Than misery itself would give; rewards</LINE>
<LINE>His deeds with doing them, and is content</LINE>
<LINE>To spend the time to end it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He's right noble:</LINE>
<LINE>Let him be call'd for.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Call Coriolanus.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Officer</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He doth appear.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Re-enter CORIOLANUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The senate, Coriolanus, are well pleased</LINE>
<LINE>To make thee consul.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do owe them still</LINE>
<LINE>My life and services.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It then remains</LINE>
<LINE>That you do speak to the people.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do beseech you,</LINE>
<LINE>Let me o'erleap that custom, for I cannot</LINE>
<LINE>Put on the gown, stand naked and entreat them,</LINE>
<LINE>For my wounds' sake, to give their suffrage: please you</LINE>
<LINE>That I may pass this doing.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sir, the people</LINE>
<LINE>Must have their voices; neither will they bate</LINE>
<LINE>One jot of ceremony.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Put them not to't:</LINE>
<LINE>Pray you, go fit you to the custom and</LINE>
<LINE>Take to you, as your predecessors have,</LINE>
<LINE>Your honour with your form.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is apart</LINE>
<LINE>That I shall blush in acting, and might well</LINE>
<LINE>Be taken from the people.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Mark you that?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To brag unto them, thus I did, and thus;</LINE>
<LINE>Show them the unaching scars which I should hide,</LINE>
<LINE>As if I had received them for the hire</LINE>
<LINE>Of their breath only!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do not stand upon't.</LINE>
<LINE>We recommend to you, tribunes of the people,</LINE>
<LINE>Our purpose to them: and to our noble consul</LINE>
<LINE>Wish we all joy and honour.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Senators</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To Coriolanus come all joy and honour!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Flourish of cornets. Exeunt all but SICINIUS
and BRUTUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You see how he intends to use the people.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>May they perceive's intent! He will require them,</LINE>
<LINE>As if he did contemn what he requested</LINE>
<LINE>Should be in them to give.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, we'll inform them</LINE>
<LINE>Of our proceedings here: on the marketplace,</LINE>
<LINE>I know, they do attend us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE III.  The same. The Forum.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter seven or eight Citizens</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Once, if he do require our voices, we ought not to deny him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We may, sir, if we will.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We have power in ourselves to do it, but it is a</LINE>
<LINE>power that we have no power to do; for if he show us</LINE>
<LINE>his wounds and tell us his deeds, we are to put our</LINE>
<LINE>tongues into those wounds and speak for them; so, if</LINE>
<LINE>he tell us his noble deeds, we must also tell him</LINE>
<LINE>our noble acceptance of them. Ingratitude is</LINE>
<LINE>monstrous, and for the multitude to be ingrateful,</LINE>
<LINE>were to make a monster of the multitude: of the</LINE>
<LINE>which we being members, should bring ourselves to be</LINE>
<LINE>monstrous members.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And to make us no better thought of, a little help</LINE>
<LINE>will serve; for once we stood up about the corn, he</LINE>
<LINE>himself stuck not to call us the many-headed multitude.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We have been called so of many; not that our heads</LINE>
<LINE>are some brown, some black, some auburn, some bald,</LINE>
<LINE>but that our wits are so diversely coloured: and</LINE>
<LINE>truly I think if all our wits were to issue out of</LINE>
<LINE>one skull, they would fly east, west, north, south,</LINE>
<LINE>and their consent of one direct way should be at</LINE>
<LINE>once to all the points o' the compass.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Think you so? Which way do you judge my wit would</LINE>
<LINE>fly?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, your wit will not so soon out as another man's</LINE>
<LINE>will;'tis strongly wedged up in a block-head, but</LINE>
<LINE>if it were at liberty, 'twould, sure, southward.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why that way?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To lose itself in a fog, where being three parts</LINE>
<LINE>melted away with rotten dews, the fourth would return</LINE>
<LINE>for conscience sake, to help to get thee a wife.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You are never without your tricks: you may, you may.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Are you all resolved to give your voices? But</LINE>
<LINE>that's no matter, the greater part carries it. I</LINE>
<LINE>say, if he would incline to the people, there was</LINE>
<LINE>never a worthier man.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter CORIOLANUS in a gown of humility, with MENENIUS</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Here he comes, and in the gown of humility: mark his</LINE>
<LINE>behavior. We are not to stay all together, but to</LINE>
<LINE>come by him where he stands, by ones, by twos, and</LINE>
<LINE>by threes. He's to make his requests by</LINE>
<LINE>particulars; wherein every one of us has a single</LINE>
<LINE>honour, in giving him our own voices with our own</LINE>
<LINE>tongues: therefore follow me, and I direct you how</LINE>
<LINE>you shall go by him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>All</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Content, content.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt Citizens</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O sir, you are not right: have you not known</LINE>
<LINE>The worthiest men have done't?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What must I say?</LINE>
<LINE>'I Pray, sir'--Plague upon't! I cannot bring</LINE>
<LINE>My tongue to such a pace:--'Look, sir, my wounds!</LINE>
<LINE>I got them in my country's service, when</LINE>
<LINE>Some certain of your brethren roar'd and ran</LINE>
<LINE>From the noise of our own drums.'</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O me, the gods!</LINE>
<LINE>You must not speak of that: you must desire them</LINE>
<LINE>To think upon you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Think upon me! hang 'em!</LINE>
<LINE>I would they would forget me, like the virtues</LINE>
<LINE>Which our divines lose by 'em.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You'll mar all:</LINE>
<LINE>I'll leave you: pray you, speak to 'em, I pray you,</LINE>
<LINE>In wholesome manner.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Bid them wash their faces</LINE>
<LINE>And keep their teeth clean.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Re-enter two of the Citizens</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>So, here comes a brace.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Re-enter a third Citizen</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>You know the cause, air, of my standing here.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We do, sir; tell us what hath brought you to't.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Mine own desert.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Your own desert!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, but not mine own desire.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How not your own desire?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, sir,'twas never my desire yet to trouble the</LINE>
<LINE>poor with begging.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You must think, if we give you any thing, we hope to</LINE>
<LINE>gain by you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well then, I pray, your price o' the consulship?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The price is to ask it kindly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Kindly! Sir, I pray, let me ha't: I have wounds to</LINE>
<LINE>show you, which shall be yours in private. Your</LINE>
<LINE>good voice, sir; what say you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You shall ha' it, worthy sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A match, sir. There's in all two worthy voices</LINE>
<LINE>begged. I have your alms: adieu.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But this is something odd.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>An 'twere to give again,--but 'tis no matter.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt the three Citizens</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Re-enter two other Citizens</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pray you now, if it may stand with the tune of your</LINE>
<LINE>voices that I may be consul, I have here the</LINE>
<LINE>customary gown.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Fourth Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You have deserved nobly of your country, and you</LINE>
<LINE>have not deserved nobly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Your enigma?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Fourth Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You have been a scourge to her enemies, you have</LINE>
<LINE>been a rod to her friends; you have not indeed loved</LINE>
<LINE>the common people.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You should account me the more virtuous that I have</LINE>
<LINE>not been common in my love. I will, sir, flatter my</LINE>
<LINE>sworn brother, the people, to earn a dearer</LINE>
<LINE>estimation of them; 'tis a condition they account</LINE>
<LINE>gentle: and since the wisdom of their choice is</LINE>
<LINE>rather to have my hat than my heart, I will practise</LINE>
<LINE>the insinuating nod and be off to them most</LINE>
<LINE>counterfeitly; that is, sir, I will counterfeit the</LINE>
<LINE>bewitchment of some popular man and give it</LINE>
<LINE>bountiful to the desirers. Therefore, beseech you,</LINE>
<LINE>I may be consul.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Fifth Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We hope to find you our friend; and therefore give</LINE>
<LINE>you our voices heartily.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Fourth Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You have received many wounds for your country.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will not seal your knowledge with showing them. I</LINE>
<LINE>will make much of your voices, and so trouble you no further.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Both Citizens</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The gods give you joy, sir, heartily!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Most sweet voices!</LINE>
<LINE>Better it is to die, better to starve,</LINE>
<LINE>Than crave the hire which first we do deserve.</LINE>
<LINE>Why in this woolvish toge should I stand here,</LINE>
<LINE>To beg of Hob and Dick, that do appear,</LINE>
<LINE>Their needless vouches? Custom calls me to't:</LINE>
<LINE>What custom wills, in all things should we do't,</LINE>
<LINE>The dust on antique time would lie unswept,</LINE>
<LINE>And mountainous error be too highly heapt</LINE>
<LINE>For truth to o'er-peer. Rather than fool it so,</LINE>
<LINE>Let the high office and the honour go</LINE>
<LINE>To one that would do thus. I am half through;</LINE>
<LINE>The one part suffer'd, the other will I do.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Re-enter three Citizens more</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Here come more voices.</LINE>
<LINE>Your voices: for your voices I have fought;</LINE>
<LINE>Watch'd for your voices; for Your voices bear</LINE>
<LINE>Of wounds two dozen odd; battles thrice six</LINE>
<LINE>I have seen and heard of; for your voices have</LINE>
<LINE>Done many things, some less, some more your voices:</LINE>
<LINE>Indeed I would be consul.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Sixth Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He has done nobly, and cannot go without any honest</LINE>
<LINE>man's voice.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Seventh Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Therefore let him be consul: the gods give him joy,</LINE>
<LINE>and make him good friend to the people!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>All Citizens</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Amen, amen. God save thee, noble consul!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Worthy voices!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Re-enter MENENIUS, with BRUTUS and SICINIUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You have stood your limitation; and the tribunes</LINE>
<LINE>Endue you with the people's voice: remains</LINE>
<LINE>That, in the official marks invested, you</LINE>
<LINE>Anon do meet the senate.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is this done?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The custom of request you have discharged:</LINE>
<LINE>The people do admit you, and are summon'd</LINE>
<LINE>To meet anon, upon your approbation.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where? at the senate-house?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>There, Coriolanus.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>May I change these garments?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You may, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That I'll straight do; and, knowing myself again,</LINE>
<LINE>Repair to the senate-house.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I'll keep you company. Will you along?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We stay here for the people.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Fare you well.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exeunt CORIOLANUS and MENENIUS</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>He has it now, and by his looks methink</LINE>
<LINE>'Tis warm at 's heart.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>With a proud heart he wore his humble weeds.</LINE>
<LINE>will you dismiss the people?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Re-enter Citizens</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How now, my masters! have you chose this man?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He has our voices, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We pray the gods he may deserve your loves.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Amen, sir: to my poor unworthy notice,</LINE>
<LINE>He mock'd us when he begg'd our voices.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Certainly</LINE>
<LINE>He flouted us downright.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No,'tis his kind of speech: he did not mock us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not one amongst us, save yourself, but says</LINE>
<LINE>He used us scornfully: he should have show'd us</LINE>
<LINE>His marks of merit, wounds received for's country.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, so he did, I am sure.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Citizens</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, no; no man saw 'em.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He said he had wounds, which he could show</LINE>
<LINE>in private;</LINE>
<LINE>And with his hat, thus waving it in scorn,</LINE>
<LINE>'I would be consul,' says he: 'aged custom,</LINE>
<LINE>But by your voices, will not so permit me;</LINE>
<LINE>Your voices therefore.' When we granted that,</LINE>
<LINE>Here was 'I thank you for your voices: thank you:</LINE>
<LINE>Your most sweet voices: now you have left</LINE>
<LINE>your voices,</LINE>
<LINE>I have no further with you.' Was not this mockery?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why either were you ignorant to see't,</LINE>
<LINE>Or, seeing it, of such childish friendliness</LINE>
<LINE>To yield your voices?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Could you not have told him</LINE>
<LINE>As you were lesson'd, when he had no power,</LINE>
<LINE>But was a petty servant to the state,</LINE>
<LINE>He was your enemy, ever spake against</LINE>
<LINE>Your liberties and the charters that you bear</LINE>
<LINE>I' the body of the weal; and now, arriving</LINE>
<LINE>A place of potency and sway o' the state,</LINE>
<LINE>If he should still malignantly remain</LINE>
<LINE>Fast foe to the plebeii, your voices might</LINE>
<LINE>Be curses to yourselves? You should have said</LINE>
<LINE>That as his worthy deeds did claim no less</LINE>
<LINE>Than what he stood for, so his gracious nature</LINE>
<LINE>Would think upon you for your voices and</LINE>
<LINE>Translate his malice towards you into love,</LINE>
<LINE>Standing your friendly lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thus to have said,</LINE>
<LINE>As you were fore-advised, had touch'd his spirit</LINE>
<LINE>And tried his inclination; from him pluck'd</LINE>
<LINE>Either his gracious promise, which you might,</LINE>
<LINE>As cause had call'd you up, have held him to</LINE>
<LINE>Or else it would have gall'd his surly nature,</LINE>
<LINE>Which easily endures not article</LINE>
<LINE>Tying him to aught; so putting him to rage,</LINE>
<LINE>You should have ta'en the advantage of his choler</LINE>
<LINE>And pass'd him unelected.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Did you perceive</LINE>
<LINE>He did solicit you in free contempt</LINE>
<LINE>When he did need your loves, and do you think</LINE>
<LINE>That his contempt shall not be bruising to you,</LINE>
<LINE>When he hath power to crush? Why, had your bodies</LINE>
<LINE>No heart among you? or had you tongues to cry</LINE>
<LINE>Against the rectorship of judgment?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Have you</LINE>
<LINE>Ere now denied the asker? and now again</LINE>
<LINE>Of him that did not ask, but mock, bestow</LINE>
<LINE>Your sued-for tongues?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He's not confirm'd; we may deny him yet.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And will deny him:</LINE>
<LINE>I'll have five hundred voices of that sound.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I twice five hundred and their friends to piece 'em.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Get you hence instantly, and tell those friends,</LINE>
<LINE>They have chose a consul that will from them take</LINE>
<LINE>Their liberties; make them of no more voice</LINE>
<LINE>Than dogs that are as often beat for barking</LINE>
<LINE>As therefore kept to do so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let them assemble,</LINE>
<LINE>And on a safer judgment all revoke</LINE>
<LINE>Your ignorant election; enforce his pride,</LINE>
<LINE>And his old hate unto you; besides, forget not</LINE>
<LINE>With what contempt he wore the humble weed,</LINE>
<LINE>How in his suit he scorn'd you; but your loves,</LINE>
<LINE>Thinking upon his services, took from you</LINE>
<LINE>The apprehension of his present portance,</LINE>
<LINE>Which most gibingly, ungravely, he did fashion</LINE>
<LINE>After the inveterate hate he bears you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Lay</LINE>
<LINE>A fault on us, your tribunes; that we laboured,</LINE>
<LINE>No impediment between, but that you must</LINE>
<LINE>Cast your election on him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Say, you chose him</LINE>
<LINE>More after our commandment than as guided</LINE>
<LINE>By your own true affections, and that your minds,</LINE>
<LINE>Preoccupied with what you rather must do</LINE>
<LINE>Than what you should, made you against the grain</LINE>
<LINE>To voice him consul: lay the fault on us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, spare us not. Say we read lectures to you.</LINE>
<LINE>How youngly he began to serve his country,</LINE>
<LINE>How long continued, and what stock he springs of,</LINE>
<LINE>The noble house o' the Marcians, from whence came</LINE>
<LINE>That Ancus Marcius, Numa's daughter's son,</LINE>
<LINE>Who, after great Hostilius, here was king;</LINE>
<LINE>Of the same house Publius and Quintus were,</LINE>
<LINE>That our beat water brought by conduits hither;</LINE>
<LINE>And  <STAGEDIR>Censorinus,</STAGEDIR>  nobly named so,</LINE>
<LINE>Twice being  <STAGEDIR>by the people chosen</STAGEDIR>  censor,</LINE>
<LINE>Was his great ancestor.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>One thus descended,</LINE>
<LINE>That hath beside well in his person wrought</LINE>
<LINE>To be set high in place, we did commend</LINE>
<LINE>To your remembrances: but you have found,</LINE>
<LINE>Scaling his present bearing with his past,</LINE>
<LINE>That he's your fixed enemy, and revoke</LINE>
<LINE>Your sudden approbation.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Say, you ne'er had done't--</LINE>
<LINE>Harp on that still--but by our putting on;</LINE>
<LINE>And presently, when you have drawn your number,</LINE>
<LINE>Repair to the Capitol.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>All</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We will so: almost all</LINE>
<LINE>Repent in their election.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt Citizens</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let them go on;</LINE>
<LINE>This mutiny were better put in hazard,</LINE>
<LINE>Than stay, past doubt, for greater:</LINE>
<LINE>If, as his nature is, he fall in rage</LINE>
<LINE>With their refusal, both observe and answer</LINE>
<LINE>The vantage of his anger.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To the Capitol, come:</LINE>
<LINE>We will be there before the stream o' the people;</LINE>
<LINE>And this shall seem, as partly 'tis, their own,</LINE>
<LINE>Which we have goaded onward.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

</ACT>

<ACT><TITLE>ACT III</TITLE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE I.  Rome. A street.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Cornets. Enter CORIOLANUS, MENENIUS, all the
Gentry, COMINIUS, TITUS LARTIUS, and other Senators</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Tullus Aufidius then had made new head?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LARTIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He had, my lord; and that it was which caused</LINE>
<LINE>Our swifter composition.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So then the Volsces stand but as at first,</LINE>
<LINE>Ready, when time shall prompt them, to make road.</LINE>
<LINE>Upon's again.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>They are worn, lord consul, so,</LINE>
<LINE>That we shall hardly in our ages see</LINE>
<LINE>Their banners wave again.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Saw you Aufidius?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LARTIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>On safe-guard he came to me; and did curse</LINE>
<LINE>Against the Volsces, for they had so vilely</LINE>
<LINE>Yielded the town: he is retired to Antium.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Spoke he of me?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LARTIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He did, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How? what?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LARTIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How often he had met you, sword to sword;</LINE>
<LINE>That of all things upon the earth he hated</LINE>
<LINE>Your person most, that he would pawn his fortunes</LINE>
<LINE>To hopeless restitution, so he might</LINE>
<LINE>Be call'd your vanquisher.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>At Antium lives he?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LARTIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>At Antium.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I wish I had a cause to seek him there,</LINE>
<LINE>To oppose his hatred fully. Welcome home.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter SICINIUS and BRUTUS</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Behold, these are the tribunes of the people,</LINE>
<LINE>The tongues o' the common mouth: I do despise them;</LINE>
<LINE>For they do prank them in authority,</LINE>
<LINE>Against all noble sufferance.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pass no further.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ha! what is that?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It will be dangerous to go on: no further.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What makes this change?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The matter?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hath he not pass'd the noble and the common?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Cominius, no.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Have I had children's voices?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Tribunes, give way; he shall to the market-place.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The people are incensed against him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Stop,</LINE>
<LINE>Or all will fall in broil.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Are these your herd?</LINE>
<LINE>Must these have voices, that can yield them now</LINE>
<LINE>And straight disclaim their tongues? What are</LINE>
<LINE>your offices?</LINE>
<LINE>You being their mouths, why rule you not their teeth?</LINE>
<LINE>Have you not set them on?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Be calm, be calm.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is a purposed thing, and grows by plot,</LINE>
<LINE>To curb the will of the nobility:</LINE>
<LINE>Suffer't, and live with such as cannot rule</LINE>
<LINE>Nor ever will be ruled.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Call't not a plot:</LINE>
<LINE>The people cry you mock'd them, and of late,</LINE>
<LINE>When corn was given them gratis, you repined;</LINE>
<LINE>Scandal'd the suppliants for the people, call'd them</LINE>
<LINE>Time-pleasers, flatterers, foes to nobleness.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, this was known before.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not to them all.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Have you inform'd them sithence?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How! I inform them!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You are like to do such business.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not unlike,</LINE>
<LINE>Each way, to better yours.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why then should I be consul? By yond clouds,</LINE>
<LINE>Let me deserve so ill as you, and make me</LINE>
<LINE>Your fellow tribune.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You show too much of that</LINE>
<LINE>For which the people stir: if you will pass</LINE>
<LINE>To where you are bound, you must inquire your way,</LINE>
<LINE>Which you are out of, with a gentler spirit,</LINE>
<LINE>Or never be so noble as a consul,</LINE>
<LINE>Nor yoke with him for tribune.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let's be calm.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The people are abused; set on. This paltering</LINE>
<LINE>Becomes not Rome, nor has Coriolanus</LINE>
<LINE>Deserved this so dishonour'd rub, laid falsely</LINE>
<LINE>I' the plain way of his merit.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Tell me of corn!</LINE>
<LINE>This was my speech, and I will speak't again--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not now, not now.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not in this heat, sir, now.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now, as I live, I will. My nobler friends,</LINE>
<LINE>I crave their pardons:</LINE>
<LINE>For the mutable, rank-scented many, let them</LINE>
<LINE>Regard me as I do not flatter, and</LINE>
<LINE>Therein behold themselves: I say again,</LINE>
<LINE>In soothing them, we nourish 'gainst our senate</LINE>
<LINE>The cockle of rebellion, insolence, sedition,</LINE>
<LINE>Which we ourselves have plough'd for, sow'd,</LINE>
<LINE>and scatter'd,</LINE>
<LINE>By mingling them with us, the honour'd number,</LINE>
<LINE>Who lack not virtue, no, nor power, but that</LINE>
<LINE>Which they have given to beggars.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, no more.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No more words, we beseech you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How! no more!</LINE>
<LINE>As for my country I have shed my blood,</LINE>
<LINE>Not fearing outward force, so shall my lungs</LINE>
<LINE>Coin words till their decay against those measles,</LINE>
<LINE>Which we disdain should tatter us, yet sought</LINE>
<LINE>The very way to catch them.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You speak o' the people,</LINE>
<LINE>As if you were a god to punish, not</LINE>
<LINE>A man of their infirmity.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Twere well</LINE>
<LINE>We let the people know't.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, what? his choler?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Choler!</LINE>
<LINE>Were I as patient as the midnight sleep,</LINE>
<LINE>By Jove, 'twould be my mind!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is a mind</LINE>
<LINE>That shall remain a poison where it is,</LINE>
<LINE>Not poison any further.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Shall remain!</LINE>
<LINE>Hear you this Triton of the minnows? mark you</LINE>
<LINE>His absolute 'shall'?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Twas from the canon.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Shall'!</LINE>
<LINE>O good but most unwise patricians! why,</LINE>
<LINE>You grave but reckless senators, have you thus</LINE>
<LINE>Given Hydra here to choose an officer,</LINE>
<LINE>That with his peremptory 'shall,' being but</LINE>
<LINE>The horn and noise o' the monster's, wants not spirit</LINE>
<LINE>To say he'll turn your current in a ditch,</LINE>
<LINE>And make your channel his? If he have power</LINE>
<LINE>Then vail your ignorance; if none, awake</LINE>
<LINE>Your dangerous lenity. If you are learn'd,</LINE>
<LINE>Be not as common fools; if you are not,</LINE>
<LINE>Let them have cushions by you. You are plebeians,</LINE>
<LINE>If they be senators: and they are no less,</LINE>
<LINE>When, both your voices blended, the great'st taste</LINE>
<LINE>Most palates theirs. They choose their magistrate,</LINE>
<LINE>And such a one as he, who puts his 'shall,'</LINE>
<LINE>His popular 'shall' against a graver bench</LINE>
<LINE>Than ever frown in Greece. By Jove himself!</LINE>
<LINE>It makes the consuls base: and my soul aches</LINE>
<LINE>To know, when two authorities are up,</LINE>
<LINE>Neither supreme, how soon confusion</LINE>
<LINE>May enter 'twixt the gap of both and take</LINE>
<LINE>The one by the other.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, on to the market-place.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Whoever gave that counsel, to give forth</LINE>
<LINE>The corn o' the storehouse gratis, as 'twas used</LINE>
<LINE>Sometime in Greece,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, well, no more of that.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Though there the people had more absolute power,</LINE>
<LINE>I say, they nourish'd disobedience, fed</LINE>
<LINE>The ruin of the state.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, shall the people give</LINE>
<LINE>One that speaks thus their voice?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I'll give my reasons,</LINE>
<LINE>More worthier than their voices. They know the corn</LINE>
<LINE>Was not our recompense, resting well assured</LINE>
<LINE>That ne'er did service for't: being press'd to the war,</LINE>
<LINE>Even when the navel of the state was touch'd,</LINE>
<LINE>They would not thread the gates. This kind of service</LINE>
<LINE>Did not deserve corn gratis. Being i' the war</LINE>
<LINE>Their mutinies and revolts, wherein they show'd</LINE>
<LINE>Most valour, spoke not for them: the accusation</LINE>
<LINE>Which they have often made against the senate,</LINE>
<LINE>All cause unborn, could never be the motive</LINE>
<LINE>Of our so frank donation. Well, what then?</LINE>
<LINE>How shall this bisson multitude digest</LINE>
<LINE>The senate's courtesy? Let deeds express</LINE>
<LINE>What's like to be their words: 'we did request it;</LINE>
<LINE>We are the greater poll, and in true fear</LINE>
<LINE>They gave us our demands.' Thus we debase</LINE>
<LINE>The nature of our seats and make the rabble</LINE>
<LINE>Call our cares fears; which will in time</LINE>
<LINE>Break ope the locks o' the senate and bring in</LINE>
<LINE>The crows to peck the eagles.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, enough.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Enough, with over-measure.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, take more:</LINE>
<LINE>What may be sworn by, both divine and human,</LINE>
<LINE>Seal what I end withal! This double worship,</LINE>
<LINE>Where one part does disdain with cause, the other</LINE>
<LINE>Insult without all reason, where gentry, title, wisdom,</LINE>
<LINE>Cannot conclude but by the yea and no</LINE>
<LINE>Of general ignorance,--it must omit</LINE>
<LINE>Real necessities, and give way the while</LINE>
<LINE>To unstable slightness: purpose so barr'd,</LINE>
<LINE>it follows,</LINE>
<LINE>Nothing is done to purpose. Therefore, beseech you,--</LINE>
<LINE>You that will be less fearful than discreet,</LINE>
<LINE>That love the fundamental part of state</LINE>
<LINE>More than you doubt the change on't, that prefer</LINE>
<LINE>A noble life before a long, and wish</LINE>
<LINE>To jump a body with a dangerous physic</LINE>
<LINE>That's sure of death without it, at once pluck out</LINE>
<LINE>The multitudinous tongue; let them not lick</LINE>
<LINE>The sweet which is their poison: your dishonour</LINE>
<LINE>Mangles true judgment and bereaves the state</LINE>
<LINE>Of that integrity which should become't,</LINE>
<LINE>Not having the power to do the good it would,</LINE>
<LINE>For the in which doth control't.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Has said enough.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Has spoken like a traitor, and shall answer</LINE>
<LINE>As traitors do.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thou wretch, despite o'erwhelm thee!</LINE>
<LINE>What should the people do with these bald tribunes?</LINE>
<LINE>On whom depending, their obedience fails</LINE>
<LINE>To the greater bench: in a rebellion,</LINE>
<LINE>When what's not meet, but what must be, was law,</LINE>
<LINE>Then were they chosen: in a better hour,</LINE>
<LINE>Let what is meet be said it must be meet,</LINE>
<LINE>And throw their power i' the dust.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Manifest treason!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This a consul? no.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The aediles, ho!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter an AEdile</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Let him be apprehended.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Go, call the people:</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit AEdile</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>in whose name myself</LINE>
<LINE>Attach thee as a traitorous innovator,</LINE>
<LINE>A foe to the public weal: obey, I charge thee,</LINE>
<LINE>And follow to thine answer.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hence, old goat!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Senators, &amp;C</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We'll surety him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Aged sir, hands off.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hence, rotten thing! or I shall shake thy bones</LINE>
<LINE>Out of thy garments.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Help, ye citizens!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter a rabble of Citizens (Plebeians), with
the AEdiles</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>On both sides more respect.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here's he that would take from you all your power.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Seize him, AEdiles!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Citizens</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Down with him! down with him!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Senators, &amp;C</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Weapons, weapons, weapons!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>They all bustle about CORIOLANUS, crying</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>'Tribunes!' 'Patricians!' 'Citizens!' 'What, ho!'</LINE>
<LINE>'Sicinius!' 'Brutus!' 'Coriolanus!' 'Citizens!'</LINE>
<LINE>'Peace, peace, peace!' 'Stay, hold, peace!'</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What is about to be? I am out of breath;</LINE>
<LINE>Confusion's near; I cannot speak. You, tribunes</LINE>
<LINE>To the people! Coriolanus, patience!</LINE>
<LINE>Speak, good Sicinius.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hear me, people; peace!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Citizens</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let's hear our tribune: peace Speak, speak, speak.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You are at point to lose your liberties:</LINE>
<LINE>Marcius would have all from you; Marcius,</LINE>
<LINE>Whom late you have named for consul.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Fie, fie, fie!</LINE>
<LINE>This is the way to kindle, not to quench.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To unbuild the city and to lay all flat.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What is the city but the people?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Citizens</SPEAKER>
<LINE>True,</LINE>
<LINE>The people are the city.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>By the consent of all, we were establish'd</LINE>
<LINE>The people's magistrates.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Citizens</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You so remain.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And so are like to do.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That is the way to lay the city flat;</LINE>
<LINE>To bring the roof to the foundation,</LINE>
<LINE>And bury all, which yet distinctly ranges,</LINE>
<LINE>In heaps and piles of ruin.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This deserves death.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Or let us stand to our authority,</LINE>
<LINE>Or let us lose it. We do here pronounce,</LINE>
<LINE>Upon the part o' the people, in whose power</LINE>
<LINE>We were elected theirs, Marcius is worthy</LINE>
<LINE>Of present death.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Therefore lay hold of him;</LINE>
<LINE>Bear him to the rock Tarpeian, and from thence</LINE>
<LINE>Into destruction cast him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>AEdiles, seize him!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Citizens</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yield, Marcius, yield!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hear me one word;</LINE>
<LINE>Beseech you, tribunes, hear me but a word.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AEdile</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Peace, peace!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>To BRUTUS</STAGEDIR>  Be that you seem, truly your</LINE>
<LINE>country's friend,</LINE>
<LINE>And temperately proceed to what you would</LINE>
<LINE>Thus violently redress.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sir, those cold ways,</LINE>
<LINE>That seem like prudent helps, are very poisonous</LINE>
<LINE>Where the disease is violent. Lay hands upon him,</LINE>
<LINE>And bear him to the rock.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, I'll die here.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Drawing his sword</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>There's some among you have beheld me fighting:</LINE>
<LINE>Come, try upon yourselves what you have seen me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Down with that sword! Tribunes, withdraw awhile.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Lay hands upon him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Help Marcius, help,</LINE>
<LINE>You that be noble; help him, young and old!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Citizens</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Down with him, down with him!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>In this mutiny, the Tribunes, the AEdiles, and the
People, are beat in</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Go, get you to your house; be gone, away!</LINE>
<LINE>All will be naught else.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Get you gone.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Stand fast;</LINE>
<LINE>We have as many friends as enemies.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sham it be put to that?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The gods forbid!</LINE>
<LINE>I prithee, noble friend, home to thy house;</LINE>
<LINE>Leave us to cure this cause.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>For 'tis a sore upon us,</LINE>
<LINE>You cannot tent yourself: be gone, beseech you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, sir, along with us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I would they were barbarians--as they are,</LINE>
<LINE>Though in Rome litter'd--not Romans--as they are not,</LINE>
<LINE>Though calved i' the porch o' the Capitol--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Be gone;</LINE>
<LINE>Put not your worthy rage into your tongue;</LINE>
<LINE>One time will owe another.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>On fair ground</LINE>
<LINE>I could beat forty of them.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I could myself</LINE>
<LINE>Take up a brace o' the best of them; yea, the</LINE>
<LINE>two tribunes:</LINE>
<LINE>But now 'tis odds beyond arithmetic;</LINE>
<LINE>And manhood is call'd foolery, when it stands</LINE>
<LINE>Against a falling fabric. Will you hence,</LINE>
<LINE>Before the tag return? whose rage doth rend</LINE>
<LINE>Like interrupted waters and o'erbear</LINE>
<LINE>What they are used to bear.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pray you, be gone:</LINE>
<LINE>I'll try whether my old wit be in request</LINE>
<LINE>With those that have but little: this must be patch'd</LINE>
<LINE>With cloth of any colour.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, come away.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt CORIOLANUS, COMINIUS, and others</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>A Patrician</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This man has marr'd his fortune.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>His nature is too noble for the world:</LINE>
<LINE>He would not flatter Neptune for his trident,</LINE>
<LINE>Or Jove for's power to thunder. His heart's his mouth:</LINE>
<LINE>What his breast forges, that his tongue must vent;</LINE>
<LINE>And, being angry, does forget that ever</LINE>
<LINE>He heard the name of death.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>A noise within</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Here's goodly work!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Patrician</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I would they were abed!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I would they were in Tiber! What the vengeance!</LINE>
<LINE>Could he not speak 'em fair?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Re-enter BRUTUS and SICINIUS, with the rabble</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where is this viper</LINE>
<LINE>That would depopulate the city and</LINE>
<LINE>Be every man himself?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You worthy tribunes,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He shall be thrown down the Tarpeian rock</LINE>
<LINE>With rigorous hands: he hath resisted law,</LINE>
<LINE>And therefore law shall scorn him further trial</LINE>
<LINE>Than the severity of the public power</LINE>
<LINE>Which he so sets at nought.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He shall well know</LINE>
<LINE>The noble tribunes are the people's mouths,</LINE>
<LINE>And we their hands.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Citizens</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He shall, sure on't.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sir, sir,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Peace!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do not cry havoc, where you should but hunt</LINE>
<LINE>With modest warrant.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sir, how comes't that you</LINE>
<LINE>Have holp to make this rescue?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hear me speak:</LINE>
<LINE>As I do know the consul's worthiness,</LINE>
<LINE>So can I name his faults,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Consul! what consul?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The consul Coriolanus.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He consul!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Citizens</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, no, no, no, no.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If, by the tribunes' leave, and yours, good people,</LINE>
<LINE>I may be heard, I would crave a word or two;</LINE>
<LINE>The which shall turn you to no further harm</LINE>
<LINE>Than so much loss of time.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Speak briefly then;</LINE>
<LINE>For we are peremptory to dispatch</LINE>
<LINE>This viperous traitor: to eject him hence</LINE>
<LINE>Were but one danger, and to keep him here</LINE>
<LINE>Our certain death: therefore it is decreed</LINE>
<LINE>He dies to-night.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now the good gods forbid</LINE>
<LINE>That our renowned Rome, whose gratitude</LINE>
<LINE>Towards her deserved children is enroll'd</LINE>
<LINE>In Jove's own book, like an unnatural dam</LINE>
<LINE>Should now eat up her own!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He's a disease that must be cut away.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, he's a limb that has but a disease;</LINE>
<LINE>Mortal, to cut it off; to cure it, easy.</LINE>
<LINE>What has he done to Rome that's worthy death?</LINE>
<LINE>Killing our enemies, the blood he hath lost--</LINE>
<LINE>Which, I dare vouch, is more than that he hath,</LINE>
<LINE>By many an ounce--he dropp'd it for his country;</LINE>
<LINE>And what is left, to lose it by his country,</LINE>
<LINE>Were to us all, that do't and suffer it,</LINE>
<LINE>A brand to the end o' the world.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This is clean kam.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Merely awry: when he did love his country,</LINE>
<LINE>It honour'd him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The service of the foot</LINE>
<LINE>Being once gangrened, is not then respected</LINE>
<LINE>For what before it was.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We'll hear no more.</LINE>
<LINE>Pursue him to his house, and pluck him thence:</LINE>
<LINE>Lest his infection, being of catching nature,</LINE>
<LINE>Spread further.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>One word more, one word.</LINE>
<LINE>This tiger-footed rage, when it shall find</LINE>
<LINE>The harm of unscann'd swiftness, will too late</LINE>
<LINE>Tie leaden pounds to's heels. Proceed by process;</LINE>
<LINE>Lest parties, as he is beloved, break out,</LINE>
<LINE>And sack great Rome with Romans.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If it were so,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What do ye talk?</LINE>
<LINE>Have we not had a taste of his obedience?</LINE>
<LINE>Our aediles smote? ourselves resisted? Come.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Consider this: he has been bred i' the wars</LINE>
<LINE>Since he could draw a sword, and is ill school'd</LINE>
<LINE>In bolted language; meal and bran together</LINE>
<LINE>He throws without distinction. Give me leave,</LINE>
<LINE>I'll go to him, and undertake to bring him</LINE>
<LINE>Where he shall answer, by a lawful form,</LINE>
<LINE>In peace, to his utmost peril.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Noble tribunes,</LINE>
<LINE>It is the humane way: the other course</LINE>
<LINE>Will prove too bloody, and the end of it</LINE>
<LINE>Unknown to the beginning.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Noble Menenius,</LINE>
<LINE>Be you then as the people's officer.</LINE>
<LINE>Masters, lay down your weapons.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Go not home.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Meet on the market-place. We'll attend you there:</LINE>
<LINE>Where, if you bring not Marcius, we'll proceed</LINE>
<LINE>In our first way.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I'll bring him to you.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>To the Senators</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Let me desire your company: he must come,</LINE>
<LINE>Or what is worst will follow.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pray you, let's to him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE II.  A room in CORIOLANUS'S house.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter CORIOLANUS with Patricians</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let them puff all about mine ears, present me</LINE>
<LINE>Death on the wheel or at wild horses' heels,</LINE>
<LINE>Or pile ten hills on the Tarpeian rock,</LINE>
<LINE>That the precipitation might down stretch</LINE>
<LINE>Below the beam of sight, yet will I still</LINE>
<LINE>Be thus to them.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>A Patrician</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You do the nobler.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I muse my mother</LINE>
<LINE>Does not approve me further, who was wont</LINE>
<LINE>To call them woollen vassals, things created</LINE>
<LINE>To buy and sell with groats, to show bare heads</LINE>
<LINE>In congregations, to yawn, be still and wonder,</LINE>
<LINE>When one but of my ordinance stood up</LINE>
<LINE>To speak of peace or war.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter VOLUMNIA</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>I talk of you:</LINE>
<LINE>Why did you wish me milder? would you have me</LINE>
<LINE>False to my nature? Rather say I play</LINE>
<LINE>The man I am.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, sir, sir, sir,</LINE>
<LINE>I would have had you put your power well on,</LINE>
<LINE>Before you had worn it out.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let go.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You might have been enough the man you are,</LINE>
<LINE>With striving less to be so; lesser had been</LINE>
<LINE>The thwartings of your dispositions, if</LINE>
<LINE>You had not show'd them how ye were disposed</LINE>
<LINE>Ere they lack'd power to cross you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let them hang.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>A Patrician</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, and burn too.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter MENENIUS and Senators</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, come, you have been too rough, something</LINE>
<LINE>too rough;</LINE>
<LINE>You must return and mend it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>There's no remedy;</LINE>
<LINE>Unless, by not so doing, our good city</LINE>
<LINE>Cleave in the midst, and perish.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pray, be counsell'd:</LINE>
<LINE>I have a heart as little apt as yours,</LINE>
<LINE>But yet a brain that leads my use of anger</LINE>
<LINE>To better vantage.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well said, noble woman?</LINE>
<LINE>Before he should thus stoop to the herd, but that</LINE>
<LINE>The violent fit o' the time craves it as physic</LINE>
<LINE>For the whole state, I would put mine armour on,</LINE>
<LINE>Which I can scarcely bear.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What must I do?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Return to the tribunes.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, what then? what then?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Repent what you have spoke.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>For them! I cannot do it to the gods;</LINE>
<LINE>Must I then do't to them?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You are too absolute;</LINE>
<LINE>Though therein you can never be too noble,</LINE>
<LINE>But when extremities speak. I have heard you say,</LINE>
<LINE>Honour and policy, like unsever'd friends,</LINE>
<LINE>I' the war do grow together: grant that, and tell me,</LINE>
<LINE>In peace what each of them by the other lose,</LINE>
<LINE>That they combine not there.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Tush, tush!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A good demand.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If it be honour in your wars to seem</LINE>
<LINE>The same you are not, which, for your best ends,</LINE>
<LINE>You adopt your policy, how is it less or worse,</LINE>
<LINE>That it shall hold companionship in peace</LINE>
<LINE>With honour, as in war, since that to both</LINE>
<LINE>It stands in like request?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why force you this?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Because that now it lies you on to speak</LINE>
<LINE>To the people; not by your own instruction,</LINE>
<LINE>Nor by the matter which your heart prompts you,</LINE>
<LINE>But with such words that are but rooted in</LINE>
<LINE>Your tongue, though but bastards and syllables</LINE>
<LINE>Of no allowance to your bosom's truth.</LINE>
<LINE>Now, this no more dishonours you at all</LINE>
<LINE>Than to take in a town with gentle words,</LINE>
<LINE>Which else would put you to your fortune and</LINE>
<LINE>The hazard of much blood.</LINE>
<LINE>I would dissemble with my nature where</LINE>
<LINE>My fortunes and my friends at stake required</LINE>
<LINE>I should do so in honour: I am in this,</LINE>
<LINE>Your wife, your son, these senators, the nobles;</LINE>
<LINE>And you will rather show our general louts</LINE>
<LINE>How you can frown than spend a fawn upon 'em,</LINE>
<LINE>For the inheritance of their loves and safeguard</LINE>
<LINE>Of what that want might ruin.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Noble lady!</LINE>
<LINE>Come, go with us; speak fair: you may salve so,</LINE>
<LINE>Not what is dangerous present, but the loss</LINE>
<LINE>Of what is past.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I prithee now, my son,</LINE>
<LINE>Go to them, with this bonnet in thy hand;</LINE>
<LINE>And thus far having stretch'd it--here be with them--</LINE>
<LINE>Thy knee bussing the stones--for in such business</LINE>
<LINE>Action is eloquence, and the eyes of the ignorant</LINE>
<LINE>More learned than the ears--waving thy head,</LINE>
<LINE>Which often, thus, correcting thy stout heart,</LINE>
<LINE>Now humble as the ripest mulberry</LINE>
<LINE>That will not hold the handling: or say to them,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou art their soldier, and being bred in broils</LINE>
<LINE>Hast not the soft way which, thou dost confess,</LINE>
<LINE>Were fit for thee to use as they to claim,</LINE>
<LINE>In asking their good loves, but thou wilt frame</LINE>
<LINE>Thyself, forsooth, hereafter theirs, so far</LINE>
<LINE>As thou hast power and person.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This but done,</LINE>
<LINE>Even as she speaks, why, their hearts were yours;</LINE>
<LINE>For they have pardons, being ask'd, as free</LINE>
<LINE>As words to little purpose.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Prithee now,</LINE>
<LINE>Go, and be ruled: although I know thou hadst rather</LINE>
<LINE>Follow thine enemy in a fiery gulf</LINE>
<LINE>Than flatter him in a bower. Here is Cominius.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter COMINIUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have been i' the market-place; and, sir,'tis fit</LINE>
<LINE>You make strong party, or defend yourself</LINE>
<LINE>By calmness or by absence: all's in anger.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Only fair speech.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I think 'twill serve, if he</LINE>
<LINE>Can thereto frame his spirit.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He must, and will</LINE>
<LINE>Prithee now, say you will, and go about it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Must I go show them my unbarbed sconce?</LINE>
<LINE>Must I with base tongue give my noble heart</LINE>
<LINE>A lie that it must bear? Well, I will do't:</LINE>
<LINE>Yet, were there but this single plot to lose,</LINE>
<LINE>This mould of Marcius, they to dust should grind it</LINE>
<LINE>And throw't against the wind. To the market-place!</LINE>
<LINE>You have put me now to such a part which never</LINE>
<LINE>I shall discharge to the life.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, come, we'll prompt you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I prithee now, sweet son, as thou hast said</LINE>
<LINE>My praises made thee first a soldier, so,</LINE>
<LINE>To have my praise for this, perform a part</LINE>
<LINE>Thou hast not done before.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, I must do't:</LINE>
<LINE>Away, my disposition, and possess me</LINE>
<LINE>Some harlot's spirit! my throat of war be turn'd,</LINE>
<LINE>Which quired with my drum, into a pipe</LINE>
<LINE>Small as an eunuch, or the virgin voice</LINE>
<LINE>That babies lulls asleep! the smiles of knaves</LINE>
<LINE>Tent in my cheeks, and schoolboys' tears take up</LINE>
<LINE>The glasses of my sight! a beggar's tongue</LINE>
<LINE>Make motion through my lips, and my arm'd knees,</LINE>
<LINE>Who bow'd but in my stirrup, bend like his</LINE>
<LINE>That hath received an alms! I will not do't,</LINE>
<LINE>Lest I surcease to honour mine own truth</LINE>
<LINE>And by my body's action teach my mind</LINE>
<LINE>A most inherent baseness.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>At thy choice, then:</LINE>
<LINE>To beg of thee, it is my more dishonour</LINE>
<LINE>Than thou of them. Come all to ruin; let</LINE>
<LINE>Thy mother rather feel thy pride than fear</LINE>
<LINE>Thy dangerous stoutness, for I mock at death</LINE>
<LINE>With as big heart as thou. Do as thou list</LINE>
<LINE>Thy valiantness was mine, thou suck'dst it from me,</LINE>
<LINE>But owe thy pride thyself.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pray, be content:</LINE>
<LINE>Mother, I am going to the market-place;</LINE>
<LINE>Chide me no more. I'll mountebank their loves,</LINE>
<LINE>Cog their hearts from them, and come home beloved</LINE>
<LINE>Of all the trades in Rome. Look, I am going:</LINE>
<LINE>Commend me to my wife. I'll return consul;</LINE>
<LINE>Or never trust to what my tongue can do</LINE>
<LINE>I' the way of flattery further.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do your will.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Away! the tribunes do attend you: arm yourself</LINE>
<LINE>To answer mildly; for they are prepared</LINE>
<LINE>With accusations, as I hear, more strong</LINE>
<LINE>Than are upon you yet.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The word is 'mildly.' Pray you, let us go:</LINE>
<LINE>Let them accuse me by invention, I</LINE>
<LINE>Will answer in mine honour.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, but mildly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, mildly be it then. Mildly!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE III.  The same. The Forum.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter SICINIUS and BRUTUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>In this point charge him home, that he affects</LINE>
<LINE>Tyrannical power: if he evade us there,</LINE>
<LINE>Enforce him with his envy to the people,</LINE>
<LINE>And that the spoil got on the Antiates</LINE>
<LINE>Was ne'er distributed.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter an AEdile</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>What, will he come?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AEdile</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He's coming.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How accompanied?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AEdile</SPEAKER>
<LINE>With old Menenius, and those senators</LINE>
<LINE>That always favour'd him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Have you a catalogue</LINE>
<LINE>Of all the voices that we have procured</LINE>
<LINE>Set down by the poll?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AEdile</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have; 'tis ready.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Have you collected them by tribes?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AEdile</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Assemble presently the people hither;</LINE>
<LINE>And when they bear me say 'It shall be so</LINE>
<LINE>I' the right and strength o' the commons,' be it either</LINE>
<LINE>For death, for fine, or banishment, then let them</LINE>
<LINE>If I say fine, cry 'Fine;' if death, cry 'Death.'</LINE>
<LINE>Insisting on the old prerogative</LINE>
<LINE>And power i' the truth o' the cause.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AEdile</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I shall inform them.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And when such time they have begun to cry,</LINE>
<LINE>Let them not cease, but with a din confused</LINE>
<LINE>Enforce the present execution</LINE>
<LINE>Of what we chance to sentence.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AEdile</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Very well.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Make them be strong and ready for this hint,</LINE>
<LINE>When we shall hap to give 't them.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Go about it.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit AEdile</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Put him to choler straight: he hath been used</LINE>
<LINE>Ever to conquer, and to have his worth</LINE>
<LINE>Of contradiction: being once chafed, he cannot</LINE>
<LINE>Be rein'd again to temperance; then he speaks</LINE>
<LINE>What's in his heart; and that is there which looks</LINE>
<LINE>With us to break his neck.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, here he comes.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter CORIOLANUS, MENENIUS, and COMINIUS,
with Senators and Patricians</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Calmly, I do beseech you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, as an ostler, that for the poorest piece</LINE>
<LINE>Will bear the knave by the volume. The honour'd gods</LINE>
<LINE>Keep Rome in safety, and the chairs of justice</LINE>
<LINE>Supplied with worthy men! plant love among 's!</LINE>
<LINE>Throng our large temples with the shows of peace,</LINE>
<LINE>And not our streets with war!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Amen, amen.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A noble wish.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Re-enter AEdile, with Citizens</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Draw near, ye people.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AEdile</SPEAKER>
<LINE>List to your tribunes. Audience: peace, I say!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>First, hear me speak.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Both Tribunes</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, say. Peace, ho!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Shall I be charged no further than this present?</LINE>
<LINE>Must all determine here?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do demand,</LINE>
<LINE>If you submit you to the people's voices,</LINE>
<LINE>Allow their officers and are content</LINE>
<LINE>To suffer lawful censure for such faults</LINE>
<LINE>As shall be proved upon you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am content.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Lo, citizens, he says he is content:</LINE>
<LINE>The warlike service he has done, consider; think</LINE>
<LINE>Upon the wounds his body bears, which show</LINE>
<LINE>Like graves i' the holy churchyard.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Scratches with briers,</LINE>
<LINE>Scars to move laughter only.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Consider further,</LINE>
<LINE>That when he speaks not like a citizen,</LINE>
<LINE>You find him like a soldier: do not take</LINE>
<LINE>His rougher accents for malicious sounds,</LINE>
<LINE>But, as I say, such as become a soldier,</LINE>
<LINE>Rather than envy you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, well, no more.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What is the matter</LINE>
<LINE>That being pass'd for consul with full voice,</LINE>
<LINE>I am so dishonour'd that the very hour</LINE>
<LINE>You take it off again?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Answer to us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Say, then: 'tis true, I ought so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We charge you, that you have contrived to take</LINE>
<LINE>From Rome all season'd office and to wind</LINE>
<LINE>Yourself into a power tyrannical;</LINE>
<LINE>For which you are a traitor to the people.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How! traitor!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, temperately; your promise.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The fires i' the lowest hell fold-in the people!</LINE>
<LINE>Call me their traitor! Thou injurious tribune!</LINE>
<LINE>Within thine eyes sat twenty thousand deaths,</LINE>
<LINE>In thy hand clutch'd as many millions, in</LINE>
<LINE>Thy lying tongue both numbers, I would say</LINE>
<LINE>'Thou liest' unto thee with a voice as free</LINE>
<LINE>As I do pray the gods.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Mark you this, people?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Citizens</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To the rock, to the rock with him!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Peace!</LINE>
<LINE>We need not put new matter to his charge:</LINE>
<LINE>What you have seen him do and heard him speak,</LINE>
<LINE>Beating your officers, cursing yourselves,</LINE>
<LINE>Opposing laws with strokes and here defying</LINE>
<LINE>Those whose great power must try him; even this,</LINE>
<LINE>So criminal and in such capital kind,</LINE>
<LINE>Deserves the extremest death.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But since he hath</LINE>
<LINE>Served well for Rome,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What do you prate of service?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I talk of that, that know it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is this the promise that you made your mother?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Know, I pray you,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know no further:</LINE>
<LINE>Let them pronounce the steep Tarpeian death,</LINE>
<LINE>Vagabond exile, raying, pent to linger</LINE>
<LINE>But with a grain a day, I would not buy</LINE>
<LINE>Their mercy at the price of one fair word;</LINE>
<LINE>Nor cheque my courage for what they can give,</LINE>
<LINE>To have't with saying 'Good morrow.'</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>For that he has,</LINE>
<LINE>As much as in him lies, from time to time</LINE>
<LINE>Envied against the people, seeking means</LINE>
<LINE>To pluck away their power, as now at last</LINE>
<LINE>Given hostile strokes, and that not in the presence</LINE>
<LINE>Of dreaded justice, but on the ministers</LINE>
<LINE>That do distribute it; in the name o' the people</LINE>
<LINE>And in the power of us the tribunes, we,</LINE>
<LINE>Even from this instant, banish him our city,</LINE>
<LINE>In peril of precipitation</LINE>
<LINE>From off the rock Tarpeian never more</LINE>
<LINE>To enter our Rome gates: i' the people's name,</LINE>
<LINE>I say it shall be so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Citizens</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It shall be so, it shall be so; let him away:</LINE>
<LINE>He's banish'd, and it shall be so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hear me, my masters, and my common friends,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He's sentenced; no more hearing.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let me speak:</LINE>
<LINE>I have been consul, and can show for Rome</LINE>
<LINE>Her enemies' marks upon me. I do love</LINE>
<LINE>My country's good with a respect more tender,</LINE>
<LINE>More holy and profound, than mine own life,</LINE>
<LINE>My dear wife's estimate, her womb's increase,</LINE>
<LINE>And treasure of my loins; then if I would</LINE>
<LINE>Speak that,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We know your drift: speak what?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>There's no more to be said, but he is banish'd,</LINE>
<LINE>As enemy to the people and his country:</LINE>
<LINE>It shall be so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Citizens</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It shall be so, it shall be so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You common cry of curs! whose breath I hate</LINE>
<LINE>As reek o' the rotten fens, whose loves I prize</LINE>
<LINE>As the dead carcasses of unburied men</LINE>
<LINE>That do corrupt my air, I banish you;</LINE>
<LINE>And here remain with your uncertainty!</LINE>
<LINE>Let every feeble rumour shake your hearts!</LINE>
<LINE>Your enemies, with nodding of their plumes,</LINE>
<LINE>Fan you into despair! Have the power still</LINE>
<LINE>To banish your defenders; till at length</LINE>
<LINE>Your ignorance, which finds not till it feels,</LINE>
<LINE>Making not reservation of yourselves,</LINE>
<LINE>Still your own foes, deliver you as most</LINE>
<LINE>Abated captives to some nation</LINE>
<LINE>That won you without blows! Despising,</LINE>
<LINE>For you, the city, thus I turn my back:</LINE>
<LINE>There is a world elsewhere.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt CORIOLANUS, COMINIUS, MENENIUS, Senators,
and Patricians</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AEdile</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The people's enemy is gone, is gone!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Citizens</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Our enemy is banish'd! he is gone! Hoo! hoo!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Shouting, and throwing up their caps</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Go, see him out at gates, and follow him,</LINE>
<LINE>As he hath followed you, with all despite;</LINE>
<LINE>Give him deserved vexation. Let a guard</LINE>
<LINE>Attend us through the city.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Citizens</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, come; let's see him out at gates; come.</LINE>
<LINE>The gods preserve our noble tribunes! Come.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

</ACT>

<ACT><TITLE>ACT IV</TITLE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE I.  Rome. Before a gate of the city.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter CORIOLANUS, VOLUMNIA, VIRGILIA, MENENIUS,
COMINIUS, with the young Nobility of Rome</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, leave your tears: a brief farewell: the beast</LINE>
<LINE>With many heads butts me away. Nay, mother,</LINE>
<LINE>Where is your ancient courage? you were used</LINE>
<LINE>To say extremity was the trier of spirits;</LINE>
<LINE>That common chances common men could bear;</LINE>
<LINE>That when the sea was calm all boats alike</LINE>
<LINE>Show'd mastership in floating; fortune's blows,</LINE>
<LINE>When most struck home, being gentle wounded, craves</LINE>
<LINE>A noble cunning: you were used to load me</LINE>
<LINE>With precepts that would make invincible</LINE>
<LINE>The heart that conn'd them.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VIRGILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O heavens! O heavens!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay! prithee, woman,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now the red pestilence strike all trades in Rome,</LINE>
<LINE>And occupations perish!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, what, what!</LINE>
<LINE>I shall be loved when I am lack'd. Nay, mother.</LINE>
<LINE>Resume that spirit, when you were wont to say,</LINE>
<LINE>If you had been the wife of Hercules,</LINE>
<LINE>Six of his labours you'ld have done, and saved</LINE>
<LINE>Your husband so much sweat. Cominius,</LINE>
<LINE>Droop not; adieu. Farewell, my wife, my mother:</LINE>
<LINE>I'll do well yet. Thou old and true Menenius,</LINE>
<LINE>Thy tears are salter than a younger man's,</LINE>
<LINE>And venomous to thine eyes. My sometime general,</LINE>
<LINE>I have seen thee stem, and thou hast oft beheld</LINE>
<LINE>Heart-hardening spectacles; tell these sad women</LINE>
<LINE>'Tis fond to wail inevitable strokes,</LINE>
<LINE>As 'tis to laugh at 'em. My mother, you wot well</LINE>
<LINE>My hazards still have been your solace: and</LINE>
<LINE>Believe't not lightly--though I go alone,</LINE>
<LINE>Like to a lonely dragon, that his fen</LINE>
<LINE>Makes fear'd and talk'd of more than seen--your son</LINE>
<LINE>Will or exceed the common or be caught</LINE>
<LINE>With cautelous baits and practise.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My first son.</LINE>
<LINE>Whither wilt thou go? Take good Cominius</LINE>
<LINE>With thee awhile: determine on some course,</LINE>
<LINE>More than a wild exposture to each chance</LINE>
<LINE>That starts i' the way before thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O the gods!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I'll follow thee a month, devise with thee</LINE>
<LINE>Where thou shalt rest, that thou mayst hear of us</LINE>
<LINE>And we of thee: so if the time thrust forth</LINE>
<LINE>A cause for thy repeal, we shall not send</LINE>
<LINE>O'er the vast world to seek a single man,</LINE>
<LINE>And lose advantage, which doth ever cool</LINE>
<LINE>I' the absence of the needer.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Fare ye well:</LINE>
<LINE>Thou hast years upon thee; and thou art too full</LINE>
<LINE>Of the wars' surfeits, to go rove with one</LINE>
<LINE>That's yet unbruised: bring me but out at gate.</LINE>
<LINE>Come, my sweet wife, my dearest mother, and</LINE>
<LINE>My friends of noble touch, when I am forth,</LINE>
<LINE>Bid me farewell, and smile. I pray you, come.</LINE>
<LINE>While I remain above the ground, you shall</LINE>
<LINE>Hear from me still, and never of me aught</LINE>
<LINE>But what is like me formerly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That's worthily</LINE>
<LINE>As any ear can hear. Come, let's not weep.</LINE>
<LINE>If I could shake off but one seven years</LINE>
<LINE>From these old arms and legs, by the good gods,</LINE>
<LINE>I'ld with thee every foot.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Give me thy hand: Come.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE II.  The same. A  street near the gate.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter SICINIUS, BRUTUS, and an AEdile</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Bid them all home; he's gone, and we'll no further.</LINE>
<LINE>The nobility are vex'd, whom we see have sided</LINE>
<LINE>In his behalf.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now we have shown our power,</LINE>
<LINE>Let us seem humbler after it is done</LINE>
<LINE>Than when it was a-doing.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Bid them home:</LINE>
<LINE>Say their great enemy is gone, and they</LINE>
<LINE>Stand in their ancient strength.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Dismiss them home.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit AEdile</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Here comes his mother.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let's not meet her.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>They say she's mad.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>They have ta'en note of us: keep on your way.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter VOLUMNIA, VIRGILIA, and MENENIUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, ye're well met: the hoarded plague o' the gods</LINE>
<LINE>Requite your love!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Peace, peace; be not so loud.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If that I could for weeping, you should hear,--</LINE>
<LINE>Nay, and you shall hear some.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>To BRUTUS</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Will you be gone?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VIRGILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>To SICINIUS</STAGEDIR>  You shall stay too: I would I had the power</LINE>
<LINE>To say so to my husband.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Are you mankind?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, fool; is that a shame? Note but this fool.</LINE>
<LINE>Was not a man my father? Hadst thou foxship</LINE>
<LINE>To banish him that struck more blows for Rome</LINE>
<LINE>Than thou hast spoken words?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O blessed heavens!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>More noble blows than ever thou wise words;</LINE>
<LINE>And for Rome's good. I'll tell thee what; yet go:</LINE>
<LINE>Nay, but thou shalt stay too: I would my son</LINE>
<LINE>Were in Arabia, and thy tribe before him,</LINE>
<LINE>His good sword in his hand.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What then?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VIRGILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What then!</LINE>
<LINE>He'ld make an end of thy posterity.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Bastards and all.</LINE>
<LINE>Good man, the wounds that he does bear for Rome!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, come, peace.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I would he had continued to his country</LINE>
<LINE>As he began, and not unknit himself</LINE>
<LINE>The noble knot he made.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I would he had.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'I would he had'! 'Twas you incensed the rabble:</LINE>
<LINE>Cats, that can judge as fitly of his worth</LINE>
<LINE>As I can of those mysteries which heaven</LINE>
<LINE>Will not have earth to know.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pray, let us go.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now, pray, sir, get you gone:</LINE>
<LINE>You have done a brave deed. Ere you go, hear this:--</LINE>
<LINE>As far as doth the Capitol exceed</LINE>
<LINE>The meanest house in Rome, so far my son--</LINE>
<LINE>This lady's husband here, this, do you see--</LINE>
<LINE>Whom you have banish'd, does exceed you all.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, well, we'll leave you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why stay we to be baited</LINE>
<LINE>With one that wants her wits?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Take my prayers with you.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exeunt Tribunes</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>I would the gods had nothing else to do</LINE>
<LINE>But to confirm my curses! Could I meet 'em</LINE>
<LINE>But once a-day, it would unclog my heart</LINE>
<LINE>Of what lies heavy to't.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You have told them home;</LINE>
<LINE>And, by my troth, you have cause. You'll sup with me?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Anger's my meat; I sup upon myself,</LINE>
<LINE>And so shall starve with feeding. Come, let's go:</LINE>
<LINE>Leave this faint puling and lament as I do,</LINE>
<LINE>In anger, Juno-like. Come, come, come.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Fie, fie, fie!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE III.  A highway between Rome and Antium.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter a Roman and a Volsce, meeting</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Roman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know you well, sir, and you know</LINE>
<LINE>me: your name, I think, is Adrian.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Volsce</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is so, sir: truly, I have forgot you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Roman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am a Roman; and my services are,</LINE>
<LINE>as you are, against 'em: know you me yet?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Volsce</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nicanor? no.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Roman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The same, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Volsce</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You had more beard when I last saw you; but your</LINE>
<LINE>favour is well approved by your tongue. What's the</LINE>
<LINE>news in Rome? I have a note from the Volscian state,</LINE>
<LINE>to find you out there: you have well saved me a</LINE>
<LINE>day's journey.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Roman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>There hath been in Rome strange insurrections; the</LINE>
<LINE>people against the senators, patricians, and nobles.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Volsce</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hath been! is it ended, then? Our state thinks not</LINE>
<LINE>so: they are in a most warlike preparation, and</LINE>
<LINE>hope to come upon them in the heat of their division.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Roman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The main blaze of it is past, but a small thing</LINE>
<LINE>would make it flame again: for the nobles receive</LINE>
<LINE>so to heart the banishment of that worthy</LINE>
<LINE>Coriolanus, that they are in a ripe aptness to take</LINE>
<LINE>all power from the people and to pluck from them</LINE>
<LINE>their tribunes for ever. This lies glowing, I can</LINE>
<LINE>tell you, and is almost mature for the violent</LINE>
<LINE>breaking out.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Volsce</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Coriolanus banished!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Roman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Banished, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Volsce</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You will be welcome with this intelligence, Nicanor.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Roman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The day serves well for them now. I have heard it</LINE>
<LINE>said, the fittest time to corrupt a man's wife is</LINE>
<LINE>when she's fallen out with her husband. Your noble</LINE>
<LINE>Tullus Aufidius will appear well in these wars, his</LINE>
<LINE>great opposer, Coriolanus, being now in no request</LINE>
<LINE>of his country.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Volsce</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He cannot choose. I am most fortunate, thus</LINE>
<LINE>accidentally to encounter you: you have ended my</LINE>
<LINE>business, and I will merrily accompany you home.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Roman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I shall, between this and supper, tell you most</LINE>
<LINE>strange things from Rome; all tending to the good of</LINE>
<LINE>their adversaries. Have you an army ready, say you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Volsce</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A most royal one; the centurions and their charges,</LINE>
<LINE>distinctly billeted, already in the entertainment,</LINE>
<LINE>and to be on foot at an hour's warning.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Roman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am joyful to hear of their readiness, and am the</LINE>
<LINE>man, I think, that shall set them in present action.</LINE>
<LINE>So, sir, heartily well met, and most glad of your company.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Volsce</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You take my part from me, sir; I have the most cause</LINE>
<LINE>to be glad of yours.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Roman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, let us go together.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE IV.  Antium. Before Aufidius's house.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter CORIOLANUS in mean apparel, disguised
and muffled</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A goodly city is this Antium. City,</LINE>
<LINE>'Tis I that made thy widows: many an heir</LINE>
<LINE>Of these fair edifices 'fore my wars</LINE>
<LINE>Have I heard groan and drop: then know me not,</LINE>
<LINE>Lest that thy wives with spits and boys with stones</LINE>
<LINE>In puny battle slay me.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter a Citizen</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Save you, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Direct me, if it be your will,</LINE>
<LINE>Where great Aufidius lies: is he in Antium?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He is, and feasts the nobles of the state</LINE>
<LINE>At his house this night.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Which is his house, beseech you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This, here before you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thank you, sir: farewell.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit Citizen</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>O world, thy slippery turns! Friends now fast sworn,</LINE>
<LINE>Whose double bosoms seem to wear one heart,</LINE>
<LINE>Whose house, whose bed, whose meal, and exercise,</LINE>
<LINE>Are still together, who twin, as 'twere, in love</LINE>
<LINE>Unseparable, shall within this hour,</LINE>
<LINE>On a dissension of a doit, break out</LINE>
<LINE>To bitterest enmity: so, fellest foes,</LINE>
<LINE>Whose passions and whose plots have broke their sleep,</LINE>
<LINE>To take the one the other, by some chance,</LINE>
<LINE>Some trick not worth an egg, shall grow dear friends</LINE>
<LINE>And interjoin their issues. So with me:</LINE>
<LINE>My birth-place hate I, and my love's upon</LINE>
<LINE>This enemy town. I'll enter: if he slay me,</LINE>
<LINE>He does fair justice; if he give me way,</LINE>
<LINE>I'll do his country service.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE V.  The same. A hall in Aufidius's house.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Music within. Enter a Servingman</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Wine, wine, wine! What service</LINE>
<LINE>is here! I think our fellows are asleep.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Enter a second Servingman</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where's Cotus? my master calls</LINE>
<LINE>for him. Cotus!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Enter CORIOLANUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A goodly house: the feast smells well; but I</LINE>
<LINE>Appear not like a guest.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Re-enter the first Servingman</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What would you have, friend? whence are you?</LINE>
<LINE>Here's no place for you: pray, go to the door.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have deserved no better entertainment,</LINE>
<LINE>In being Coriolanus.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Re-enter second Servingman</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Whence are you, sir? Has the porter his eyes in his</LINE>
<LINE>head; that he gives entrance to such companions?</LINE>
<LINE>Pray, get you out.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Away!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Away! get you away.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now thou'rt troublesome.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Are you so brave? I'll have you talked with anon.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter a third Servingman. The first meets him</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What fellow's this?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A strange one as ever I looked on: I cannot get him</LINE>
<LINE>out of the house: prithee, call my master to him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Retires</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What have you to do here, fellow? Pray you, avoid</LINE>
<LINE>the house.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let me but stand; I will not hurt your hearth.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What are you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A gentleman.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A marvellous poor one.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>True, so I am.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pray you, poor gentleman, take up some other</LINE>
<LINE>station; here's no place for you; pray you, avoid: come.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Follow your function, go, and batten on cold bits.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Pushes him away</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, you will not? Prithee, tell my master what a</LINE>
<LINE>strange guest he has here.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And I shall.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where dwellest thou?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Under the canopy.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Under the canopy!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where's that?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I' the city of kites and crows.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I' the city of kites and crows! What an ass it is!</LINE>
<LINE>Then thou dwellest with daws too?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, I serve not thy master.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How, sir! do you meddle with my master?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay; 'tis an honester service than to meddle with thy</LINE>
<LINE>mistress. Thou pratest, and pratest; serve with thy</LINE>
<LINE>trencher, hence!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Beats him away. Exit third Servingman</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Enter AUFIDIUS with the second Servingman</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where is this fellow?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here, sir: I'ld have beaten him like a dog, but for</LINE>
<LINE>disturbing the lords within.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Retires</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Whence comest thou? what wouldst thou? thy name?</LINE>
<LINE>Why speak'st not? speak, man: what's thy name?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If, Tullus,</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Unmuffling</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Not yet thou knowest me, and, seeing me, dost not</LINE>
<LINE>Think me for the man I am, necessity</LINE>
<LINE>Commands me name myself.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What is thy name?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A name unmusical to the Volscians' ears,</LINE>
<LINE>And harsh in sound to thine.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Say, what's thy name?</LINE>
<LINE>Thou hast a grim appearance, and thy face</LINE>
<LINE>Bears a command in't; though thy tackle's torn.</LINE>
<LINE>Thou show'st a noble vessel: what's thy name?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Prepare thy brow to frown: know'st</LINE>
<LINE>thou me yet?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know thee not: thy name?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My name is Caius Marcius, who hath done</LINE>
<LINE>To thee particularly and to all the Volsces</LINE>
<LINE>Great hurt and mischief; thereto witness may</LINE>
<LINE>My surname, Coriolanus: the painful service,</LINE>
<LINE>The extreme dangers and the drops of blood</LINE>
<LINE>Shed for my thankless country are requited</LINE>
<LINE>But with that surname; a good memory,</LINE>
<LINE>And witness of the malice and displeasure</LINE>
<LINE>Which thou shouldst bear me: only that name remains;</LINE>
<LINE>The cruelty and envy of the people,</LINE>
<LINE>Permitted by our dastard nobles, who</LINE>
<LINE>Have all forsook me, hath devour'd the rest;</LINE>
<LINE>And suffer'd me by the voice of slaves to be</LINE>
<LINE>Whoop'd out of Rome. Now this extremity</LINE>
<LINE>Hath brought me to thy hearth; not out of hope--</LINE>
<LINE>Mistake me not--to save my life, for if</LINE>
<LINE>I had fear'd death, of all the men i' the world</LINE>
<LINE>I would have 'voided thee, but in mere spite,</LINE>
<LINE>To be full quit of those my banishers,</LINE>
<LINE>Stand I before thee here. Then if thou hast</LINE>
<LINE>A heart of wreak in thee, that wilt revenge</LINE>
<LINE>Thine own particular wrongs and stop those maims</LINE>
<LINE>Of shame seen through thy country, speed</LINE>
<LINE>thee straight,</LINE>
<LINE>And make my misery serve thy turn: so use it</LINE>
<LINE>That my revengeful services may prove</LINE>
<LINE>As benefits to thee, for I will fight</LINE>
<LINE>Against my canker'd country with the spleen</LINE>
<LINE>Of all the under fiends. But if so be</LINE>
<LINE>Thou darest not this and that to prove more fortunes</LINE>
<LINE>Thou'rt tired, then, in a word, I also am</LINE>
<LINE>Longer to live most weary, and present</LINE>
<LINE>My throat to thee and to thy ancient malice;</LINE>
<LINE>Which not to cut would show thee but a fool,</LINE>
<LINE>Since I have ever follow'd thee with hate,</LINE>
<LINE>Drawn tuns of blood out of thy country's breast,</LINE>
<LINE>And cannot live but to thy shame, unless</LINE>
<LINE>It be to do thee service.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O Marcius, Marcius!</LINE>
<LINE>Each word thou hast spoke hath weeded from my heart</LINE>
<LINE>A root of ancient envy. If Jupiter</LINE>
<LINE>Should from yond cloud speak divine things,</LINE>
<LINE>And say 'Tis true,' I'ld not believe them more</LINE>
<LINE>Than thee, all noble Marcius. Let me twine</LINE>
<LINE>Mine arms about that body, where against</LINE>
<LINE>My grained ash an hundred times hath broke</LINE>
<LINE>And scarr'd the moon with splinters: here I clip</LINE>
<LINE>The anvil of my sword, and do contest</LINE>
<LINE>As hotly and as nobly with thy love</LINE>
<LINE>As ever in ambitious strength I did</LINE>
<LINE>Contend against thy valour. Know thou first,</LINE>
<LINE>I loved the maid I married; never man</LINE>
<LINE>Sigh'd truer breath; but that I see thee here,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou noble thing! more dances my rapt heart</LINE>
<LINE>Than when I first my wedded mistress saw</LINE>
<LINE>Bestride my threshold. Why, thou Mars! I tell thee,</LINE>
<LINE>We have a power on foot; and I had purpose</LINE>
<LINE>Once more to hew thy target from thy brawn,</LINE>
<LINE>Or lose mine arm fort: thou hast beat me out</LINE>
<LINE>Twelve several times, and I have nightly since</LINE>
<LINE>Dreamt of encounters 'twixt thyself and me;</LINE>
<LINE>We have been down together in my sleep,</LINE>
<LINE>Unbuckling helms, fisting each other's throat,</LINE>
<LINE>And waked half dead with nothing. Worthy Marcius,</LINE>
<LINE>Had we no quarrel else to Rome, but that</LINE>
<LINE>Thou art thence banish'd, we would muster all</LINE>
<LINE>From twelve to seventy, and pouring war</LINE>
<LINE>Into the bowels of ungrateful Rome,</LINE>
<LINE>Like a bold flood o'er-bear. O, come, go in,</LINE>
<LINE>And take our friendly senators by the hands;</LINE>
<LINE>Who now are here, taking their leaves of me,</LINE>
<LINE>Who am prepared against your territories,</LINE>
<LINE>Though not for Rome itself.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You bless me, gods!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Therefore, most absolute sir, if thou wilt have</LINE>
<LINE>The leading of thine own revenges, take</LINE>
<LINE>The one half of my commission; and set down--</LINE>
<LINE>As best thou art experienced, since thou know'st</LINE>
<LINE>Thy country's strength and weakness,--thine own ways;</LINE>
<LINE>Whether to knock against the gates of Rome,</LINE>
<LINE>Or rudely visit them in parts remote,</LINE>
<LINE>To fright them, ere destroy. But come in:</LINE>
<LINE>Let me commend thee first to those that shall</LINE>
<LINE>Say yea to thy desires. A thousand welcomes!</LINE>
<LINE>And more a friend than e'er an enemy;</LINE>
<LINE>Yet, Marcius, that was much. Your hand: most welcome!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt CORIOLANUS and AUFIDIUS. The two
Servingmen come forward</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here's a strange alteration!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>By my hand, I had thought to have strucken him with</LINE>
<LINE>a cudgel; and yet my mind gave me his clothes made a</LINE>
<LINE>false report of him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What an arm he has! he turned me about with his</LINE>
<LINE>finger and his thumb, as one would set up a top.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, I knew by his face that there was something in</LINE>
<LINE>him: he had, sir, a kind of face, methought,--I</LINE>
<LINE>cannot tell how to term it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He had so; looking as it were--would I were hanged,</LINE>
<LINE>but I thought there was more in him than I could think.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So did I, I'll be sworn: he is simply the rarest</LINE>
<LINE>man i' the world.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I think he is: but a greater soldier than he you wot on.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Who, my master?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, it's no matter for that.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Worth six on him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, not so neither: but I take him to be the</LINE>
<LINE>greater soldier.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Faith, look you, one cannot tell how to say that:</LINE>
<LINE>for the defence of a town, our general is excellent.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, and for an assault too.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Re-enter third Servingman</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O slaves, I can tell you news,-- news, you rascals!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Servingman</SPEAKER>
<SPEAKER>Second Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, what, what? let's partake.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I would not be a Roman, of all nations; I had as</LINE>
<LINE>lieve be a condemned man.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Servingman</SPEAKER>
<SPEAKER>Second Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Wherefore? wherefore?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, here's he that was wont to thwack our general,</LINE>
<LINE>Caius Marcius.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why do you say 'thwack our general '?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do not say 'thwack our general;' but he was always</LINE>
<LINE>good enough for him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, we are fellows and friends: he was ever too</LINE>
<LINE>hard for him; I have heard him say so himself.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He was too hard for him directly, to say the troth</LINE>
<LINE>on't: before Corioli he scotched him and notched</LINE>
<LINE>him like a carbon ado.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>An he had been cannibally given, he might have</LINE>
<LINE>broiled and eaten him too.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But, more of thy news?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, he is so made on here within, as if he were son</LINE>
<LINE>and heir to Mars; set at upper end o' the table; no</LINE>
<LINE>question asked him by any of the senators, but they</LINE>
<LINE>stand bald before him: our general himself makes a</LINE>
<LINE>mistress of him: sanctifies himself with's hand and</LINE>
<LINE>turns up the white o' the eye to his discourse. But</LINE>
<LINE>the bottom of the news is that our general is cut i'</LINE>
<LINE>the middle and but one half of what he was</LINE>
<LINE>yesterday; for the other has half, by the entreaty</LINE>
<LINE>and grant of the whole table. He'll go, he says,</LINE>
<LINE>and sowl the porter of Rome gates by the ears: he</LINE>
<LINE>will mow all down before him, and leave his passage polled.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And he's as like to do't as any man I can imagine.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do't! he will do't; for, look you, sir, he has as</LINE>
<LINE>many friends as enemies; which friends, sir, as it</LINE>
<LINE>were, durst not, look you, sir, show themselves, as</LINE>
<LINE>we term it, his friends whilst he's in directitude.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Directitude! what's that?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But when they shall see, sir, his crest up again,</LINE>
<LINE>and the man in blood, they will out of their</LINE>
<LINE>burrows, like conies after rain, and revel all with</LINE>
<LINE>him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But when goes this forward?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To-morrow; to-day; presently; you shall have the</LINE>
<LINE>drum struck up this afternoon: 'tis, as it were, a</LINE>
<LINE>parcel of their feast, and to be executed ere they</LINE>
<LINE>wipe their lips.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, then we shall have a stirring world again.</LINE>
<LINE>This peace is nothing, but to rust iron, increase</LINE>
<LINE>tailors, and breed ballad-makers.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let me have war, say I; it exceeds peace as far as</LINE>
<LINE>day does night; it's spritely, waking, audible, and</LINE>
<LINE>full of vent. Peace is a very apoplexy, lethargy;</LINE>
<LINE>mulled, deaf, sleepy, insensible; a getter of more</LINE>
<LINE>bastard children than war's a destroyer of men.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis so: and as war, in some sort, may be said to</LINE>
<LINE>be a ravisher, so it cannot be denied but peace is a</LINE>
<LINE>great maker of cuckolds.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, and it makes men hate one another.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Servingman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Reason; because they then less need one another.</LINE>
<LINE>The wars for my money. I hope to see Romans as cheap</LINE>
<LINE>as Volscians. They are rising, they are rising.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>All</SPEAKER>
<LINE>In, in, in, in!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE VI.  Rome. A public place.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter SICINIUS and BRUTUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We hear not of him, neither need we fear him;</LINE>
<LINE>His remedies are tame i' the present peace</LINE>
<LINE>And quietness of the people, which before</LINE>
<LINE>Were in wild hurry. Here do we make his friends</LINE>
<LINE>Blush that the world goes well, who rather had,</LINE>
<LINE>Though they themselves did suffer by't, behold</LINE>
<LINE>Dissentious numbers pestering streets than see</LINE>
<LINE>Our tradesmen with in their shops and going</LINE>
<LINE>About their functions friendly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We stood to't in good time.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter MENENIUS</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Is this Menenius?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis he,'tis he: O, he is grown most kind of late.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Both Tribunes</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hail sir!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hail to you both!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Your Coriolanus</LINE>
<LINE>Is not much miss'd, but with his friends:</LINE>
<LINE>The commonwealth doth stand, and so would do,</LINE>
<LINE>Were he more angry at it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>All's well; and might have been much better, if</LINE>
<LINE>He could have temporized.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where is he, hear you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, I hear nothing: his mother and his wife</LINE>
<LINE>Hear nothing from him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter three or four Citizens</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Citizens</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The gods preserve you both!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>God-den, our neighbours.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>God-den to you all, god-den to you all.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ourselves, our wives, and children, on our knees,</LINE>
<LINE>Are bound to pray for you both.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Live, and thrive!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Farewell, kind neighbours: we wish'd Coriolanus</LINE>
<LINE>Had loved you as we did.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Citizens</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now the gods keep you!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Both Tribunes</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Farewell, farewell.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt Citizens</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This is a happier and more comely time</LINE>
<LINE>Than when these fellows ran about the streets,</LINE>
<LINE>Crying confusion.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Caius Marcius was</LINE>
<LINE>A worthy officer i' the war; but insolent,</LINE>
<LINE>O'ercome with pride, ambitious past all thinking,</LINE>
<LINE>Self-loving,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And affecting one sole throne,</LINE>
<LINE>Without assistance.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I think not so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We should by this, to all our lamentation,</LINE>
<LINE>If he had gone forth consul, found it so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The gods have well prevented it, and Rome</LINE>
<LINE>Sits safe and still without him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter an AEdile</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AEdile</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Worthy tribunes,</LINE>
<LINE>There is a slave, whom we have put in prison,</LINE>
<LINE>Reports, the Volsces with two several powers</LINE>
<LINE>Are enter'd in the Roman territories,</LINE>
<LINE>And with the deepest malice of the war</LINE>
<LINE>Destroy what lies before 'em.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis Aufidius,</LINE>
<LINE>Who, hearing of our Marcius' banishment,</LINE>
<LINE>Thrusts forth his horns again into the world;</LINE>
<LINE>Which were inshell'd when Marcius stood for Rome,</LINE>
<LINE>And durst not once peep out.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, what talk you</LINE>
<LINE>Of Marcius?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Go see this rumourer whipp'd. It cannot be</LINE>
<LINE>The Volsces dare break with us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Cannot be!</LINE>
<LINE>We have record that very well it can,</LINE>
<LINE>And three examples of the like have been</LINE>
<LINE>Within my age. But reason with the fellow,</LINE>
<LINE>Before you punish him, where he heard this,</LINE>
<LINE>Lest you shall chance to whip your information</LINE>
<LINE>And beat the messenger who bids beware</LINE>
<LINE>Of what is to be dreaded.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Tell not me:</LINE>
<LINE>I know this cannot be.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not possible.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter a Messenger</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Messenger</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The nobles in great earnestness are going</LINE>
<LINE>All to the senate-house: some news is come</LINE>
<LINE>That turns their countenances.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis this slave;--</LINE>
<LINE>Go whip him, 'fore the people's eyes:--his raising;</LINE>
<LINE>Nothing but his report.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Messenger</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yes, worthy sir,</LINE>
<LINE>The slave's report is seconded; and more,</LINE>
<LINE>More fearful, is deliver'd.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What more fearful?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Messenger</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is spoke freely out of many mouths--</LINE>
<LINE>How probable I do not know--that Marcius,</LINE>
<LINE>Join'd with Aufidius, leads a power 'gainst Rome,</LINE>
<LINE>And vows revenge as spacious as between</LINE>
<LINE>The young'st and oldest thing.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This is most likely!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Raised only, that the weaker sort may wish</LINE>
<LINE>Good Marcius home again.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The very trick on't.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This is unlikely:</LINE>
<LINE>He and Aufidius can no more atone</LINE>
<LINE>Than violentest contrariety.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter a second Messenger</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Messenger</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You are sent for to the senate:</LINE>
<LINE>A fearful army, led by Caius Marcius</LINE>
<LINE>Associated with Aufidius, rages</LINE>
<LINE>Upon our territories; and have already</LINE>
<LINE>O'erborne their way, consumed with fire, and took</LINE>
<LINE>What lay before them.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter COMINIUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, you have made good work!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What news? what news?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You have holp to ravish your own daughters and</LINE>
<LINE>To melt the city leads upon your pates,</LINE>
<LINE>To see your wives dishonour'd to your noses,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What's the news? what's the news?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Your temples burned in their cement, and</LINE>
<LINE>Your franchises, whereon you stood, confined</LINE>
<LINE>Into an auger's bore.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pray now, your news?</LINE>
<LINE>You have made fair work, I fear me.--Pray, your news?--</LINE>
<LINE>If Marcius should be join'd with Volscians,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If!</LINE>
<LINE>He is their god: he leads them like a thing</LINE>
<LINE>Made by some other deity than nature,</LINE>
<LINE>That shapes man better; and they follow him,</LINE>
<LINE>Against us brats, with no less confidence</LINE>
<LINE>Than boys pursuing summer butterflies,</LINE>
<LINE>Or butchers killing flies.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You have made good work,</LINE>
<LINE>You and your apron-men; you that stood so up much</LINE>
<LINE>on the voice of occupation and</LINE>
<LINE>The breath of garlic-eaters!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He will shake</LINE>
<LINE>Your Rome about your ears.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>As Hercules</LINE>
<LINE>Did shake down mellow fruit.</LINE>
<LINE>You have made fair work!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But is this true, sir?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay; and you'll look pale</LINE>
<LINE>Before you find it other. All the regions</LINE>
<LINE>Do smilingly revolt; and who resist</LINE>
<LINE>Are mock'd for valiant ignorance,</LINE>
<LINE>And perish constant fools. Who is't can blame him?</LINE>
<LINE>Your enemies and his find something in him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We are all undone, unless</LINE>
<LINE>The noble man have mercy.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Who shall ask it?</LINE>
<LINE>The tribunes cannot do't for shame; the people</LINE>
<LINE>Deserve such pity of him as the wolf</LINE>
<LINE>Does of the shepherds: for his best friends, if they</LINE>
<LINE>Should say 'Be good to Rome,' they charged him even</LINE>
<LINE>As those should do that had deserved his hate,</LINE>
<LINE>And therein show'd like enemies.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis true:</LINE>
<LINE>If he were putting to my house the brand</LINE>
<LINE>That should consume it, I have not the face</LINE>
<LINE>To say 'Beseech you, cease.' You have made fair hands,</LINE>
<LINE>You and your crafts! you have crafted fair!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You have brought</LINE>
<LINE>A trembling upon Rome, such as was never</LINE>
<LINE>So incapable of help.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Both Tribunes</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Say not we brought it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How! Was it we? we loved him but, like beasts</LINE>
<LINE>And cowardly nobles, gave way unto your clusters,</LINE>
<LINE>Who did hoot him out o' the city.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But I fear</LINE>
<LINE>They'll roar him in again. Tullus Aufidius,</LINE>
<LINE>The second name of men, obeys his points</LINE>
<LINE>As if he were his officer: desperation</LINE>
<LINE>Is all the policy, strength and defence,</LINE>
<LINE>That Rome can make against them.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter a troop of Citizens</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here come the clusters.</LINE>
<LINE>And is Aufidius with him? You are they</LINE>
<LINE>That made the air unwholesome, when you cast</LINE>
<LINE>Your stinking greasy caps in hooting at</LINE>
<LINE>Coriolanus' exile. Now he's coming;</LINE>
<LINE>And not a hair upon a soldier's head</LINE>
<LINE>Which will not prove a whip: as many coxcombs</LINE>
<LINE>As you threw caps up will he tumble down,</LINE>
<LINE>And pay you for your voices. 'Tis no matter;</LINE>
<LINE>if he could burn us all into one coal,</LINE>
<LINE>We have deserved it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Citizens</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Faith, we hear fearful news.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>For mine own part,</LINE>
<LINE>When I said, banish him, I said 'twas pity.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And so did I.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And so did I; and, to say the truth, so did very</LINE>
<LINE>many of us: that we did, we did for the best; and</LINE>
<LINE>though we willingly consented to his banishment, yet</LINE>
<LINE>it was against our will.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ye re goodly things, you voices!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You have made</LINE>
<LINE>Good work, you and your cry! Shall's to the Capitol?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, ay, what else?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt COMINIUS and MENENIUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Go, masters, get you home; be not dismay'd:</LINE>
<LINE>These are a side that would be glad to have</LINE>
<LINE>This true which they so seem to fear. Go home,</LINE>
<LINE>And show no sign of fear.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The gods be good to us! Come, masters, let's home.</LINE>
<LINE>I ever said we were i' the wrong when we banished</LINE>
<LINE>him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So did we all. But, come, let's home.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt Citizens</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do not like this news.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nor I.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let's to the Capitol. Would half my wealth</LINE>
<LINE>Would buy this for a lie!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pray, let us go.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE VII.  A camp, at a small distance from Rome.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter AUFIDIUS and his Lieutenant</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do they still fly to the Roman?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Lieutenant</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do not know what witchcraft's in him, but</LINE>
<LINE>Your soldiers use him as the grace 'fore meat,</LINE>
<LINE>Their talk at table, and their thanks at end;</LINE>
<LINE>And you are darken'd in this action, sir,</LINE>
<LINE>Even by your own.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I cannot help it now,</LINE>
<LINE>Unless, by using means, I lame the foot</LINE>
<LINE>Of our design. He bears himself more proudlier,</LINE>
<LINE>Even to my person, than I thought he would</LINE>
<LINE>When first I did embrace him: yet his nature</LINE>
<LINE>In that's no changeling; and I must excuse</LINE>
<LINE>What cannot be amended.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Lieutenant</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yet I wish, sir,--</LINE>
<LINE>I mean for your particular,--you had not</LINE>
<LINE>Join'd in commission with him; but either</LINE>
<LINE>Had borne the action of yourself, or else</LINE>
<LINE>To him had left it solely.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I understand thee well; and be thou sure,</LINE>
<LINE>when he shall come to his account, he knows not</LINE>
<LINE>What I can urge against him. Although it seems,</LINE>
<LINE>And so he thinks, and is no less apparent</LINE>
<LINE>To the vulgar eye, that he bears all things fairly.</LINE>
<LINE>And shows good husbandry for the Volscian state,</LINE>
<LINE>Fights dragon-like, and does achieve as soon</LINE>
<LINE>As draw his sword; yet he hath left undone</LINE>
<LINE>That which shall break his neck or hazard mine,</LINE>
<LINE>Whene'er we come to our account.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Lieutenant</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sir, I beseech you, think you he'll carry Rome?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>All places yield to him ere he sits down;</LINE>
<LINE>And the nobility of Rome are his:</LINE>
<LINE>The senators and patricians love him too:</LINE>
<LINE>The tribunes are no soldiers; and their people</LINE>
<LINE>Will be as rash in the repeal, as hasty</LINE>
<LINE>To expel him thence. I think he'll be to Rome</LINE>
<LINE>As is the osprey to the fish, who takes it</LINE>
<LINE>By sovereignty of nature. First he was</LINE>
<LINE>A noble servant to them; but he could not</LINE>
<LINE>Carry his honours even: whether 'twas pride,</LINE>
<LINE>Which out of daily fortune ever taints</LINE>
<LINE>The happy man; whether defect of judgment,</LINE>
<LINE>To fail in the disposing of those chances</LINE>
<LINE>Which he was lord of; or whether nature,</LINE>
<LINE>Not to be other than one thing, not moving</LINE>
<LINE>From the casque to the cushion, but commanding peace</LINE>
<LINE>Even with the same austerity and garb</LINE>
<LINE>As he controll'd the war; but one of these--</LINE>
<LINE>As he hath spices of them all, not all,</LINE>
<LINE>For I dare so far free him--made him fear'd,</LINE>
<LINE>So hated, and so banish'd: but he has a merit,</LINE>
<LINE>To choke it in the utterance. So our virtues</LINE>
<LINE>Lie in the interpretation of the time:</LINE>
<LINE>And power, unto itself most commendable,</LINE>
<LINE>Hath not a tomb so evident as a chair</LINE>
<LINE>To extol what it hath done.</LINE>
<LINE>One fire drives out one fire; one nail, one nail;</LINE>
<LINE>Rights by rights falter, strengths by strengths do fail.</LINE>
<LINE>Come, let's away. When, Caius, Rome is thine,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou art poor'st of all; then shortly art thou mine.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

</ACT>

<ACT><TITLE>ACT V</TITLE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE I.  Rome. A public place.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter MENENIUS, COMINIUS, SICINIUS, BRUTUS,
and others</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, I'll not go: you hear what he hath said</LINE>
<LINE>Which was sometime his general; who loved him</LINE>
<LINE>In a most dear particular. He call'd me father:</LINE>
<LINE>But what o' that? Go, you that banish'd him;</LINE>
<LINE>A mile before his tent fall down, and knee</LINE>
<LINE>The way into his mercy: nay, if he coy'd</LINE>
<LINE>To hear Cominius speak, I'll keep at home.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He would not seem to know me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do you hear?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yet one time he did call me by my name:</LINE>
<LINE>I urged our old acquaintance, and the drops</LINE>
<LINE>That we have bled together. Coriolanus</LINE>
<LINE>He would not answer to: forbad all names;</LINE>
<LINE>He was a kind of nothing, titleless,</LINE>
<LINE>Till he had forged himself a name o' the fire</LINE>
<LINE>Of burning Rome.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, so: you have made good work!</LINE>
<LINE>A pair of tribunes that have rack'd for Rome,</LINE>
<LINE>To make coals cheap,--a noble memory!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I minded him how royal 'twas to pardon</LINE>
<LINE>When it was less expected: he replied,</LINE>
<LINE>It was a bare petition of a state</LINE>
<LINE>To one whom they had punish'd.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Very well:</LINE>
<LINE>Could he say less?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I offer'd to awaken his regard</LINE>
<LINE>For's private friends: his answer to me was,</LINE>
<LINE>He could not stay to pick them in a pile</LINE>
<LINE>Of noisome musty chaff: he said 'twas folly,</LINE>
<LINE>For one poor grain or two, to leave unburnt,</LINE>
<LINE>And still to nose the offence.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>For one poor grain or two!</LINE>
<LINE>I am one of those; his mother, wife, his child,</LINE>
<LINE>And this brave fellow too, we are the grains:</LINE>
<LINE>You are the musty chaff; and you are smelt</LINE>
<LINE>Above the moon: we must be burnt for you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, pray, be patient: if you refuse your aid</LINE>
<LINE>In this so never-needed help, yet do not</LINE>
<LINE>Upbraid's with our distress. But, sure, if you</LINE>
<LINE>Would be your country's pleader, your good tongue,</LINE>
<LINE>More than the instant army we can make,</LINE>
<LINE>Might stop our countryman.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, I'll not meddle.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pray you, go to him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What should I do?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Only make trial what your love can do</LINE>
<LINE>For Rome, towards Marcius.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, and say that Marcius</LINE>
<LINE>Return me, as Cominius is return'd,</LINE>
<LINE>Unheard; what then?</LINE>
<LINE>But as a discontented friend, grief-shot</LINE>
<LINE>With his unkindness? say't be so?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yet your good will</LINE>
<LINE>must have that thanks from Rome, after the measure</LINE>
<LINE>As you intended well.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I'll undertake 't:</LINE>
<LINE>I think he'll hear me. Yet, to bite his lip</LINE>
<LINE>And hum at good Cominius, much unhearts me.</LINE>
<LINE>He was not taken well; he had not dined:</LINE>
<LINE>The veins unfill'd, our blood is cold, and then</LINE>
<LINE>We pout upon the morning, are unapt</LINE>
<LINE>To give or to forgive; but when we have stuff'd</LINE>
<LINE>These and these conveyances of our blood</LINE>
<LINE>With wine and feeding, we have suppler souls</LINE>
<LINE>Than in our priest-like fasts: therefore I'll watch him</LINE>
<LINE>Till he be dieted to my request,</LINE>
<LINE>And then I'll set upon him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You know the very road into his kindness,</LINE>
<LINE>And cannot lose your way.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good faith, I'll prove him,</LINE>
<LINE>Speed how it will. I shall ere long have knowledge</LINE>
<LINE>Of my success.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He'll never hear him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>COMINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I tell you, he does sit in gold, his eye</LINE>
<LINE>Red as 'twould burn Rome; and his injury</LINE>
<LINE>The gaoler to his pity. I kneel'd before him;</LINE>
<LINE>'Twas very faintly he said 'Rise;' dismiss'd me</LINE>
<LINE>Thus, with his speechless hand: what he would do,</LINE>
<LINE>He sent in writing after me; what he would not,</LINE>
<LINE>Bound with an oath to yield to his conditions:</LINE>
<LINE>So that all hope is vain.</LINE>
<LINE>Unless his noble mother, and his wife;</LINE>
<LINE>Who, as I hear, mean to solicit him</LINE>
<LINE>For mercy to his country. Therefore, let's hence,</LINE>
<LINE>And with our fair entreaties haste them on.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE II.  Entrance of the Volscian camp before Rome. Two Sentinels on guard.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter to them, MENENIUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Stay: whence are you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Stand, and go back.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You guard like men; 'tis well: but, by your leave,</LINE>
<LINE>I am an officer of state, and come</LINE>
<LINE>To speak with Coriolanus.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>From whence?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>From Rome.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You may not pass, you must return: our general</LINE>
<LINE>Will no more hear from thence.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You'll see your Rome embraced with fire before</LINE>
<LINE>You'll speak with Coriolanus.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good my friends,</LINE>
<LINE>If you have heard your general talk of Rome,</LINE>
<LINE>And of his friends there, it is lots to blanks,</LINE>
<LINE>My name hath touch'd your ears it is Menenius.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Be it so; go back: the virtue of your name</LINE>
<LINE>Is not here passable.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I tell thee, fellow,</LINE>
<LINE>The general is my lover: I have been</LINE>
<LINE>The book of his good acts, whence men have read</LINE>
<LINE>His name unparallel'd, haply amplified;</LINE>
<LINE>For I have ever verified my friends,</LINE>
<LINE>Of whom he's chief, with all the size that verity</LINE>
<LINE>Would without lapsing suffer: nay, sometimes,</LINE>
<LINE>Like to a bowl upon a subtle ground,</LINE>
<LINE>I have tumbled past the throw; and in his praise</LINE>
<LINE>Have almost stamp'd the leasing: therefore, fellow,</LINE>
<LINE>I must have leave to pass.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Faith, sir, if you had told as many lies in his</LINE>
<LINE>behalf as you have uttered words in your own, you</LINE>
<LINE>should not pass here; no, though it were as virtuous</LINE>
<LINE>to lie as to live chastely. Therefore, go back.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Prithee, fellow, remember my name is Menenius,</LINE>
<LINE>always factionary on the party of your general.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Howsoever you have been his liar, as you say you</LINE>
<LINE>have, I am one that, telling true under him, must</LINE>
<LINE>say, you cannot pass. Therefore, go back.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Has he dined, canst thou tell? for I would not</LINE>
<LINE>speak with him till after dinner.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You are a Roman, are you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am, as thy general is.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then you should hate Rome, as he does. Can you,</LINE>
<LINE>when you have pushed out your gates the very</LINE>
<LINE>defender of them, and, in a violent popular</LINE>
<LINE>ignorance, given your enemy your shield, think to</LINE>
<LINE>front his revenges with the easy groans of old</LINE>
<LINE>women, the virginal palms of your daughters, or with</LINE>
<LINE>the palsied intercession of such a decayed dotant as</LINE>
<LINE>you seem to be? Can you think to blow out the</LINE>
<LINE>intended fire your city is ready to flame in, with</LINE>
<LINE>such weak breath as this? No, you are deceived;</LINE>
<LINE>therefore, back to Rome, and prepare for your</LINE>
<LINE>execution: you are condemned, our general has sworn</LINE>
<LINE>you out of reprieve and pardon.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sirrah, if thy captain knew I were here, he would</LINE>
<LINE>use me with estimation.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, my captain knows you not.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I mean, thy general.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My general cares not for you. Back, I say, go; lest</LINE>
<LINE>I let forth your half-pint of blood; back,--that's</LINE>
<LINE>the utmost of your having: back.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, but, fellow, fellow,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter CORIOLANUS and AUFIDIUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What's the matter?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now, you companion, I'll say an errand for you:</LINE>
<LINE>You shall know now that I am in estimation; you shall</LINE>
<LINE>perceive that a Jack guardant cannot office me from</LINE>
<LINE>my son Coriolanus: guess, but by my entertainment</LINE>
<LINE>with him, if thou standest not i' the state of</LINE>
<LINE>hanging, or of some death more long in</LINE>
<LINE>spectatorship, and crueller in suffering; behold now</LINE>
<LINE>presently, and swoon for what's to come upon thee.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>To CORIOLANUS</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>The glorious gods sit in hourly synod about thy</LINE>
<LINE>particular prosperity, and love thee no worse than</LINE>
<LINE>thy old father Menenius does! O my son, my son!</LINE>
<LINE>thou art preparing fire for us; look thee, here's</LINE>
<LINE>water to quench it. I was hardly moved to come to</LINE>
<LINE>thee; but being assured none but myself could move</LINE>
<LINE>thee, I have been blown out of your gates with</LINE>
<LINE>sighs; and conjure thee to pardon Rome, and thy</LINE>
<LINE>petitionary countrymen. The good gods assuage thy</LINE>
<LINE>wrath, and turn the dregs of it upon this varlet</LINE>
<LINE>here,--this, who, like a block, hath denied my</LINE>
<LINE>access to thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Away!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How! away!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Wife, mother, child, I know not. My affairs</LINE>
<LINE>Are servanted to others: though I owe</LINE>
<LINE>My revenge properly, my remission lies</LINE>
<LINE>In Volscian breasts. That we have been familiar,</LINE>
<LINE>Ingrate forgetfulness shall poison, rather</LINE>
<LINE>Than pity note how much. Therefore, be gone.</LINE>
<LINE>Mine ears against your suits are stronger than</LINE>
<LINE>Your gates against my force. Yet, for I loved thee,</LINE>
<LINE>Take this along; I writ it for thy sake</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Gives a letter</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>And would have rent it. Another word, Menenius,</LINE>
<LINE>I will not hear thee speak. This man, Aufidius,</LINE>
<LINE>Was my beloved in Rome: yet thou behold'st!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You keep a constant temper.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt CORIOLANUS and AUFIDIUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now, sir, is your name Menenius?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis a spell, you see, of much power: you know the</LINE>
<LINE>way home again.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do you hear how we are shent for keeping your</LINE>
<LINE>greatness back?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What cause, do you think, I have to swoon?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I neither care for the world nor your general: for</LINE>
<LINE>such things as you, I can scarce think there's any,</LINE>
<LINE>ye're so slight. He that hath a will to die by</LINE>
<LINE>himself fears it not from another: let your general</LINE>
<LINE>do his worst. For you, be that you are, long; and</LINE>
<LINE>your misery increase with your age! I say to you,</LINE>
<LINE>as I was said to, Away!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A noble fellow, I warrant him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The worthy fellow is our general: he's the rock, the</LINE>
<LINE>oak not to be wind-shaken.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE III.  The tent of Coriolanus.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter CORIOLANUS, AUFIDIUS, and others</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We will before the walls of Rome tomorrow</LINE>
<LINE>Set down our host. My partner in this action,</LINE>
<LINE>You must report to the Volscian lords, how plainly</LINE>
<LINE>I have borne this business.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Only their ends</LINE>
<LINE>You have respected; stopp'd your ears against</LINE>
<LINE>The general suit of Rome; never admitted</LINE>
<LINE>A private whisper, no, not with such friends</LINE>
<LINE>That thought them sure of you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This last old man,</LINE>
<LINE>Whom with a crack'd heart I have sent to Rome,</LINE>
<LINE>Loved me above the measure of a father;</LINE>
<LINE>Nay, godded me, indeed. Their latest refuge</LINE>
<LINE>Was to send him; for whose old love I have,</LINE>
<LINE>Though I show'd sourly to him, once more offer'd</LINE>
<LINE>The first conditions, which they did refuse</LINE>
<LINE>And cannot now accept; to grace him only</LINE>
<LINE>That thought he could do more, a very little</LINE>
<LINE>I have yielded to: fresh embassies and suits,</LINE>
<LINE>Nor from the state nor private friends, hereafter</LINE>
<LINE>Will I lend ear to. Ha! what shout is this?</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Shout within</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Shall I be tempted to infringe my vow</LINE>
<LINE>In the same time 'tis made? I will not.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter in mourning habits, VIRGILIA, VOLUMNIA,
leading young MARCIUS, VALERIA, and Attendants</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>My wife comes foremost; then the honour'd mould</LINE>
<LINE>Wherein this trunk was framed, and in her hand</LINE>
<LINE>The grandchild to her blood. But, out, affection!</LINE>
<LINE>All bond and privilege of nature, break!</LINE>
<LINE>Let it be virtuous to be obstinate.</LINE>
<LINE>What is that curt'sy worth? or those doves' eyes,</LINE>
<LINE>Which can make gods forsworn? I melt, and am not</LINE>
<LINE>Of stronger earth than others. My mother bows;</LINE>
<LINE>As if Olympus to a molehill should</LINE>
<LINE>In supplication nod: and my young boy</LINE>
<LINE>Hath an aspect of intercession, which</LINE>
<LINE>Great nature cries 'Deny not.' let the Volsces</LINE>
<LINE>Plough Rome and harrow Italy: I'll never</LINE>
<LINE>Be such a gosling to obey instinct, but stand,</LINE>
<LINE>As if a man were author of himself</LINE>
<LINE>And knew no other kin.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VIRGILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord and husband!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>These eyes are not the same I wore in Rome.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VIRGILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The sorrow that delivers us thus changed</LINE>
<LINE>Makes you think so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Like a dull actor now,</LINE>
<LINE>I have forgot my part, and I am out,</LINE>
<LINE>Even to a full disgrace. Best of my flesh,</LINE>
<LINE>Forgive my tyranny; but do not say</LINE>
<LINE>For that 'Forgive our Romans.' O, a kiss</LINE>
<LINE>Long as my exile, sweet as my revenge!</LINE>
<LINE>Now, by the jealous queen of heaven, that kiss</LINE>
<LINE>I carried from thee, dear; and my true lip</LINE>
<LINE>Hath virgin'd it e'er since. You gods! I prate,</LINE>
<LINE>And the most noble mother of the world</LINE>
<LINE>Leave unsaluted: sink, my knee, i' the earth;</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Kneels</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Of thy deep duty more impression show</LINE>
<LINE>Than that of common sons.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, stand up blest!</LINE>
<LINE>Whilst, with no softer cushion than the flint,</LINE>
<LINE>I kneel before thee; and unproperly</LINE>
<LINE>Show duty, as mistaken all this while</LINE>
<LINE>Between the child and parent.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Kneels</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What is this?</LINE>
<LINE>Your knees to me? to your corrected son?</LINE>
<LINE>Then let the pebbles on the hungry beach</LINE>
<LINE>Fillip the stars; then let the mutinous winds</LINE>
<LINE>Strike the proud cedars 'gainst the fiery sun;</LINE>
<LINE>Murdering impossibility, to make</LINE>
<LINE>What cannot be, slight work.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thou art my warrior;</LINE>
<LINE>I holp to frame thee. Do you know this lady?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The noble sister of Publicola,</LINE>
<LINE>The moon of Rome, chaste as the icicle</LINE>
<LINE>That's curdied by the frost from purest snow</LINE>
<LINE>And hangs on Dian's temple: dear Valeria!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This is a poor epitome of yours,</LINE>
<LINE>Which by the interpretation of full time</LINE>
<LINE>May show like all yourself.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The god of soldiers,</LINE>
<LINE>With the consent of supreme Jove, inform</LINE>
<LINE>Thy thoughts with nobleness; that thou mayst prove</LINE>
<LINE>To shame unvulnerable, and stick i' the wars</LINE>
<LINE>Like a great sea-mark, standing every flaw,</LINE>
<LINE>And saving those that eye thee!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Your knee, sirrah.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That's my brave boy!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Even he, your wife, this lady, and myself,</LINE>
<LINE>Are suitors to you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I beseech you, peace:</LINE>
<LINE>Or, if you'ld ask, remember this before:</LINE>
<LINE>The thing I have forsworn to grant may never</LINE>
<LINE>Be held by you denials. Do not bid me</LINE>
<LINE>Dismiss my soldiers, or capitulate</LINE>
<LINE>Again with Rome's mechanics: tell me not</LINE>
<LINE>Wherein I seem unnatural: desire not</LINE>
<LINE>To ally my rages and revenges with</LINE>
<LINE>Your colder reasons.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, no more, no more!</LINE>
<LINE>You have said you will not grant us any thing;</LINE>
<LINE>For we have nothing else to ask, but that</LINE>
<LINE>Which you deny already: yet we will ask;</LINE>
<LINE>That, if you fail in our request, the blame</LINE>
<LINE>May hang upon your hardness: therefore hear us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Aufidius, and you Volsces, mark; for we'll</LINE>
<LINE>Hear nought from Rome in private. Your request?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Should we be silent and not speak, our raiment</LINE>
<LINE>And state of bodies would bewray what life</LINE>
<LINE>We have led since thy exile. Think with thyself</LINE>
<LINE>How more unfortunate than all living women</LINE>
<LINE>Are we come hither: since that thy sight,</LINE>
<LINE>which should</LINE>
<LINE>Make our eyes flow with joy, hearts dance</LINE>
<LINE>with comforts,</LINE>
<LINE>Constrains them weep and shake with fear and sorrow;</LINE>
<LINE>Making the mother, wife and child to see</LINE>
<LINE>The son, the husband and the father tearing</LINE>
<LINE>His country's bowels out. And to poor we</LINE>
<LINE>Thine enmity's most capital: thou barr'st us</LINE>
<LINE>Our prayers to the gods, which is a comfort</LINE>
<LINE>That all but we enjoy; for how can we,</LINE>
<LINE>Alas, how can we for our country pray.</LINE>
<LINE>Whereto we are bound, together with thy victory,</LINE>
<LINE>Whereto we are bound? alack, or we must lose</LINE>
<LINE>The country, our dear nurse, or else thy person,</LINE>
<LINE>Our comfort in the country. We must find</LINE>
<LINE>An evident calamity, though we had</LINE>
<LINE>Our wish, which side should win: for either thou</LINE>
<LINE>Must, as a foreign recreant, be led</LINE>
<LINE>With manacles thorough our streets, or else</LINE>
<LINE>triumphantly tread on thy country's ruin,</LINE>
<LINE>And bear the palm for having bravely shed</LINE>
<LINE>Thy wife and children's blood. For myself, son,</LINE>
<LINE>I purpose not to wait on fortune till</LINE>
<LINE>These wars determine: if I cannot persuade thee</LINE>
<LINE>Rather to show a noble grace to both parts</LINE>
<LINE>Than seek the end of one, thou shalt no sooner</LINE>
<LINE>March to assault thy country than to tread--</LINE>
<LINE>Trust to't, thou shalt not--on thy mother's womb,</LINE>
<LINE>That brought thee to this world.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VIRGILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, and mine,</LINE>
<LINE>That brought you forth this boy, to keep your name</LINE>
<LINE>Living to time.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Young MARCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A' shall not tread on me;</LINE>
<LINE>I'll run away till I am bigger, but then I'll fight.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not of a woman's tenderness to be,</LINE>
<LINE>Requires nor child nor woman's face to see.</LINE>
<LINE>I have sat too long.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Rising</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, go not from us thus.</LINE>
<LINE>If it were so that our request did tend</LINE>
<LINE>To save the Romans, thereby to destroy</LINE>
<LINE>The Volsces whom you serve, you might condemn us,</LINE>
<LINE>As poisonous of your honour: no; our suit</LINE>
<LINE>Is that you reconcile them: while the Volsces</LINE>
<LINE>May say 'This mercy we have show'd;' the Romans,</LINE>
<LINE>'This we received;' and each in either side</LINE>
<LINE>Give the all-hail to thee and cry 'Be blest</LINE>
<LINE>For making up this peace!' Thou know'st, great son,</LINE>
<LINE>The end of war's uncertain, but this certain,</LINE>
<LINE>That, if thou conquer Rome, the benefit</LINE>
<LINE>Which thou shalt thereby reap is such a name,</LINE>
<LINE>Whose repetition will be dogg'd with curses;</LINE>
<LINE>Whose chronicle thus writ: 'The man was noble,</LINE>
<LINE>But with his last attempt he wiped it out;</LINE>
<LINE>Destroy'd his country, and his name remains</LINE>
<LINE>To the ensuing age abhorr'd.' Speak to me, son:</LINE>
<LINE>Thou hast affected the fine strains of honour,</LINE>
<LINE>To imitate the graces of the gods;</LINE>
<LINE>To tear with thunder the wide cheeks o' the air,</LINE>
<LINE>And yet to charge thy sulphur with a bolt</LINE>
<LINE>That should but rive an oak. Why dost not speak?</LINE>
<LINE>Think'st thou it honourable for a noble man</LINE>
<LINE>Still to remember wrongs? Daughter, speak you:</LINE>
<LINE>He cares not for your weeping. Speak thou, boy:</LINE>
<LINE>Perhaps thy childishness will move him more</LINE>
<LINE>Than can our reasons. There's no man in the world</LINE>
<LINE>More bound to 's mother; yet here he lets me prate</LINE>
<LINE>Like one i' the stocks. Thou hast never in thy life</LINE>
<LINE>Show'd thy dear mother any courtesy,</LINE>
<LINE>When she, poor hen, fond of no second brood,</LINE>
<LINE>Has cluck'd thee to the wars and safely home,</LINE>
<LINE>Loaden with honour. Say my request's unjust,</LINE>
<LINE>And spurn me back: but if it be not so,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou art not honest; and the gods will plague thee,</LINE>
<LINE>That thou restrain'st from me the duty which</LINE>
<LINE>To a mother's part belongs. He turns away:</LINE>
<LINE>Down, ladies; let us shame him with our knees.</LINE>
<LINE>To his surname Coriolanus 'longs more pride</LINE>
<LINE>Than pity to our prayers. Down: an end;</LINE>
<LINE>This is the last: so we will home to Rome,</LINE>
<LINE>And die among our neighbours. Nay, behold 's:</LINE>
<LINE>This boy, that cannot tell what he would have</LINE>
<LINE>But kneels and holds up bands for fellowship,</LINE>
<LINE>Does reason our petition with more strength</LINE>
<LINE>Than thou hast to deny 't. Come, let us go:</LINE>
<LINE>This fellow had a Volscian to his mother;</LINE>
<LINE>His wife is in Corioli and his child</LINE>
<LINE>Like him by chance. Yet give us our dispatch:</LINE>
<LINE>I am hush'd until our city be a-fire,</LINE>
<LINE>And then I'll speak a little.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>He holds her by the hand, silent</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O mother, mother!</LINE>
<LINE>What have you done? Behold, the heavens do ope,</LINE>
<LINE>The gods look down, and this unnatural scene</LINE>
<LINE>They laugh at. O my mother, mother! O!</LINE>
<LINE>You have won a happy victory to Rome;</LINE>
<LINE>But, for your son,--believe it, O, believe it,</LINE>
<LINE>Most dangerously you have with him prevail'd,</LINE>
<LINE>If not most mortal to him. But, let it come.</LINE>
<LINE>Aufidius, though I cannot make true wars,</LINE>
<LINE>I'll frame convenient peace. Now, good Aufidius,</LINE>
<LINE>Were you in my stead, would you have heard</LINE>
<LINE>A mother less? or granted less, Aufidius?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I was moved withal.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I dare be sworn you were:</LINE>
<LINE>And, sir, it is no little thing to make</LINE>
<LINE>Mine eyes to sweat compassion. But, good sir,</LINE>
<LINE>What peace you'll make, advise me: for my part,</LINE>
<LINE>I'll not to Rome, I'll back with you; and pray you,</LINE>
<LINE>Stand to me in this cause. O mother! wife!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>Aside</STAGEDIR>  I am glad thou hast set thy mercy and</LINE>
<LINE>thy honour</LINE>
<LINE>At difference in thee: out of that I'll work</LINE>
<LINE>Myself a former fortune.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>The Ladies make signs to CORIOLANUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, by and by;</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>To VOLUMNIA, VIRGILIA, &amp;c</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>But we will drink together; and you shall bear</LINE>
<LINE>A better witness back than words, which we,</LINE>
<LINE>On like conditions, will have counter-seal'd.</LINE>
<LINE>Come, enter with us. Ladies, you deserve</LINE>
<LINE>To have a temple built you: all the swords</LINE>
<LINE>In Italy, and her confederate arms,</LINE>
<LINE>Could not have made this peace.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE IV.  Rome. A public place.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter MENENIUS and SICINIUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>See you yond coign o' the Capitol, yond</LINE>
<LINE>corner-stone?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, what of that?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If it be possible for you to displace it with your</LINE>
<LINE>little finger, there is some hope the ladies of</LINE>
<LINE>Rome, especially his mother, may prevail with him.</LINE>
<LINE>But I say there is no hope in't: our throats are</LINE>
<LINE>sentenced and stay upon execution.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is't possible that so short a time can alter the</LINE>
<LINE>condition of a man!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>There is differency between a grub and a butterfly;</LINE>
<LINE>yet your butterfly was a grub. This Marcius is grown</LINE>
<LINE>from man to dragon: he has wings; he's more than a</LINE>
<LINE>creeping thing.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He loved his mother dearly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So did he me: and he no more remembers his mother</LINE>
<LINE>now than an eight-year-old horse. The tartness</LINE>
<LINE>of his face sours ripe grapes: when he walks, he</LINE>
<LINE>moves like an engine, and the ground shrinks before</LINE>
<LINE>his treading: he is able to pierce a corslet with</LINE>
<LINE>his eye; talks like a knell, and his hum is a</LINE>
<LINE>battery. He sits in his state, as a thing made for</LINE>
<LINE>Alexander. What he bids be done is finished with</LINE>
<LINE>his bidding. He wants nothing of a god but eternity</LINE>
<LINE>and a heaven to throne in.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yes, mercy, if you report him truly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I paint him in the character. Mark what mercy his</LINE>
<LINE>mother shall bring from him: there is no more mercy</LINE>
<LINE>in him than there is milk in a male tiger; that</LINE>
<LINE>shall our poor city find: and all this is long of</LINE>
<LINE>you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The gods be good unto us!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, in such a case the gods will not be good unto</LINE>
<LINE>us. When we banished him, we respected not them;</LINE>
<LINE>and, he returning to break our necks, they respect not us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter a Messenger</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Messenger</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sir, if you'ld save your life, fly to your house:</LINE>
<LINE>The plebeians have got your fellow-tribune</LINE>
<LINE>And hale him up and down, all swearing, if</LINE>
<LINE>The Roman ladies bring not comfort home,</LINE>
<LINE>They'll give him death by inches.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter a second Messenger</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What's the news?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Messenger</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good news, good news; the ladies have prevail'd,</LINE>
<LINE>The Volscians are dislodged, and Marcius gone:</LINE>
<LINE>A merrier day did never yet greet Rome,</LINE>
<LINE>No, not the expulsion of the Tarquins.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Friend,</LINE>
<LINE>Art thou certain this is true? is it most certain?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Messenger</SPEAKER>
<LINE>As certain as I know the sun is fire:</LINE>
<LINE>Where have you lurk'd, that you make doubt of it?</LINE>
<LINE>Ne'er through an arch so hurried the blown tide,</LINE>
<LINE>As the recomforted through the gates. Why, hark you!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Trumpets; hautboys; drums beat; all together</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>The trumpets, sackbuts, psalteries and fifes,</LINE>
<LINE>Tabours and cymbals and the shouting Romans,</LINE>
<LINE>Make the sun dance. Hark you!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>A shout within</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MENENIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This is good news:</LINE>
<LINE>I will go meet the ladies. This Volumnia</LINE>
<LINE>Is worth of consuls, senators, patricians,</LINE>
<LINE>A city full; of tribunes, such as you,</LINE>
<LINE>A sea and land full. You have pray'd well to-day:</LINE>
<LINE>This morning for ten thousand of your throats</LINE>
<LINE>I'd not have given a doit. Hark, how they joy!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Music still, with shouts</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>First, the gods bless you for your tidings; next,</LINE>
<LINE>Accept my thankfulness.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Messenger</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sir, we have all</LINE>
<LINE>Great cause to give great thanks.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>They are near the city?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Messenger</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Almost at point to enter.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>SICINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We will meet them,</LINE>
<LINE>And help the joy.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE V.  The same. A street near the gate.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter two Senators with VOLUMNIA, VIRGILIA,
VALERIA, &amp;c. passing over the stage,
followed by Patricians and others</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Behold our patroness, the life of Rome!</LINE>
<LINE>Call all your tribes together, praise the gods,</LINE>
<LINE>And make triumphant fires; strew flowers before them:</LINE>
<LINE>Unshout the noise that banish'd Marcius,</LINE>
<LINE>Repeal him with the welcome of his mother;</LINE>
<LINE>Cry 'Welcome, ladies, welcome!'</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>All</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Welcome, ladies, Welcome!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>A flourish with drums and trumpets. Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE VI.  Antium. A public place.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter TULLUS AUFIDIUS, with Attendants</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Go tell the lords o' the city I am here:</LINE>
<LINE>Deliver them this paper: having read it,</LINE>
<LINE>Bid them repair to the market place; where I,</LINE>
<LINE>Even in theirs and in the commons' ears,</LINE>
<LINE>Will vouch the truth of it. Him I accuse</LINE>
<LINE>The city ports by this hath enter'd and</LINE>
<LINE>Intends to appear before the people, hoping</LINE>
<LINE>To purge herself with words: dispatch.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exeunt Attendants</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Enter three or four Conspirators of AUFIDIUS' faction</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Most welcome!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Conspirator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How is it with our general?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Even so</LINE>
<LINE>As with a man by his own alms empoison'd,</LINE>
<LINE>And with his charity slain.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Conspirator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Most noble sir,</LINE>
<LINE>If you do hold the same intent wherein</LINE>
<LINE>You wish'd us parties, we'll deliver you</LINE>
<LINE>Of your great danger.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sir, I cannot tell:</LINE>
<LINE>We must proceed as we do find the people.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Conspirator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The people will remain uncertain whilst</LINE>
<LINE>'Twixt you there's difference; but the fall of either</LINE>
<LINE>Makes the survivor heir of all.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know it;</LINE>
<LINE>And my pretext to strike at him admits</LINE>
<LINE>A good construction. I raised him, and I pawn'd</LINE>
<LINE>Mine honour for his truth: who being so heighten'd,</LINE>
<LINE>He water'd his new plants with dews of flattery,</LINE>
<LINE>Seducing so my friends; and, to this end,</LINE>
<LINE>He bow'd his nature, never known before</LINE>
<LINE>But to be rough, unswayable and free.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Conspirator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sir, his stoutness</LINE>
<LINE>When he did stand for consul, which he lost</LINE>
<LINE>By lack of stooping,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That I would have spoke of:</LINE>
<LINE>Being banish'd for't, he came unto my hearth;</LINE>
<LINE>Presented to my knife his throat: I took him;</LINE>
<LINE>Made him joint-servant with me; gave him way</LINE>
<LINE>In all his own desires; nay, let him choose</LINE>
<LINE>Out of my files, his projects to accomplish,</LINE>
<LINE>My best and freshest men; served his designments</LINE>
<LINE>In mine own person; holp to reap the fame</LINE>
<LINE>Which he did end all his; and took some pride</LINE>
<LINE>To do myself this wrong: till, at the last,</LINE>
<LINE>I seem'd his follower, not partner, and</LINE>
<LINE>He waged me with his countenance, as if</LINE>
<LINE>I had been mercenary.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Conspirator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So he did, my lord:</LINE>
<LINE>The army marvell'd at it, and, in the last,</LINE>
<LINE>When he had carried Rome and that we look'd</LINE>
<LINE>For no less spoil than glory,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>There was it:</LINE>
<LINE>For which my sinews shall be stretch'd upon him.</LINE>
<LINE>At a few drops of women's rheum, which are</LINE>
<LINE>As cheap as lies, he sold the blood and labour</LINE>
<LINE>Of our great action: therefore shall he die,</LINE>
<LINE>And I'll renew me in his fall. But, hark!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Drums and trumpets sound, with great shouts of
the People</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Conspirator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Your native town you enter'd like a post,</LINE>
<LINE>And had no welcomes home: but he returns,</LINE>
<LINE>Splitting the air with noise.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Conspirator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And patient fools,</LINE>
<LINE>Whose children he hath slain, their base throats tear</LINE>
<LINE>With giving him glory.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Conspirator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Therefore, at your vantage,</LINE>
<LINE>Ere he express himself, or move the people</LINE>
<LINE>With what he would say, let him feel your sword,</LINE>
<LINE>Which we will second. When he lies along,</LINE>
<LINE>After your way his tale pronounced shall bury</LINE>
<LINE>His reasons with his body.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Say no more:</LINE>
<LINE>Here come the lords.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter the Lords of the city</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>All The Lords</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You are most welcome home.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have not deserved it.</LINE>
<LINE>But, worthy lords, have you with heed perused</LINE>
<LINE>What I have written to you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Lords</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We have.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Lord</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And grieve to hear't.</LINE>
<LINE>What faults he made before the last, I think</LINE>
<LINE>Might have found easy fines: but there to end</LINE>
<LINE>Where he was to begin and give away</LINE>
<LINE>The benefit of our levies, answering us</LINE>
<LINE>With our own charge, making a treaty where</LINE>
<LINE>There was a yielding,--this admits no excuse.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He approaches: you shall hear him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Enter CORIOLANUS, marching with drum and
colours; commoners being with him</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hail, lords! I am return'd your soldier,</LINE>
<LINE>No more infected with my country's love</LINE>
<LINE>Than when I parted hence, but still subsisting</LINE>
<LINE>Under your great command. You are to know</LINE>
<LINE>That prosperously I have attempted and</LINE>
<LINE>With bloody passage led your wars even to</LINE>
<LINE>The gates of Rome. Our spoils we have brought home</LINE>
<LINE>Do more than counterpoise a full third part</LINE>
<LINE>The charges of the action. We have made peace</LINE>
<LINE>With no less honour to the Antiates</LINE>
<LINE>Than shame to the Romans: and we here deliver,</LINE>
<LINE>Subscribed by the consuls and patricians,</LINE>
<LINE>Together with the seal o' the senate, what</LINE>
<LINE>We have compounded on.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Read it not, noble lords;</LINE>
<LINE>But tell the traitor, in the high'st degree</LINE>
<LINE>He hath abused your powers.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Traitor! how now!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, traitor, Marcius!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Marcius!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, Marcius, Caius Marcius: dost thou think</LINE>
<LINE>I'll grace thee with that robbery, thy stol'n name</LINE>
<LINE>Coriolanus in Corioli?</LINE>
<LINE>You lords and heads o' the state, perfidiously</LINE>
<LINE>He has betray'd your business, and given up,</LINE>
<LINE>For certain drops of salt, your city Rome,</LINE>
<LINE>I say 'your city,' to his wife and mother;</LINE>
<LINE>Breaking his oath and resolution like</LINE>
<LINE>A twist of rotten silk, never admitting</LINE>
<LINE>Counsel o' the war, but at his nurse's tears</LINE>
<LINE>He whined and roar'd away your victory,</LINE>
<LINE>That pages blush'd at him and men of heart</LINE>
<LINE>Look'd wondering each at other.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hear'st thou, Mars?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Name not the god, thou boy of tears!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ha!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No more.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Measureless liar, thou hast made my heart</LINE>
<LINE>Too great for what contains it. Boy! O slave!</LINE>
<LINE>Pardon me, lords, 'tis the first time that ever</LINE>
<LINE>I was forced to scold. Your judgments, my grave lords,</LINE>
<LINE>Must give this cur the lie: and his own notion--</LINE>
<LINE>Who wears my stripes impress'd upon him; that</LINE>
<LINE>Must bear my beating to his grave--shall join</LINE>
<LINE>To thrust the lie unto him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Lord</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Peace, both, and hear me speak.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Cut me to pieces, Volsces; men and lads,</LINE>
<LINE>Stain all your edges on me. Boy! false hound!</LINE>
<LINE>If you have writ your annals true, 'tis there,</LINE>
<LINE>That, like an eagle in a dove-cote, I</LINE>
<LINE>Flutter'd your Volscians in Corioli:</LINE>
<LINE>Alone I did it. Boy!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, noble lords,</LINE>
<LINE>Will you be put in mind of his blind fortune,</LINE>
<LINE>Which was your shame, by this unholy braggart,</LINE>
<LINE>'Fore your own eyes and ears?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>All Conspirators</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let him die for't.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>All The People</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tear him to pieces.' 'Do it presently.' 'He kill'd</LINE>
<LINE>my son.' 'My daughter.' 'He killed my cousin</LINE>
<LINE>Marcus.' 'He killed my father.'</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Lord</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Peace, ho! no outrage: peace!</LINE>
<LINE>The man is noble and his fame folds-in</LINE>
<LINE>This orb o' the earth. His last offences to us</LINE>
<LINE>Shall have judicious hearing. Stand, Aufidius,</LINE>
<LINE>And trouble not the peace.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CORIOLANUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O that I had him,</LINE>
<LINE>With six Aufidiuses, or more, his tribe,</LINE>
<LINE>To use my lawful sword!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Insolent villain!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>All Conspirators</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Kill, kill, kill, kill, kill him!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>The Conspirators draw, and kill CORIOLANUS:
AUFIDIUS stands on his body</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Lords</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hold, hold, hold, hold!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My noble masters, hear me speak.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Lord</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O Tullus,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Lord</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thou hast done a deed whereat valour will weep.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Lord</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Tread not upon him. Masters all, be quiet;</LINE>
<LINE>Put up your swords.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lords, when you shall know--as in this rage,</LINE>
<LINE>Provoked by him, you cannot--the great danger</LINE>
<LINE>Which this man's life did owe you, you'll rejoice</LINE>
<LINE>That he is thus cut off. Please it your honours</LINE>
<LINE>To call me to your senate, I'll deliver</LINE>
<LINE>Myself your loyal servant, or endure</LINE>
<LINE>Your heaviest censure.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Lord</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Bear from hence his body;</LINE>
<LINE>And mourn you for him: let him be regarded</LINE>
<LINE>As the most noble corse that ever herald</LINE>
<LINE>Did follow to his urn.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Lord</SPEAKER>
<LINE>His own impatience</LINE>
<LINE>Takes from Aufidius a great part of blame.</LINE>
<LINE>Let's make the best of it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>AUFIDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My rage is gone;</LINE>
<LINE>And I am struck with sorrow. Take him up.</LINE>
<LINE>Help, three o' the chiefest soldiers; I'll be one.</LINE>
<LINE>Beat thou the drum, that it speak mournfully:</LINE>
<LINE>Trail your steel pikes. Though in this city he</LINE>
<LINE>Hath widow'd and unchilded many a one,</LINE>
<LINE>Which to this hour bewail the injury,</LINE>
<LINE>Yet he shall have a noble memory. Assist.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt, bearing the body of CORIOLANUS. A dead
march sounded</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>
</ACT>
</PLAY>
