<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../documentation.dtd">
<section>
  <title>Utilities</title>

  <para>The NOF provides a number of utilities for helping to create a naked
  objects system ranging from about objects and splash screens, to logging and
  debugging utilities.</para>

  <subheading>About</subheading>

  <para>The NOF provides a static class <class>AboutNakedObjects</class> in
  the <path>org.nakedobjects.utility</path> package that is used by the
  famework, and can be used elsewhere, to display information about the
  framework and the application being run. This includes titles, versions and
  copyright messages. The details about the framework are hard code when the
  framework is build, but details about the application can be set at
  runtime.</para>

  <block>
    <label><method>setApplicationName(String) </method></label>

    <para>Allows you to programmatically specify the application name for your
    application.</para>
  </block>

  <block>
    <label><method>setApplicationCopyrightNotice(String)</method></label>

    <para>Allows you to programmatically specify a copyright notice for your
    application.</para>
  </block>

  <block>
    <label><method>setApplicationVersion(String)</method></label>

    <para>Allows you to programmatically specify the version.</para>
  </block>

  <para>These details and details about the framework can be accessed using
  the static accessors.</para>

  <subheading>Splash window</subheading>

  <para>The splah window uses Java AWT components to render a splash window
  displaying an logo graphic and details about the application and framework
  in the following order: application name, copyright and version; framework
  name, copyright, version and build number. The image is loaded from the
  <path>images</path> directory using a default file name of
  <path>logo.jpg</path>. The splash window is brought up by instantiating an
  instance of <class>org.nakedobjects.utility.SplashWindow</class> and is
  removed using the <method>removeImmediately</method> and
  <method>removeAfterDelay</method> methods. The parameter for delaying
  version is the number of seconds it should remain on the screen for.</para>
</section>