<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.1//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.1/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title></title>

    <author>
      <firstname></firstname>

      <surname></surname>

      <affiliation>
        <orgname></orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

    <pubdate></pubdate>
  </articleinfo>

  <section>
    <title>Submitting patches</title>

    <para>Patches for bug fixes, improvements and extension are welcomed and
    sought by the [[NAME]] development team. The process is simple: get
    the latest code; make your changes; create a patch file; and email it to
    us. As most development is done within the Eclipse IDE that is the best
    place to create the patches, although patches created in other ways (as
    long as they following the standard structure) are fine too. We will look
    at using both Eclipse and Subversion here.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Getting the latest code</title>

      <para>It is important that you make changes against the latest version
      of the development code so that it easier merge. Code that is easier to
      merge gets incorporated more quickly.</para>

      <para>The latest version of the source can be checked out of the
      Subversion repository using the following command:</para>

      <literallayout>$ svn co http://apache.isis.svn/svnroot/trunk isis</literallayout>

      <para>or, assuming you have already checked it out, then ensure that it
      up-to-date:</para>

      <literallayout>$ cd isis
$ svn up</literallayout>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Changing the code</title>

      <para>Make the changes to your local copy ensuring that you use the same
      coding style and formatting (see <ulink
      url="http://isis.apache.org/framework.html">code style</ulink> for
      details and for the location of the Eclipse settings to assist
      you).</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Creating the patch</title>

      <para>A patch is just a special file that details what files are
      affected and what the changes are. This way a set of related changes can
      be grouped together and the size of the file is minimal.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Creating from within Eclipse</title>

        <para>Creating a patch from within Eclipse can be done easily, but
        only if you are have one of the Subversion plug-ins installed and the
        project is shared (see the <option>Team/Share...</option>
        option).</para>

        <para>From within Eclipse open up the contextual menu (right-click) on
        the file, package or project that has been changed and select the
        <option>Team/Create Patch...</option> option. In the dialog (shown
        below) that comes up specify a <emphasis
        role="strong">descriptive</emphasis> file name and confirm that all
        the files that are checked are the ones that you want to submit. Press
        the <option>Finish</option> button to create the patch file.</para>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/create-patch-dialog.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Creating using Subversion</title>

        <para>Subversion's <command>diff</command> command will do a similar
        thing, but of course you need to use the command line. (You can also
        use other Subversion clients, such as Tortoise, but you need to find
        out which menu items correspond to the diff command). Use the
        following command with a specific project (as shown here), package or
        file identified to create the patch and redirect the output to a file.
        Here we are creating a patch for the whole of the runtime project and
        placing it in the file <filename>fixture-patch.txt</filename>.</para>

        <literallayout>$ svn diff core/runtime &gt; fixture-patch.txt</literallayout>

        <para>NOTE - when using Subversion's diff command only those files
        that are under Subversion's control are included. Specifically new
        files are not part of that set until they have been added (using
        <literal>svn add</literal>). So to submit new files either add them
        with the appropriate <literal>svn</literal> command or submit them
        separately.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>An example file</title>

        <para>The result of this is a file like this (which has been truncated
        to save space):</para>

        <literallayout>Index: /home/rcm/no-development/workspace_DEV_4.0/isis/core/runtime/src/main/java/org/apache/isis/runtime/fixture/ObjectFixtureService.java
===================================================================
--- /home/rcm/no-development/workspace_DEV_4.0/isis/core/runtime/src/main/java/org/apache/isis/runtime/fixture/ObjectFixtureService.java	(revision 14471)
+++ /home/rcm/no-development/workspace_DEV_4.0/isis/core/runtime/src/main/java/org/apache/isis/runtime/fixture/ObjectFixtureService.java	(working copy)
@@ -2,10 +2,12 @@
 
 import java.io.BufferedReader;
 import java.io.File;
+import java.io.FileNotFoundException;
 import java.io.FileReader;
 import java.io.FileWriter;
 import java.io.IOException;
 import java.io.PrintWriter;
+import java.io.Reader;
 import java.util.HashMap;
 import java.util.HashSet;
 import java.util.Map;
@@ -28,6 +30,7 @@
 import org.apache.isis.metamodel.spec.feature.OneToOneAssociation;
 import org.apache.isis.metamodel.util.CollectionFacetUtils;
 import org.apache.isis.runtime.context.IsisContext;
+import org.apache.isis.runtime.fixturesinstaller.FixtureException;
 
 
 public class ObjectFixtureService {
@@ -55,6 +58,9 @@
 
         public ObjectAdapter get(String data) {
             int pos = data.indexOf('#');
+            if (pos == -1) {
+                throw new FixtureException("read failed - object spec: " + data);
+            }
             String id = data.substring(pos + 1);
             ObjectAdapter object = idMap.get(id);
             if (object == null) {</literallayout>

        <para>This was produced using Subversion. The file produced by Eclipse
        is the same except it has a couple of comments at the top, one of
        which indicates which project the changes come from.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Submitting the patch</title>

      <para>Now simply email the patch to us. The email address is <ulink
      url="mailto:patches@isis.apache.org">patches@isis.apache.org</ulink>.
      The subject line should start with the text <emphasis
      role="strong">PATCH:</emphasis> so that they are not picked out as Spam.
      Attach the files to the email and in the body explain what the patch is
      for and what changes it makes. This will help the developers assess the
      patches and apply them quickly. Please also ensure your email address is
      correct so that we can contact you if necessary.</para>

      <para>When we receive a patch we will load it up using Eclipse and can
      immediately see what changes will be made. After checking the changes
      they will be applied to the code and checked in. If you have requested a
      response we will then email you to let you know what change has been
      applied.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>
